<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Docbook XML V.4.3//EN"
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
	  <!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
	  %globalent;
	  <!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
	  %gnome-menus-C;
	  <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
	  %xinclude;
	  <!ENTITY language "en">
	  <!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
	  ]>
	  <?db.chunk.max_depth 4?>
<?yelp:chunk-depth 4?>
<chapter id="music" status="review">
	<title>Music</title>
	<para>This section describes how to import, organize and use music, videos and 
    photos with Ubuntu.</para>
    <sect1 id="music-listen" status="review">
        <title>Listen</title>
        <para>
        You can use <application>Rhythmbox</application> (&rhythmbox;) 
        and <application>Movie Player</application> (&totem;) to listen 
        to music on your computer.</para>
        <para>Audio files will be opened in Movie Player when 
        double-clicked but Rhythmbox is better at handling large music 
        collections.</para>
        <para>Rhythmbox is also able to play audio CDs and work with MP3
        players. It should open automatically when you insert a CD.</para>
        <para>See the <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:rhythmbox'>
        Rhythmbox manual</ulink> for more information.</para>
        <sect2 id="music-cd-autoplay" status="review">
			<title>How can I prevent CDs from playing when I insert them?</title>
			<para>Rhythmbox should start playing a CD automatically when you insert it 
			into your CD drive.</para>
			<para>To prevent this from happening, open your Home folder by clicking 
			&home-folder; on the panel at the top of the screen. Then, click 
			<menuchoice>
				<guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem>
				<guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
				<guimenuitem>Media</guimenuitem>
			</menuchoice> and change the <guilabel>CD Audio</guilabel> option to 
			<guilabel>Do Nothing</guilabel>. Finally, press <guibutton>Close</guibutton>.
			</para>
			<para>See the <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:user-guide#nautilus-preferences'>
			Nautilus Preferences article</ulink> for more information.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="music-missingmetadata" status="review">
			<title>Song names/cover art are missing/wrong for some songs</title>
			<para>Music player applications fetch cover art and other information about 
			songs from the Internet. If song names or cover art are missing, make 
			sure that you are connected to the Internet.</para>
			<para>Sometimes, your music player may not be able to identify a particular 
			song or album correctly. If this is the case, you can add the correct 
			information manually by using a tag editor such as 
			<ulink url="apt:cowbell">Cowbell</ulink> or 
			<ulink url="apt:easytag-aac">EasyTAG</ulink>. 
			Some music players even have their own tag editor.</para>
			<para><emphasis role='strong'>If only the album cover art is missing for an album:</emphasis>
			</para>
			<procedure>
				<step><para>Find a picture of the album cover on the Internet. 
				<ulink url="http://www.amazon.com/">Amazon</ulink> 
				and other music retailers often display pictures of the album 
				cover; right-click it and click <guibutton>Save Image As</guibutton> 
				to save it to your computer.</para></step>
				<step><para>Rename the picture to <filename>cover.jpg</filename> 
				and copy it into the folder which contains the songs from the album.</para></step>
				<step><para>Rhythmbox and most other music players should display the correct 
				cover art when a song from the album is next played.</para></step>
			</procedure>
			<para>Rhythmbox and some other music players allow you to drag a picture onto 
			their cover art display area to change or add cover art for an album.</para>
		</sect2>
    </sect1>
	<sect1 id="music-extract" status="review">
        <title>Extract from a CD</title>
        <para>You can extract music from a CD to your computer so that you do not have 
        to have the CD in the drive to play songs from it. You can then copy 
        the songs to a digital audio player, such as an MP3 player.</para>
        <note>
        	<para>Rhythmbox stores extracted files in the Music folder (&music;).</para>
        </note>
        <procedure>
        	<step><para>Insert an Audio CD.</para></step>
        	<step><para>You will be prompted to choose which application to launch, 
        	choose <guilabel>Open Rhythmbox Music Player</guilabel>.</para></step>
        	<step><para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para></step>
        	<step><para>In the left hand pane, under <guilabel>Devices</guilabel>, right click
        	the CD name you want to extract.</para></step>
        	<step><para>Click <guibutton>Extract to Library</guibutton>.</para></step>
        </procedure>
        <para>You can change the default file format used by Rhythmbox when copying 
        CDs. Click 
        <menuchoice>
            <guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem>
            <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
            <guimenuitem>Music</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice> 
        and change the <guilabel>Preferred Format</guilabel> to the format of 
        your choice. In future, all CDs copied to your computer will be copied 
        in this format.
        </para>
        <note>
            <para>
            If an MP3 option is not shown in the <guilabel>Preferred Format
            </guilabel> list, <ulink url='apt:gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly-multiverse'>install the 
            <application>gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly-multiverse</application> package</ulink> and restart 
            Rhythmbox. The option <guilabel>CD Quality, MP3 (.mp3 type)
            </guilabel> should appear in the <guilabel>Preferred Format
            </guilabel> list.
            </para>
        </note>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="music-burn" status="review">
        <title>Copy to a CD</title>
        <para>
        You can create your own audio CDs by copying music from your computer 
        onto a blank disc. CDs that you create in this way should play in any 
        device that can play standard (manufactured) audio CDs. All that is 
        required is a CD burner (also called a CD writer). Most computers have 
        one of these.
        </para>
        <para>
        To begin creating an audio CD, start Brasero (&brasero;) and select 
        <guibutton>Audio project</guibutton> from the main screen. Then, select 
        the songs that you want to add to the CD and add them to the project. 
        Finally, click <guibutton>Burn</guibutton> to copy the songs to a CD.
        </para>
        <para>
        You will also need to select the maximum duration of the CD which you 
        inserted (e.g. 80 minutes), which can be done by clicking on the small 
        CD icon near the bottom of the window. Brasero will warn you if you 
        have selected more files than can fit on the disc.
        </para>
        <para>
        See the <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:brasero'>
        Brasero manual</ulink> for full instructions.
        </para>
    </sect1>
   <sect1 id="music-portable" status="review">
        <title>Portable music players</title>
        <para>
        Ubuntu will work with most portable audio players, including iPods. 
        Normally, all you have to do is plug the player into your computer and 
        then use Rhythmbox to copy songs to and from the player. The audio 
        player should appear in the <guilabel>Devices</guilabel> section of the 
        list which is underneath the <guibutton>Play</guibutton> button.
        See the 
        <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:rhythmbox'>Rhythmbox manual</ulink> for 
        more information.
        </para>
        <sect2 id="music-portable-ipod" status="review">
        	<title>iPod</title>
			<para>
			If you have a portable music player which can also display photos and 
			videos, you may prefer to use <ulink url="apt:banshee">Banshee</ulink>, 
			which is a music player with good support for such devices. 
			iPod owners may also like to try specialized applications such as 
			<ulink url="apt:gpixpod">GPixPod</ulink> and 
			<ulink url="apt:gtkpod">gtkpod</ulink> for handling multimedia.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="music-portable-mtp" status="review">
			<title>MTP Media Players</title>
			<para>A number of MP3 players, such as those produced by Samsung use 
			Media Transfer Protocol(MTP). These devices, when used with the correct
			driver, often appear in Windows as a media device but can be accessed as a USB
			device.</para>
			<para>Ubuntu supports these devices but requires two steps:</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Install the <ulink url="apt:mtpfs"><application>mtpfs</application></ulink> 
				and <ulink url="apt:mtpfs"><application>mtp-tools</application></ulink> packages.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Open &rhythmbox;.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu><guimenuitem>Plugins</guimenuitem></menuchoice></para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Tick the <guilabel>Portable Players - MTP</guilabel> plugin.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click <guibutton>Close</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para>Your device will now be displayed in the left hand pane under <guilabel>Devices</guilabel> 
			when connected.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="music-convert" status="review">
		<title>Converting audio files</title>
		<para>When you extract music from a CD onto a computer, it must be stored in a 
		specific <emphasis>audio format</emphasis>. The default format used by 
		Rhythmbox is Ogg Vorbis (<filename>.ogg</filename> or 
		<filename>.oga</filename>). This is explained in <xref linkend="music-extract" />.
		</para>
		<para>
		Not all portable audio players are able to play files in the Ogg Vorbis 
		format; for example, iPods cannot play this format. In order for your 
		player to recognize your songs, you must convert them to a format which 
		it supports. Nearly every player on the market supports the MP3 format, 
		so this is usually a safe bet.
		</para>
		<para>
		You can convert existing audio files to other formats using 
		<ulink url="apt:soundconverter">Sound Converter</ulink>. The output 
		format can be selected in the Sound Converter preferences.
		</para>
		<para>
		You can change the default file format used by Rhythmbox when copying 
		CDs. Click 
		<menuchoice>
			<guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem>
			<guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
			<guimenuitem>Music</guimenuitem>
		</menuchoice> 
		and change the <guilabel>Preferred Format</guilabel> to the format of 
		your choice. In future, all CDs copied to your computer will be copied 
		in this format.
		</para>
		<note>
			<para>
			If an MP3 option is not shown in the <guilabel>Preferred Format
			</guilabel> list, <ulink url='apt:gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly-multiverse'>install the 
			<application>gstreamer0.10-plugins-ugly-multiverse</application> package</ulink> and restart 
			Rhythmbox. The option <guilabel>CD Quality, MP3 (.mp3 type)
			</guilabel> should appear in the <guilabel>Preferred Format
			</guilabel> list.
			</para>
		</note>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="music-podcasts" status="review">
        <title>Podcasts and Internet radio stations</title>
        <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Podcasts</emphasis> are pre-recorded shows 
        which you can download and listen to on your computer or portable audio 
        player. Thousands of podcasts are available and most can be downloaded 
        for free.
        </para>
        <para>
        You can use Rhythmbox to download and play podcasts; select 
        <guilabel>Podcasts</guilabel> from the <guilabel>Library</guilabel> 
        section of the Rhythmbox window to get started. The 
        <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:rhythmbox'>Rhythmbox manual</ulink> has 
        further instructions. Alternatively, you may prefer to use a dedicated 
        podcast manager such as <ulink url="apt:gpodder">gPodder</ulink> or 
        <ulink url="apt:penguintv">PenguinTV</ulink>.
        </para>
        <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Internet radio stations</emphasis> are live 
        <emphasis>audio streams</emphasis>, similar to standard radio but 
        transmitted over the Internet. You can use Rhythmbox to listen to 
        Internet radio too; select <guilabel>Radio</guilabel> from the 
        <guilabel>Library</guilabel> section of the Rhythmbox window to get 
        started and see the 
        <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:rhythmbox'>Rhythmbox manual</ulink> for 
        more details.
        </para>
        <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>RealAudio streams</emphasis>, as used by some 
        Internet radio stations, are not supported by Rhythmbox. To listen to 
        this type of stream, <link linkend="video-realplayer">
        install RealPlayer</link>.
        </para>
    </sect1>
    
    <sect1 id="music-download" status="review">
        <title>Download music from the Internet</title>
        <para>
        Many websites which allow you to buy music online and download it onto 
        your computer are designed to work with Microsoft Windows only. As a 
        result, some services will not work with Ubuntu.
        </para>
        <para>
        Ubuntu is able to play most audio formats, including MP3, WMA and AAC. 
        However, it does not support the various DRM (Digital Rights 
        Management) schemes which stores sometimes use to restrict access to 
        their music. If you download audio files which are DRM-restricted, they 
        are unlikely to work in Ubuntu. In particular, nearly all music from 
        the iTunes music store is DRM-restricted and so cannot be played.
        </para>
        <para>
        Two services which offer unrestricted (DRM-free) music are 
        <ulink url="http://www.jamendo.com">Jamendo</ulink> and 
        <ulink url="">Magnatune</ulink>. You can buy songs from both of these 
        stores online, or directly from within Rhythmbox if the appropriate 
        plugins are enabled (see the <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:rhythmbox'>
        Rhythmbox manual</ulink> for more information).
        </para>
        <caution>
            <para>
            Downloading music from the Internet without the permission of its 
            copyright holder is considered illegal in many countries. You 
            should check that you are within your rights to download a music 
            file before saving it onto your computer.
            </para>
        </caution>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 id="music-recording" status="review">
        <title>Recording sounds</title>
        <para>
        You can record sounds onto your computer if you have a microphone or 
        other recording equipment connected to it.
        </para>
        <para>
        To start a basic sound recording application, press 
        <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo>, 
        type <userinput>gnome-sound-recorder</userinput> into the text box and 
        then click <guibutton>Run</guibutton>. See the 
        <ulink type='help' url="ghelp:gnome-sound-recorder">
        Sound Recorder manual</ulink> for instructions on how to use it.
        </para>
        <para>
        For more advanced recording needs, you may like to try a multi-track 
        audio editor such as 
        <ulink url="apt:jokosher">Jokosher</ulink> or 
        <ulink url="apt:audacity">Audacity</ulink>.
        </para>
        <para>
        Many other professional-level recording tools are available for Ubuntu. 
        See the <ulink url="http://ubuntustudio.org/">
        Ubuntu Studio website</ulink> for more information.
        </para>
	</sect1>
    <sect1 id="music-microphone" status="review">
        <title>My microphone does not work or is too quiet</title>
        <para>
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role='strong'>
                    Check that the microphone is connected to the correct socket
                    </emphasis>
                </para>
                <para>
                Most computers have three or more similar-looking audio 
                sockets, so you should check that the microphone is plugged 
                into the correct one. It is usually colored pink and has a 
                microphone icon next to it.
                </para>
                <para>
                In some rare cases, sockets do not work as labeled. For 
                example, your microphone socket may act as the 
                <quote>Line Out</quote> socket and vice versa. If this is the 
                case, use trial and error to find the correct microphone socket.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role='strong'>
                    Check that the microphone is not muted in the settings
                    </emphasis>
                </para>
                <para>
                The microphone input may have been muted or its volume reduced 
                in the system settings.
                </para>
                <procedure>
                    <step>
                    <para>
                    Right-click the speaker icon on the panel at the top of 
                    your screen and select 
                    <guilabel>Open Volume Control</guilabel>. If you do not 
                    have a speaker icon on your panel, press 
                    <keycombo>
                        <keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap>
                    </keycombo>, type 
                    <userinput>gnome-volume-control</userinput> and click 
                    <guibutton>Run</guibutton> instead.
                    </para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                    <para>
                    When the Volume Control opens, click 
                    <guibutton>Preferences</guibutton>
                    and make sure that all of the items related to the 
                    microphone settings are checked. Click 
                    <guibutton>Close</guibutton> to return to the volume 
                    control.
                    </para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                    <para>
                    Under the <guilabel>Playback</guilabel> tab, make sure that 
                    all of the microphone settings are unmuted and that their 
                    volume is set high enough. If a microphone is muted, a 
                    speaker icon with a red cross over it will be displayed 
                    underneath its volume slider; click that icon to unmute the 
                    microphone.
                    </para>
                    </step>
                    <step>
                    <para>
                    You may also find it necessary to change other settings to 
                    get your microphone to work properly. For example, the 
                    <guilabel>Mic Boost</guilabel> and 
                    <guilabel>External Amplifier</guilabel> settings under the 
                    <guilabel>Switches</guilabel> tab and the 
                    <guilabel>Mic Select</guilabel> setting under the 
                    <guilabel>Options</guilabel> tab can all affect the volume 
                    of your microphone.
                    </para>
                    </step>
                </procedure>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role='strong'>
                    Check the volume control on the microphone
                    </emphasis>
                </para>
                <para>
                Some microphones have an integrated volume control. Check that 
                the volume control on your microphone is turned up.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role='strong'>
                    Check the volume control in the recording application
                    </emphasis>
                </para>
                <para>
                Some applications allow you to change the volume of the 
                microphone from within the application. Check the volume 
                settings in the application that you are using.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
