<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<article id="desktop-effects" status="review">
	<articleinfo>
		<title>Visual Effects</title>
    	&legalnotice;
	</articleinfo>
	
<sect1 id="compiz-intro" status="review">
	<title>What are visual effects?</title>
	<para>
	Ubuntu includes special visual effects which are intended to make your 
	desktop more fun and easier to use. These include translucent windows, 
	3D desktop capabilities, shadow effects, motion effects and animations.
    </para>
	<para>
	Visual effects are enabled by default, but it is not necessary to have them 
	turned on.
	</para>
	<para>
	If visual effects are not enabled, your graphics card may not support them. 
	Try <link linkend="compiz-configure">turning them on manually</link> to 
	check if this is the case.
	</para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="compiz-configure" status="review">
	<title>Configuring visual effects</title>
	<para>
	Press &desktop-effects; to change basic options relating to visual effects.
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
    	<para>
    	Select <guilabel>None</guilabel> to provide a simple desktop 
    	environment without any effects.
    	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
    	<para>
    	Select <guilabel>Normal</guilabel> to provide a good balance between 
    	attractiveness and performance.
    	</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
    	<para>
    	Select <guilabel>Extra</guilabel> to provide an aesthetically pleasing 
    	set of graphics.
    	</para>
	</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
	<para>
	When you select an option, it may take several seconds for the change to be 
	applied. During this time, your screen may flicker briefly.
	</para>
	<para>
	Once the settings have been applied, a dialog box will appear asking you to 
	either keep the new settings or to revert to your previous settings. If you 
	find that the new settings work correctly, then click 
	<guibutton>Keep Settings</guibutton>. Otherwise click 
	<guibutton>Use Previous Settings</guibutton>. If you do not select anything 
	for 20 seconds the system will return to your previous settings.
	</para>
</sect1>
	<sect1 id="compiz-default-plugins" status="review">
		<title>Using keyboard shortcuts with visual effects </title>
		<para>Ubuntu includes extra <application>Compiz</application> plugins which provide extra functionality with certain keyboard combinations. Examples of these plugins are Application Switcher, Expo and Scale.</para>
		<para>These extra plugins are explained in this section.</para>
		<note><para> Some commands use the <keycap>Super</keycap> key, which is the Windows key on many keyboards.</para></note>
		<sect2 id="application-switcher" status="review">		
		<title>Application Switcher </title>
		<para>The Application Switcher provides the same functionality as the traditional Gnome and KDE Alt+Tab switcher, but uses live window thumbnails to show its previews. You can use the Application Switcher to switch between windows of different contexts with different keybindings.</para>
			 <itemizedlist>					
				<listitem>
				<para>To flip to the next window, press <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo> </para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>	
				<para> To flip to the previous window, press <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo></para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para>To flip to the next window in all workspaces, press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo></para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para> To flip to the previous window in all workspaces, press <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo></para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="desktop-wall" status="review">
		<title>Desktop Wall </title>
		<para>The Desktop Wall is a lightweight alternative to the Desktop Cube plugin. It is used to change workspaces, has support for workspace previews and can use workspaces on the horizonal plane and the vertical plane. The Expo plugin works well with the Desktop Wall plugin.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>				
			<para>To navigate in the Desktop Wall, press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo> with Up, Down, Left, or Right.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para> To navigate in the Desktop Wall with a window, press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo> with Up, Down, Left, or Right.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="enhanced-zoom-desktop" status="review">
		<title>Enhanced Zoom Desktop</title>
		<para>The Enhanced Zoom Desktop plugin allows the whole screen to be zoomed in for improved legibility. It is possible to continue working with other applications while zoomed in.</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
			<para>To center the mouse on the screen, press <keycombo><keycap>Super</keycap><keycap>C</keycap></keycombo></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para>To lock the the zoom area (field of view) so it will not move to follow the mouse cursor, use  <keycombo><keycap>Super</keycap><keycap>1.</keycap></keycombo></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para>To resize the  focused window so that it fills the field of view, press <keycombo><keycap>Super</keycap><keycap>v.</keycap></keycombo></para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			<para> To adjust the zoom level so that the window fills the field of view, press <keycombo><keycap>Super</keycap><keycap>r.</keycap></keycombo></para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="expo" status="review">
		<title>Expo</title>
		<para>By default, Expo is activated by moving the mouse cursor to the top-left corner of the screen, or by pressing <keycombo><keycap>Super</keycap><keycap>E.</keycap></keycombo> This causes the viewport to zoom out until all viewports are scaled and visible on-screen in a grid formation, complete with all open windows.</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="negative" status="review">
		<title>Negative</title>
		<para>The Negative plugin provides immediate, high-contrast windows for the visually impaired by inverting the colors of individual windows, or all windows at once.</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
				<para>To enable or disable Negative on the focused window, press<keycombo><keycap>Super</keycap><keycap>n.</keycap></keycombo></para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para>To enable or disable Negative on the screen, press <keycombo><keycap>Super</keycap><keycap>m.</keycap></keycombo></para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="viewport-switcher" status="review">
		<title>Viewport Switcher</title>
		<para>The Viewport Switcher is used to switch <ulink type='help' url='ghelp:user-guide#overview-workspaces'>workspaces</ulink>
via different keystrokes and buttons. You can use it with the middle mouse button on the desktop and by pressing a keybinding and selecting a workspace number.</para> 
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
				<para>To move to the next workspace, press Button5 (Scroll up)</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
				<para>To move to the previous workspace, press Button4 (Scroll down)</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

<sect1 id="compiz-configure-advanced" status="review">
	<title>Enabling extra effects</title>
	<para>As well as the visual effects which are available by default, many 
	additional effects are available. These range from effects intended to make 
	it easier to use your computer, to ones which are just for fun.
	</para>
	<para>
	To enable additional effects:
	</para>
	<procedure>
	<step>
		<para>
		<ulink url="apt:compizconfig-settings-manager">Install the
		Advanced Desktop Effects Settings application</ulink>.
		</para>
	</step>
	<step>
		<para>
		Click &compizconfig;.
		</para>
	</step>
	<step>
		<para>
		Check the box next to an effect to enable it.
		</para>
	</step>
	<step>
		<para>
		Click on an effect to change its settings.
		</para>
	</step>
	</procedure>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="compiz-problems" status="review">
	<title>Common problems</title>
	<para>
	If you experience problems when using visual effects, it is advisable to 
	disable them by opening &desktop-effects; and selecting 
	<guilabel>None</guilabel>.
	</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
		<para>
		If you receive an error message saying that 
		<quote>Visual effects could not be enabled</quote>, it is likely that 
		your graphics driver does not currently support visual effects.
		</para>
		<para>
		In this case, you will not be able to use visual effects with your 
		default graphics driver. However, you may be able to use a 
		<ulink type='help' url='ghelp:hardware#restricted-manager'>restricted 
		driver</ulink> instead.
		</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
		<para>
		If your computer runs slowly, disabling visual effects may improve 
		performance. Visual effects require more system resources, and so older 
		or less powerful computers may not be able to cope with the extra load.
		</para>
	</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="compiz-moreinfo" status="review">
	<title>Further information</title>
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
        <para>
        See the <ulink url='http://wiki.compiz-fusion.org/'>Compiz-Fusion 
        documentation website</ulink> for more information on advanced 
        configuration of visual effects.
        </para>
	</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</sect1>

</article>
