<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
<!ENTITY appversion "0.2.4">
<!ENTITY app "<application>User Switcher</application>">
<!ENTITY appname "User Switcher">
]>
<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Maintained by the GNOME Documentation Project
  http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp
  Template version: 2.0 beta
  Template last modified Feb 12, 2002
-->
<article id="index" lang="pa">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ ਐਪਲਿਟ</title>
    <copyright>
      <year>2005</year>
      <holder>ਜੋਸਫ ਪਿੰਗਨੋਟ</holder>
    </copyright>
    <copyright>
      <year>2005</year>
      <holder>ਜੇਮਜ਼ ਐਮ ਕੇਪੀ</holder>
    </copyright>

<!-- translators: uncomment this:

    <copyright>
      <year>2002</year>
      <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
    </copyright>

   -->

    <publisher>
      <publishername>ਗਨੋਮ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ ਪਰੋਜੈੱਕਟ</publishername>
    </publisher>

      <legalnotice id="legalnotice">
	<para>ਇਹ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ ਨੂੰ ਗਨੂ ਮੁਕਤ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ ਲਾਈਸੈਂਸ (GFDL), ਵਰਜਨ 1.1 ਜਾਂ ਨਵੇਂ, ਜੋ ਕਿ ਫਰੀ ਸਾਫਟਵੇਅਰ ਫਾਊਡੇਸ਼ਨ ਵਲੋਂ ਬਦਲਵੇਂ ਭਾਗ, ਨਾ ਮੁੱਢਲੇ-ਢੱਕਣ ਪਾਠ ਅਤੇ ਨਾ ਹੀ ਪਿੱਛੇ-ਢੱਕਣ ਪਾਠ ਨਾਲ ਜਾਰੀ ਹੈ, ਦੀਆਂ ਸ਼ਰਤਾਂ ਅਧੀਨ ਨਕਲ ਕਰਨ, ਵੰਡਣ ਅਤੇ/ਜਾਂ ਸੋਧਣ ਦਾ ਅਧਿਕਾਰ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਗਿਆ ਹੈ। ਤੁਸੀਂ GFDL ਦੀ ਨਕਲ <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:fdl"> ਸਬੰਧ</ulink> ਉੱਤੇ ਜਾਂ ਇਹ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ 'ਚ COPYING-DOCS ਫਾਇਲ ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਲੈ ਸਕਦੇ ਹੋ।</para>
         <para>ਇਹ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ GFDL ਹੇਠ ਵੰਡੇ ਜਾ ਰਹੇ ਗਨੋਮ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ਾਂ ਦਾ ਭਾਗ ਹੈ। ਜੇਕਰ ਤੁਸੀਂ ਇਸ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ ਨੂੰ ਇਸ ਭੰਡਾਰ ਤੋਂ ਅੱਡ ਵੰਡਣਾ ਚਾਹੁੰਦੇ ਹੋ ਤਾਂ ਤੁਸੀਂ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ ਵਿੱਚ ਲਾਇਸੈਂਸ ਦੇ ਭਾਗ 6 ਵਿੱਚ ਦਿੱਤੇ ਵਾਂਗ ਇੱਕ ਨਕਲ ਰੱਖ ਕੇ ਕਰ ਸਕਦੇ ਹੋ।</para>

	<para>ਕੰਪਨੀਆਂ ਵਲੋਂ ਆਪਣੇ ਉਤਪਾਦਾਂ ਅਤੇ ਸੇਵਾਵਾਂ ਲਈ ਵਰਤੇ ਗਏ ਕਈ ਨਾਂ ਮਾਰਕੇ ਹਨ। ਜਦੋਂ ਵੀ ਉਹ ਨਾਂ ਕਿਸੇ ਗਨੋਮ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ ਪ੍ਰੋਜੈਕਟ ਵਿੱਚ ਆਉਦੇ ਹਨ ਅਤੇ ਗਨੋਮ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ ਪ੍ਰੋਜੈਕਟ ਦੇ ਮੈਂਬਰ ਹਨ ਤਾਂ ਉਨ੍ਹਾਂ ਮਾਰਕਿਆਂ ਬਾਰੇ ਜਾਣਕਾਰੀ ਦੇਣ ਲਈ, ਉਹਨਾਂ ਨੇ ਦੇ ਨਾਂ ਵੱਡੇ ਅੱਖਰਾਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਜਾਂ ਪਹਿਲੇਂ ਅੱਖਰ ਵੱਡੇ ਰੱਖੇ ਗਏ ਹਨ।</para>

	<para>DOCUMENT AND MODIFIED VERSIONS OF THE DOCUMENT ARE PROVIDED UNDER THE TERMS OF THE GNU FREE DOCUMENTATION LICENSE WITH THE FURTHER UNDERSTANDING THAT: <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>DOCUMENT IS PROVIDED ON AN "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EITHER EXPRESSED OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, WARRANTIES THAT THE DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED VERSION OF THE DOCUMENT IS FREE OF DEFECTS MERCHANTABLE, FIT FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE OR NON-INFRINGING. THE ENTIRE RISK AS TO THE QUALITY, ACCURACY, AND PERFORMANCE OF THE DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED VERSION OF THE DOCUMENT IS WITH YOU. SHOULD ANY DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED VERSION PROVE DEFECTIVE IN ANY RESPECT, YOU (NOT THE INITIAL WRITER, AUTHOR OR ANY CONTRIBUTOR) ASSUME THE COST OF ANY NECESSARY SERVICING, REPAIR OR CORRECTION. THIS DISCLAIMER OF WARRANTY CONSTITUTES AN ESSENTIAL PART OF THIS LICENSE. NO USE OF ANY DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED VERSION OF THE DOCUMENT IS AUTHORIZED HEREUNDER EXCEPT UNDER THIS DISCLAIMER; AND</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>UNDER NO CIRCUMSTANCES AND UNDER NO LEGAL THEORY, WHETHER IN TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE), CONTRACT, OR OTHERWISE, SHALL THE AUTHOR, INITIAL WRITER, ANY CONTRIBUTOR, OR ANY DISTRIBUTOR OF THE DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED VERSION OF THE DOCUMENT, OR ANY SUPPLIER OF ANY OF SUCH PARTIES, BE LIABLE TO ANY PERSON FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OF ANY CHARACTER INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, DAMAGES FOR LOSS OF GOODWILL, WORK STOPPAGE, COMPUTER FAILURE OR MALFUNCTION, OR ANY AND ALL OTHER DAMAGES OR LOSSES ARISING OUT OF OR RELATING TO USE OF THE DOCUMENT AND MODIFIED VERSIONS OF THE DOCUMENT, EVEN IF SUCH PARTY SHALL HAVE BEEN INFORMED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGES.</para>
		</listitem>
	  </orderedlist></para>
  </legalnotice>


  <!-- This file  contains link to license for the documentation (GNU FDL), and
        other legal stuff such as "NO WARRANTY" statement. Please do not change 
        any of this. -->

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>ਜੋਸਫ਼</firstname>
        <surname>ਪਿੰਗਨੋਟ</surname>
      </author>
      <author role="maintainer">
	<firstname>ਜੇਮਜ਼</firstname>
	<surname>ਕੇਪੀ</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <abstract role="description">
      <para>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ ਐਪਲਿਟ ਲਈ ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ ਹੈ।</para>
    </abstract>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>ਵਰਜਨ 0.1</revnumber>
	<date>ਮਈ 2005</date>
	<authorinitials>JP</authorinitials>
	<revdescription>
	   <para role="author">ਜੋਸਫ ਪਿੰਗਨੋਟ</para>
	   <para role="publisher">ਗਨੋਮ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ ਪਰੋਜੈੱਕਟ</para>
	   <para>Infrastrucutre (e.g. legal notice, boilerplate code) shamelessly copied from the GNOME Drive Mount Applet Manual. Thanks!</para>
	</revdescription>
      </revision>

      <revision>
	<revnumber>ਵਰਜਨ 0.2</revnumber>
	<date>ਜੁਲਾਈ 2005</date>
	<authorinitials>JMC</authorinitials>
	<revdescription>
	   <para role="author">ਜੇਮਜ਼ ਐਮ ਕੇਪੀ</para>
	   <para role="publisher">ਗਨੋਮ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ ਪਰੋਜੈੱਕਟ</para>
	   <para>ਇੰਟਰਫੇਸ ਤਬਦੀਲੀਆਂ ਲਈ ਅੱਪਡੇਟ ਹੈ।</para>
	</revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    
    <releaseinfo>ਇਹ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ ਵਿੱਚ ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ ਐਪਲਿਟ ਦੇ ਵਰਜਨ 0.2.4 ਬਾਰੇ ਜਾਣਕਾਰੀ ਹੈ।</releaseinfo>
    <legalnotice>
      <title>ਸੁਝਾਅ</title>
      <para><application>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ</application> ਐਪਲਿਟ ਜਾਂ ਇਹ ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ ਬਾਰੇ ਬੱਗ ਰਿਪੋਰਟ ਦੇਣ ਜਾਂ ਸੁਝਾਅ ਲਈ, <ulink url="ghelp:gnome-feedback" type="help">ਗਨੋਮ ਸੁਝਾਅ ਸਫ਼ਾ</ulink> ਦੀਆਂ ਹਦਾਇਤਾਂ ਦੀ ਪਾਲਨਾ ਕਰੋ।</para>
<!-- Translators may also add here feedback address for translations -->
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <indexterm zone="index"> 
    <primary>ਚੁਸਤ ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ ਐਪਲਿਟ</primary> 
  </indexterm> 
  

  <!-- =======================  Introduction  ======================= -->
  <sect1 id="fusa-intro">
    <title>ਜਾਣ ਪਛਾਣ</title>
    <figure id="fusa-intro-fig"> 
      <title>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ ਐਪਲਿਟ</title> 
      <screenshot> 
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/fast_user_switch_applet-text.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ ਐਪਲਿਟ ਪਾਠ ਵਾਂਗ ਹੈ।</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    <para><application>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ</application> ਤੁਹਾਨੂੰ ਬਿਨਾਂ ਲਾਗਆਉਟ ਹੋਏ ਦੇ ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਖਾਤਿਆਂ 'ਚ ਬਦਲਣ ਲਈ ਸਹਾਇਕ ਹੈ।</para>
    <para>ਤੁਹਾਡੇ ਸਿਸਟਮ ਪਰਸ਼ਾਸ਼ਕ ਵਲੋਂ <application>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ</application> ਇੰਸਟਾਲ ਕਰਨ ਬਾਅਦ, ਬਹੁਤੇ ਉਪਭੋਗੀਆਂ ਵਾਸਤੇ ਕਿਸੇ ਸੰਰਚਨਾ ਦੀ ਲੋੜ ਨਹੀਂ ਰਹਿੰਦੀ ਹੈ। ਤੁਸੀਂ ਪੈਨਲ ਵਿੱਚ ਇੱਕ ਐਪਲਿਟ ਸ਼ਾਮਲ ਕਰਨ ਬਾਅਦ ਤੁਰੰਤ ਇਸ ਦੀ ਵਰਤੋਂ ਕਰ ਸਕਦੇ ਹੋ।</para>
    <sect2 id="fusa-intro-adding">
      <title><application>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ</application> ਨੂੰ <application>ਪੈਨਲ</application> ਵਿੱਚ ਜੋੜਨਾ</title>
      <para>
	To add <application>User Switcher</application> to your <application>Panel</application>, simply right-click on the <application>Panel</application> to which you wish to add <application>User Switcher</application>, select <guimenuitem>Add to Panel...</guimenuitem>, and then select <guilabel>User Switcher</guilabel> from the list of items presented to you, and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.
      </para>
      <para>
	The exact appearance of the <application>User Switcher</application> depends on the size and type of the panel in which it resides, but you should now be able to use the <application>User Switcher</application> by clicking on the word <guilabel>Users</guilabel>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="fusa-usage">
    <title><application>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ</application> ਦੀ ਵਰਤੋਂ</title>
    <para><application>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ</application> ਦੀ ਵਰਤੋਂ ਕਰਨੀ ਆਸਾਨ ਹੈ। ਤੁਸੀਂ ਆਪਣੇ ਪੈਨਲ ਉੱਤੇ <guilabel>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ</guilabel> ਸ਼ਬਦ ਵੇਖੋਗੇ। ਤੁਸੀਂ ਐਪਲਿਟ ਨੂੰ ਉਹ ਸ਼ਬਦ ਉੱਤੇ ਦਬਾ ਕੇ ਵਰਤ ਸਕਦੇ ਹੋ, ਜੋ ਕਿ ਮਾਊਸ ਦੇ ਬਟਨ ਦੀ ਵਰਤੋਂ ਦੇ ਆਧਾਰ ਉੱਤੇ ਵੱਖ ਵੱਖ ਕੰਮ ਕਰ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ।</para>
    <sect2 id="fusa-usage-left">
      <title>ਐਪਲਿਟ ਉੱਤੇ ਖੱਬਾ ਬਟਨ ਦੱਬਣਾ</title>
      <figure id="fusa-usage-left-fig"> 
        <title>ਐਪਲਿਟ ਮੇਨੂ</title> 
        <screenshot> 
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/fast_user_switch_applet.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>ਐਪਲਿਟ ਮੇਨੂ ਹੈ।</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>
	When you left-click on the <application>User Switcher</application>, a menu will pop up. This menu contains a list of users to which you can switch, as well as the option to simply go to the login screen.
      </para>
      <para>
	To either log in as another user, or to resume another user's session, simply click on that user's name. If the user is already logged in, then you will switch to that user's session and you will have to unlock the screen. If the user hasn't logged in, then you will be sent to the login screen.  Simply enter the user's name and password as requested, just as you do to log in normally.
      </para>
      <para>ਜਦੋਂ ਤੁਸੀਂ ਹੋਰ ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਲਈ ਬਦਲਣਾ ਹੋਵੇ ਤਾਂ ਤੁਹਾਡੇ ਸ਼ੈਸ਼ਨ ਨੂੰ ਤਾਲਾਬੰਦ ਕਰ ਦਿੱਤਾ ਜਾਵੇਗਾ। ਤੁਹਾਨੂੰ ਆਪਣਾ ਸ਼ੈਸ਼ਨ ਖਤਮ ਹੋਣ ਉਪਰੰਤ ਆਪਣਾ ਗੁਪਤ-ਕੋਡ ਵੀ ਦੇਣਾ ਪਵੇਗਾ।</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="fusa-usage-middle">
      <title>ਐਪਲਿਟ ਉੱਤੇ ਵਿੱਚਲਾ ਬਟਨ ਦਬਾਉਣਾ</title>
      <para>
	As with any other GNOME applet, you can use the middle mousebutton to easily move an applet around on the <application>Panel</application>. Simply move your mouse over the <application>User Switcher</application>, and then press and hold the middle mousebutton. While holding the middle mousebutton, move your mouse. You should also move the applet.  If the applet does not move, you will need to unlock the applet by releasing the middle mousebutton, and then using the right mousebutton to bring up applet options, as described in the next section.
      </para>
      <para>
        Once you are satisfied with the applet's location on the <application>Panel</application>, release the middle mousebutton, and you're done! You may optionally lock the applet to this location, as described in the next section.   Middle-clicking on the applet allows you to move it within the panel. See
        <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide?gospanel-32">Moving a panel object</ulink> for more information.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="fusa-usage-right">
      <title>ਐਪਲਿਟ ਉੱਤੇ ਸੱਜਾ ਬਟਨ ਦਬਾਉਣਾ</title>
      <figure id="fusa-usage-right-fig"> 
        <title>ਪਰਸੰਗ ਮੇਨੂ</title> 
        <screenshot> 
          <mediaobject> 
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/fast_user_switch_applet-context.png" format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>ਪਰਸੰਗ ਮੇਨੂ</phrase>
            </textobject> 
          </mediaobject> 
        </screenshot> 
      </figure>
      <para>ਜਦੋਂ ਤੁਸੀਂ <application>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ</application> ਉੱਤੇ ਸੱਜਾ ਬਟਨ ਦੱਬਦੇ ਹੋ ਤਾਂ ਇੱਕ ਮੇਨੂ ਵੇਖਾਈ ਦਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ। ਇਹ ਮੇਨੂ ਅੱਗੇ ਦਿੱਤੀਆਂ ਇਕਾਈਆਂ ਵੇਖਾਉਦਾ ਹੈ, ਜਿਸ ਨਾਲ ਤੁਸੀਂ ਕਰ ਸਕਦੇ ਹੋ:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem id="fusa-usage-right-epi">
	  <simpara>
	    <guimenuitem>ਨਿੱਜੀ ਜਾਣਕਾਰੀ ਸੋਧ</guimenuitem>
	  </simpara>
	  <para>ਇਹ ਚੋਣ ਗਨੋਮ ਕੰਟਰੋਲ ਸੈਂਟਰ ਦੇ <application>ਮੇਰੇ ਬਾਰੇ</application> ਸੰਰਚਨਾ ਵਾਰਤਾਲਾਪ ਲਈ ਸ਼ਾਰਟਕੱਟਹੈ, ਜੋ ਕਿ ਤੁਹਾਨੂੰ ਆਪਣਾ ਨਾਂ, ਗੁਪਤ-ਕੋਡ ਅਤੇ ਫੋਟੋ ਆਦਿ ਬਦਲਣ ਲਈ ਸਹਾਇਕ ਹੈ।</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem id="fusa-usage-right-eug">
	  <simpara>
	    <guimenuitem>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਅਤੇ ਗਰੁੱਪ ਸੋਧ</guimenuitem>
	  </simpara>
	  <para>
	    This option is a shortcut into the GNOME system utilites' user management system.  In order to run the tool, you must have administrator privileges. When you are finished, click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>, and you can continue into the GNOME system utilities' user management system. Please refer to that manual for further information on managing users and groups. To exit the password request, click <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem id="fusa-usage-right-sls">
	  <simpara>
	    <guimenuitem>ਲਾਗਿੰਨ ਪਰਦਾ ਸਥਾਪਨ</guimenuitem>
	  </simpara>
	  <para>
	    This item, like the <guimenuitem>Edit Users and Groups</guimenuitem> menu item, requires administrator privileges, and lets you modify the appearance of the login screen. See the <guimenuitem>Edit Users and Groups</guimenuitem> and the login screen settings information in the GNOME system utilities manual for more information.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem id="fusa-usage-right-prefs">
	  <simpara>
	    <guimenuitem>ਮੇਰੀ ਪਸੰਦ</guimenuitem>
	  </simpara>
	  <para><guimenuitem>ਮੇਰੀ ਪਸੰਦ</guimenuitem> ਮੇਨ ਇਕਾਈ ਪਸੰਦ ਵਾਰਤਾਲਾਪ ਖੋਲ੍ਹੇਗੀ, ਜਿਸ ਨੂੰ <application>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ</application> ਦੀ ਸੰਰਚਨਾ ਕਰਨ ਲਈ ਵਰਤਿਆ ਜਾ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ। ਹੋਰ ਜਾਣਕਾਰੀ ਲਈ <xref linkend="fusa-config"/> ਵੇਖੋ।</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem id="fusa-usage-right-about">
	  <simpara>
	    <guimenuitem>ਇਸ ਬਾਰੇ</guimenuitem>
	  </simpara>
	  <para>
	    The <guimenuitem>About</guimenuitem> menu item will bring up a new window which will tell you a little bit more about the <application>User Switcher</application>. Here you can find out what version of the <application>User Switcher</application> you have, who made it, and where its home website is located. Additionally, by selecting the <guibutton>Credits</guibutton> and <guibutton>License</guibutton> buttons, you can find out who helped create it, and under what license it is distributed. Click the <guibutton>Close</guibutton> button to close this window when you are done.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem id="fusa-usage-right-rfp">
	  <simpara>
	    <guimenuitem>ਪੈਨਲ ਤੋਂ ਹਟਾਉਣਾ</guimenuitem>
	  </simpara>
	  <para><guimenuitem>ਪੈਨਲ 'ਚੋਂ ਹਟਾਓ</guimenuitem> ਮੇਨ ਇਕਾਈ ਤੁਹਾਨੂੰ ਇੱਕ ਐਪਲਿਟ ਨੂੰ <application>ਪੈਨਲ</application> ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਹਟਾਉਣ ਲਈ ਸਹਾਇਕ ਹੈ। ਤੁਸੀਂ ਬਾਅਦ ਵਿੱਚ ਐਪਲਿਟ ਵਿੱਚ ਜਾਣ ਪਛਾਣ ਵਿੱਚ ਦਿੱਤੀ ਜਾਣਕਾਰੀ ਮੁਤਾਬਕ ਸ਼ਾਮਲ ਕਰ ਸਕਦੇ ਹੋ। ਪਰ, ਜਦੋਂ ਇੱਕ ਐਪਲਿਟ ਨੂੰ ਪੈਨਲ ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਹਟਾਇਆ ਜਾਂਦਾ ਹੈ ਤਾਂ ਇਸ ਦੀ ਸੈਟਿੰਗ ਖਤਮ ਹੋ ਜਾਂਦੀ ਹੈ। ਤੁਹਾਨੂੰ ਪੁਛਿਆਂ ਨਹੀਂ ਜਾਵੇਗਾ, ਜੇ ਐਪਲਿਟ ਹਟਾਉਣ ਬਾਰੇ ਤੁਸੀਂ ਜਾਣਦੇ ਹੋ।</para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem id="fusa-usage-right-move">
	  <simpara>
	    <guimenuitem>ਏਧਰ-ਓਧਰ</guimenuitem>
	  </simpara>
	  <para>
	    The <guimenuitem>Move</guimenuitem> menu item provides another common way to move applets on the <application>Panel</application>. When you select this option, the applet may be moved simply by moving your mouse. Your cursor will change to illustrate the fact that you are moving the applet. When you have the applet where you want it on the <application>Panel</application>, press any mousebutton to drop the applet into place. Your cursor will change back, reflecting the fact that you are no longer moving the applet.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem id="fusa-usage-right-lock">
	  <simpara>
	    <guimenuitem>ਪੈਲਨ ਵਿੱਚ ਤਾਲਾਬੰਦ</guimenuitem>
	  </simpara>
	  <para>
	    The <guimenuitem>Lock To Panel</guimenuitem> menu item lets you lock the applet into its position on the <application>Panel</application>. Once an applet is Locked, it cannot be moved accidentally. The <guimenuitem>Move</guimenuitem> menu item (discussed next) will be "greyed" and you will no longer be able to select it. To move the applet again, you must first unlock the applet by selecting the <guimenuitem>Lock To Panel</guimenuitem> menu item again. The <guimenuitem>Move</guimenuitem> menu item will once again be selectable.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ======================  Configuration  ======================= -->
  <sect1 id="fusa-config">
    <title><application>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ</application> ਦੀ ਸੰਰਚਨਾ ਜਾਰੀ</title>
    <figure id="fusa-config-prefs-fig"> 
      <title>ਪਸੰਦ ਵਾਰਤਾਲਾਪ</title>
      <screenshot> 
        <mediaobject> 
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/fast_user_switch_applet-prefs.png" format="PNG"/> 
          </imageobject>
          <textobject> 
            <phrase>ਪਸੰਦ ਵਾਰਤਾਲਾਪ ਹੈ।</phrase>
          </textobject> 
        </mediaobject> 
      </screenshot> 
    </figure>
    <para>
      The "Preferences" menu item brings up window where you may change the <application>User Switcher</application>'s behavior and appearance. There are two major sections in it: "Appearance" and "Options".
    </para>
    <sect2 id="fusa-config-appearance">
      <title>ਸਰੂਪ</title>
      <para>
	The <guilabel>Appearance</guilabel> option group changes the way the <application>User Switcher</application> applet is displayed on the panel to match the selected option.
      </para>
      <para>
	The first option, which should appear as your name, will make the applet appear as your name on the Panel. That is, the word <guilabel>Users</guilabel> will be replaced by your username. In the example above, the user's name is "Tyler Durden". If the name which appears here is not your name, you may change it using the <guimenuitem>Edit Personal Information</guimenuitem> item in the context menu. 
      </para>
      <figure id="fusa-config-appearance-username-fig"> 
        <title>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਨਾਂ ਢੰਗ ਵਿੱਚ ਐਪਲਿਟ</title> 
        <screenshot> 
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/fast_user_switch_applet-username.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>ਮੌਜੂਦਾ ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਨਾਂ ਨਾਲ ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ ਐਪਲਿਟ ਹੈ।</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>
	The second option is the word <guilabel>Users</guilabel> and is what is in use if you don't change your Preferences. The word <guilabel>Users</guilabel> will appear on the <application>Panel</application> to represent the <application>User Switcher</application>.
      </para>
      <figure id="fusa-config-appearance-text-fig"> 
        <title>ਪਾਠ ਢੰਗ ਵਿੱਚ ਐਪਲਿਟ</title> 
        <screenshot> 
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/fast_user_switch_applet-text.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ ਐਪਲਿਟ ਪਾਠ ਵਾਂਗ ਹੈ।</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>
	The third and final option is a picture (see the example above). If you select this option, this picture will appear on the Panel to represent the <application>User Switcher</application>.
      </para>
      <figure id="fusa-config-appearance-icon-fig"> 
        <title>ਆਈਕਾਨ ਢੰਗ ਵਿੱਚ ਐਪਲਿਟ</title> 
        <screenshot> 
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/fast_user_switch_applet-icon.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ ਐਪਲਿਟ ਆਈਕਾਨ ਵਾਂਗ ਹੈ।</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="fusa-config-options">
      <title>ਚੋਣ</title>
      <para>
	The <guilabel>Options</guilabel> preference section provides options which control the behavior (as opposed to the appearance) of the <application>User Switcher</application>.
      </para>
      <sect3 id="fusa-config-options-lock">
	<title>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਤਬਦੀਲ ਕਰਨ ਦੇ ਬਾਅਦ ਪਰਦੇ ਨੂੰ ਤਾਲਾ</title>
	<para>
	  This option determines whether the <application>User Switcher</application> will attempt to lock the screen after switching to another user or login screen. If this option is enabled, your password must be entered to regain access to your desktop. If this option is disabled, then anyone on your computer may access your desktop without any passwords by switching back to your desktop.
	</para>
	<para>
	  When disabled, this option will disable security when switching users, so unless you explicitly trust everyone with access to the computer, it's better to leave it enabled.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="fusa-config-options-nested">
	<title>ਅੰਦਰੂਨੀ ਝਰੋਖਿਆਂ ਵਿੱਚ ਨਵੇਂ ਲਾਗਿੰਨ ਬਣਾਉਣੇ</title>
	<para>
	  When this option is active, you will not actually switch screens when you log in as another user with the <application>User Switcher</application>. Instead, each new login will appear inside a window on your current screen. For obvious reasons, the current screen will not be locked when creating a new logins inside windows.
	</para>
	<para>ਇਹ ਚੋਣ ਕਈ ਡੈਸਕਟਾਪ ਤਕਨਾਲੋਜੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਵਿਕਾਸ ਵਾਸਤੇ ਮੌਜੂਦ ਹੈ, ਇਸਕਰਕੇ ਬਹੁਤੇ ਲੋਕਾਂ ਨੂੰ ਇਹ ਯੋਗ ਨਹੀਂ ਕਰਨੀ ਪੈਂਦੀ ਹੈ।</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  <!-- ===========================  Notes  =========================== -->
  <sect1 id="fusa-notes">
    <title>ਸੂਚਨਾ</title>
    <sect2 id="fusa-notes-problems">
      <title>ਆਮ ਸਮੱਸਿਆਵਾਂ</title>
      <qandaset>
        <qandaentry>
          <question>
            <para>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ "faces" ਹੋਰ ਉਪਭੋਗੀਆਂ ਦੇ ਮੇਨੂ ਵਿੱਚ ਨਹੀਂ ਦਿੱਸੇਗਾ।</para>
          </question>
          <answer>
            <para>
              In order for user faces to be visible, they must be readable by all users. Currently, faces are stored in image format in the file called <filename>~/.face</filename>. As a result, the <filename>~/.face</filename> file must have permissions which allow other users to read it (typically, a permissions mask of <computeroutput>0644</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>-rw-r--r--</computeroutput> will suffice), and the users home directories must allow listing by others (at minimum, <computeroutput>0711</computeroutput>, or <computeroutput>drwx--x--x</computeroutput> will suffice).
            </para>
          </answer>
        </qandaentry>
        <qandaentry>
          <question>
            <para><application>ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਸਵਿੱਚਰ</application> <guilabel>ਪੈਨਲ ਵਿੱਚ ਸ਼ਾਮਲ</guilabel> ਵਾਰਤਾਲਾਪ ਵਿੱਚ ਵੇਖਾਈ ਨਹੀਂ ਦਿੰਦਾ ਹੈ।</para>
          </question>
          <answer>
            <para>
              The <application>User Switcher</application> must be installed to the same prefix as the <application>Panel</application>. That is, if the <application>Panel</application> is at <command>/usr/bin/panel</command>, the applet should be installed to the /usr prefix. If the applet was installed properly (for example, via your distribution), then try logging out and back in to refresh the <guilabel>Add to Panel</guilabel> list.
            </para>
          </answer>
        </qandaentry>
      </qandaset>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="fusa-notes-hidden">
      <title>ਲੁਕਵੀਆਂ ਚੋਣਾਂ</title>
      <para>
        The <application>User Switcher</application> applet contains some useful hidden options for geeks, nerds, administrators, and other misfits. These options require modifying the configuration using special tools like the <application>Configuration Editor</application> or <command>gconftool-2</command>, but they can cause some unexpected or undesired behavior. These options affect every instance of the <application>User Switcher</application> for a particular user, and can be locked by administrators.
      </para>
      <sect3 id="fusa-notes-hidden-show-active-users-only">
        <title>ਸਿਰਫ਼ ਸਰਗਰਮ ਉਪਭੋਗੀ ਹੀ ਵੇਖਾਓ</title>
        <para>ਇਹ ਕੁੰਜੀ, <filename>/apps/fast-user-switch-applet/show_active_users_only</filename> ਵਿੱਚ ਪਛਾਣ ਕਰਦੀ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਇਸ ਸਮੇਂ ਲਾਗਿੰਨ ਉਪਭੋਗੀ (ਜਦੋਂ ਯੋਗ ਹੋਣ), ਉਹੀ ਵੇਖਾਉਣੇ ਹਨ, ਜਾਂ ਸਭ ਜਾਇਜ਼ ਉਪਭੋਗੀ (ਜਦੋਂ ਅਯੋਗ ਹੋਣ) ਵੇਖਾਉਣੇ ਹਨ।</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="fusa-notes-hidden-show-screen-item">
        <title>ਲਾਗਿੰਨ ਪਰਦਾ ਮੇਨੂ ਇਕਾਈ ਵੇਖਾਓ</title>
        <para>
          This key, in <filename>/apps/fast-user-switch-applet/show_screen_item</filename> determines whether to show the <guimenuitem>Login Screen</guimenuitem> menu item at the bottom of the left-click menu (see <xref linkend="fusa-usage-left"/> for more information on this menu). This item is used to create a new, empty login screen. If this option is set to <computeroutput>always</computeroutput>, the item will always be shown. If this option is set to <computeroutput>auto</computeroutput>, then the item will be shown if the applet is configured to not use nested logins (see <xref linkend="fusa-config-options-nested"/> for more information). If this option is set to <computeroutput>never</computeroutput>, then the item will never be shown. 
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="fusa-notes-hidden-show-window-item">
        <title>ਲਾਗਿੰਨ ਝਰੋਖੇ ਮੇਨੂ ਇਕਾਈ ਵੇਖਾਓ</title>
        <para>
          This key, in <filename>/apps/fast-user-switch-applet/show_window_item</filename> determines whether to show the <guimenuitem>Login Window</guimenuitem> menu item at the bottom of the left-click menu (see <xref linkend="fusa-usage-left"/> for more information on this menu). This item is used to create a new empty login screen inside a window on the current screen. If this option is set to <computeroutput>always</computeroutput>, the item will always be shown. If this option is set to <computeroutput>auto</computeroutput>, then the item will be shown if the applet is configured to use nested logins (see <xref linkend="fusa-config-options-nested"/> for more information). If this option is set to <computeroutput>never</computeroutput>, then the item will never be shown.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>
