<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY legal SYSTEM "legal.xml">
<!ENTITY appversion "0.2.4">
<!ENTITY app "<application>User Switcher</application>">
<!ENTITY appname "User Switcher">
]>
<!--
      (Do not remove this comment block.)
  Maintained by the GNOME Documentation Project
  http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gdp
  Template version: 2.0 beta
  Template last modified Feb 12, 2002
-->
<article id="index" lang="sr">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>User Switcher Applet</title>
    <copyright>
      <year>2005</year>
      <holder>Joseph Pingenot</holder>
    </copyright>
    <copyright>
      <year>2005</year>
      <holder>James M. Cape</holder>
    </copyright><copyright><year>2004</year><holder>Данило Шеган (српски превод)</holder></copyright>

<!-- translators: uncomment this:

    <copyright>
      <year>2002</year>
      <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
    </copyright>

   -->

    <publisher>
      <publishername>Подухват документовања Гнома</publishername>
    </publisher>

      <legalnotice id="legalnotice">
	<para>
	  Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
	  document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation
	  License (GFDL), Version 1.1 or any later version published
	  by the Free Software Foundation with no Invariant Sections,
	  no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.  You can find
	  a copy of the GFDL at this <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:fdl">link</ulink> or in the file COPYING-DOCS
	  distributed with this manual.
         </para>
         <para> This manual is part of a collection of GNOME manuals
          distributed under the GFDL.  If you want to distribute this
          manual separately from the collection, you can do so by
          adding a copy of the license to the manual, as described in
          section 6 of the license.
	</para>

	<para>
	  Many of the names used by companies to distinguish their
	  products and services are claimed as trademarks. Where those
	  names appear in any GNOME documentation, and the members of
	  the GNOME Documentation Project are made aware of those
	  trademarks, then the names are in capital letters or initial
	  capital letters.
	</para>

	<para>
	  DOCUMENT AND MODIFIED VERSIONS OF THE DOCUMENT ARE PROVIDED
	  UNDER  THE TERMS OF THE GNU FREE DOCUMENTATION LICENSE
	  WITH THE FURTHER UNDERSTANDING THAT:

	  <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		  <para>DOCUMENT IS PROVIDED ON AN "AS IS" BASIS,
                    WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EITHER EXPRESSED OR
                    IMPLIED, INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, WARRANTIES
                    THAT THE DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED VERSION OF THE
                    DOCUMENT IS FREE OF DEFECTS MERCHANTABLE, FIT FOR
                    A PARTICULAR PURPOSE OR NON-INFRINGING. THE ENTIRE
                    RISK AS TO THE QUALITY, ACCURACY, AND PERFORMANCE
                    OF THE DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED VERSION OF THE
                    DOCUMENT IS WITH YOU. SHOULD ANY DOCUMENT OR
                    MODIFIED VERSION PROVE DEFECTIVE IN ANY RESPECT,
                    YOU (NOT THE INITIAL WRITER, AUTHOR OR ANY
                    CONTRIBUTOR) ASSUME THE COST OF ANY NECESSARY
                    SERVICING, REPAIR OR CORRECTION. THIS DISCLAIMER
                    OF WARRANTY CONSTITUTES AN ESSENTIAL PART OF THIS
                    LICENSE. NO USE OF ANY DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED
                    VERSION OF THE DOCUMENT IS AUTHORIZED HEREUNDER
                    EXCEPT UNDER THIS DISCLAIMER; AND
		  </para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
		  <para>UNDER NO CIRCUMSTANCES AND UNDER NO LEGAL
                       THEORY, WHETHER IN TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE),
                       CONTRACT, OR OTHERWISE, SHALL THE AUTHOR,
                       INITIAL WRITER, ANY CONTRIBUTOR, OR ANY
                       DISTRIBUTOR OF THE DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED VERSION
                       OF THE DOCUMENT, OR ANY SUPPLIER OF ANY OF SUCH
                       PARTIES, BE LIABLE TO ANY PERSON FOR ANY
                       DIRECT, INDIRECT, SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL, OR
                       CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OF ANY CHARACTER
                       INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, DAMAGES FOR LOSS
                       OF GOODWILL, WORK STOPPAGE, COMPUTER FAILURE OR
                       MALFUNCTION, OR ANY AND ALL OTHER DAMAGES OR
                       LOSSES ARISING OUT OF OR RELATING TO USE OF THE
                       DOCUMENT AND MODIFIED VERSIONS OF THE DOCUMENT,
                       EVEN IF SUCH PARTY SHALL HAVE BEEN INFORMED OF
                       THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGES.
		  </para>
		</listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
	</para>
  </legalnotice>


  <!-- This file  contains link to license for the documentation (GNU FDL), and
        other legal stuff such as "NO WARRANTY" statement. Please do not change 
        any of this. -->

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Joseph</firstname>
        <surname>Pingenot</surname>
      </author>
      <author role="maintainer">
	<firstname>James</firstname>
	<surname>Cape</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <abstract role="description">
      <para>User manual for the User Switcher applet.</para>
    </abstract>

    <revhistory>
      <revision>
	<revnumber>Издање 0.1</revnumber>
	<date>мај 2005.</date>
	<authorinitials>JP</authorinitials>
	<revdescription>
	   <para role="author">Joseph Pingenot</para>
	   <para role="publisher">Подухват документовања Гнома</para>
	   <para>Infrastrucutre (e.g. legal notice, boilerplate code) shamelessly copied from the GNOME Drive Mount Applet Manual. Thanks!</para>
	</revdescription>
      </revision>

      <revision>
	<revnumber>Издање 0.2</revnumber>
	<date>јул 2005.</date>
	<authorinitials>JMC</authorinitials>
	<revdescription>
	   <para role="author">James M. Cape</para>
	   <para role="publisher">Подухват документовања Гнома</para>
	   <para>Updates for interface changes.</para>
	</revdescription>
      </revision>
    </revhistory>
    
    <releaseinfo>Ово упутство описује издање 0.2.4 програмчета за замену корисника.</releaseinfo>
    <legalnotice>
      <title>Примедбе</title>
      <para>Да пријавите грешку или нешто предложите у вези овог програмчета <application>замене корисника</application> или овог упутства, погледајте <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gnome-feedback">страну за примедбе о Гному</ulink></para>
<!-- Translators may also add here feedback address for translations -->
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <indexterm zone="index"> 
    <primary>Програмче за брзу замену корисника</primary> 
  </indexterm> 
  

  <!-- =======================  Introduction  ======================= -->
  <sect1 id="fusa-intro">
    <title>Увод</title>
    <figure id="fusa-intro-fig"> 
      <title>User Switcher Applet</title> 
      <screenshot> 
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/fast_user_switch_applet-text.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject>
            <phrase>The User Switcher applet as text.</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The <application>User Switcher</application> allows you to quickly change between user accounts without having to log out.
    </para>
    <para>
      After your system administrator has installed <application>User Switcher</application>, no further configuration is necessary for most users. You may add the applet to a panel and begin using it immediately.
    </para>
    <sect2 id="fusa-intro-adding">
      <title>Adding the <application>User Switcher</application> to a <application>Panel</application></title>
      <para>
	To add <application>User Switcher</application> to your <application>Panel</application>, simply right-click on the <application>Panel</application> to which you wish to add <application>User Switcher</application>, select <guimenuitem>Add to Panel...</guimenuitem>, and then select <guilabel>User Switcher</guilabel> from the list of items presented to you, and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.
      </para>
      <para>
	The exact appearance of the <application>User Switcher</application> depends on the size and type of the panel in which it resides, but you should now be able to use the <application>User Switcher</application> by clicking on the word <guilabel>Users</guilabel>.
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="fusa-usage">
    <title>Употреба <application>Замене корисника</application>.</title>
    <para>
      Using the <application>User Switcher</application> is easy. You should see the word <guilabel>Users</guilabel> on your Panel. You use the Applet by clicking on that word, which does different things depending on the mouse button you are using.
    </para>
    <sect2 id="fusa-usage-left">
      <title>Left-Clicking on the Applet</title>
      <figure id="fusa-usage-left-fig"> 
        <title>The applet menu</title> 
        <screenshot> 
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/fast_user_switch_applet.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>The applet menu.</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>
	When you left-click on the <application>User Switcher</application>, a menu will pop up. This menu contains a list of users to which you can switch, as well as the option to simply go to the login screen.
      </para>
      <para>
	To either log in as another user, or to resume another user's session, simply click on that user's name. If the user is already logged in, then you will switch to that user's session and you will have to unlock the screen. If the user hasn't logged in, then you will be sent to the login screen.  Simply enter the user's name and password as requested, just as you do to log in normally.
      </para>
      <para>
	When you switch to another user, your session will be locked. You will have to enter your password to finish resuming your session.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="fusa-usage-middle">
      <title>Middle-Clicking on the Applet</title>
      <para>
	As with any other GNOME applet, you can use the middle mousebutton to easily move an applet around on the <application>Panel</application>. Simply move your mouse over the <application>User Switcher</application>, and then press and hold the middle mousebutton. While holding the middle mousebutton, move your mouse. You should also move the applet.  If the applet does not move, you will need to unlock the applet by releasing the middle mousebutton, and then using the right mousebutton to bring up applet options, as described in the next section.
      </para>
      <para>
        Once you are satisfied with the applet's location on the <application>Panel</application>, release the middle mousebutton, and you're done! You may optionally lock the applet to this location, as described in the next section.   Middle-clicking on the applet allows you to move it within the panel. See
        <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide?gospanel-32">Moving a panel object</ulink> for more information.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="fusa-usage-right">
      <title>Right-Clicking on the Applet</title>
      <figure id="fusa-usage-right-fig"> 
        <title>The Context Menu</title> 
        <screenshot> 
          <mediaobject> 
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/fast_user_switch_applet-context.png" format="PNG"/> 
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>The context menu</phrase>
            </textobject> 
          </mediaobject> 
        </screenshot> 
      </figure>
      <para>
	When you right-click on the <application>User Switcher</application>, a menu will appear. This menu lists the following things which you can do:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem id="fusa-usage-right-epi">
	  <simpara>
	    <guimenuitem>Edit Personal Information</guimenuitem>
	  </simpara>
	  <para>
	    This option is a shortcut into the GNOME control center's <application>About Me</application> configuration dialog, which allows you to change your name, password, photo, etc.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem id="fusa-usage-right-eug">
	  <simpara>
	    <guimenuitem>Edit Users and Groups</guimenuitem>
	  </simpara>
	  <para>
	    This option is a shortcut into the GNOME system utilites' user management system.  In order to run the tool, you must have administrator privileges. When you are finished, click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>, and you can continue into the GNOME system utilities' user management system. Please refer to that manual for further information on managing users and groups. To exit the password request, click <guibutton>Cancel</guibutton>.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem id="fusa-usage-right-sls">
	  <simpara>
	    <guimenuitem>Setup Login Screen</guimenuitem>
	  </simpara>
	  <para>
	    This item, like the <guimenuitem>Edit Users and Groups</guimenuitem> menu item, requires administrator privileges, and lets you modify the appearance of the login screen. See the <guimenuitem>Edit Users and Groups</guimenuitem> and the login screen settings information in the GNOME system utilities manual for more information.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem id="fusa-usage-right-prefs">
	  <simpara>
	    <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
	  </simpara>
	  <para>
	    The <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem> menu item will open the preferences dialog, which can be used to configure the <application>User Switcher</application>. See <xref linkend="fusa-config"/> for more information.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem id="fusa-usage-right-about">
	  <simpara>
	    <guimenuitem>About</guimenuitem>
	  </simpara>
	  <para>
	    The <guimenuitem>About</guimenuitem> menu item will bring up a new window which will tell you a little bit more about the <application>User Switcher</application>. Here you can find out what version of the <application>User Switcher</application> you have, who made it, and where its home website is located. Additionally, by selecting the <guibutton>Credits</guibutton> and <guibutton>License</guibutton> buttons, you can find out who helped create it, and under what license it is distributed. Click the <guibutton>Close</guibutton> button to close this window when you are done.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem id="fusa-usage-right-rfp">
	  <simpara>
	    <guimenuitem>Remove from Panel</guimenuitem>
	  </simpara>
	  <para>
	    The <guimenuitem>Remove From Panel</guimenuitem> menu item allows you to remove an applet from the <application>Panel</application>. You can later add the applet back again as described in the introduction. However, when an applet is removed from the panel, its settings will be lost. You will not be asked if you are sure before the applet is removed.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem id="fusa-usage-right-move">
	  <simpara>
	    <guimenuitem>Move</guimenuitem>
	  </simpara>
	  <para>
	    The <guimenuitem>Move</guimenuitem> menu item provides another common way to move applets on the <application>Panel</application>. When you select this option, the applet may be moved simply by moving your mouse. Your cursor will change to illustrate the fact that you are moving the applet. When you have the applet where you want it on the <application>Panel</application>, press any mousebutton to drop the applet into place. Your cursor will change back, reflecting the fact that you are no longer moving the applet.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem id="fusa-usage-right-lock">
	  <simpara>
	    <guimenuitem>Lock To Panel</guimenuitem>
	  </simpara>
	  <para>
	    The <guimenuitem>Lock To Panel</guimenuitem> menu item lets you lock the applet into its position on the <application>Panel</application>. Once an applet is Locked, it cannot be moved accidentally. The <guimenuitem>Move</guimenuitem> menu item (discussed next) will be "greyed" and you will no longer be able to select it. To move the applet again, you must first unlock the applet by selecting the <guimenuitem>Lock To Panel</guimenuitem> menu item again. The <guimenuitem>Move</guimenuitem> menu item will once again be selectable.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ======================  Configuration  ======================= -->
  <sect1 id="fusa-config">
    <title>Configuring the <application>User Switcher</application></title>
    <figure id="fusa-config-prefs-fig"> 
      <title>Preferences dialog</title>
      <screenshot> 
        <mediaobject> 
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/fast_user_switch_applet-prefs.png" format="PNG"/> 
          </imageobject>
          <textobject> 
            <phrase>The Preferences dialog.</phrase>
          </textobject> 
        </mediaobject> 
      </screenshot> 
    </figure>
    <para>
      The "Preferences" menu item brings up window where you may change the <application>User Switcher</application>'s behavior and appearance. There are two major sections in it: "Appearance" and "Options".
    </para>
    <sect2 id="fusa-config-appearance">
      <title>Appearance</title>
      <para>
	The <guilabel>Appearance</guilabel> option group changes the way the <application>User Switcher</application> applet is displayed on the panel to match the selected option.
      </para>
      <para>
	The first option, which should appear as your name, will make the applet appear as your name on the Panel. That is, the word <guilabel>Users</guilabel> will be replaced by your username. In the example above, the user's name is "Tyler Durden". If the name which appears here is not your name, you may change it using the <guimenuitem>Edit Personal Information</guimenuitem> item in the context menu. 
      </para>
      <figure id="fusa-config-appearance-username-fig"> 
        <title>The applet in username mode</title> 
        <screenshot> 
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/fast_user_switch_applet-username.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>The User Switcher applet as the current user name.</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>
	The second option is the word <guilabel>Users</guilabel> and is what is in use if you don't change your Preferences. The word <guilabel>Users</guilabel> will appear on the <application>Panel</application> to represent the <application>User Switcher</application>.
      </para>
      <figure id="fusa-config-appearance-text-fig"> 
        <title>The applet in text mode</title> 
        <screenshot> 
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/fast_user_switch_applet-text.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>The User Switcher applet as text.</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
      <para>
	The third and final option is a picture (see the example above). If you select this option, this picture will appear on the Panel to represent the <application>User Switcher</application>.
      </para>
      <figure id="fusa-config-appearance-icon-fig"> 
        <title>The applet in icon mode</title> 
        <screenshot> 
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="figures/fast_user_switch_applet-icon.png" format="PNG"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject>
              <phrase>The User Switcher applet as icon.</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </screenshot>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="fusa-config-options">
      <title>Options</title>
      <para>
	The <guilabel>Options</guilabel> preference section provides options which control the behavior (as opposed to the appearance) of the <application>User Switcher</application>.
      </para>
      <sect3 id="fusa-config-options-lock">
	<title>Lock the screen after switching users</title>
	<para>
	  This option determines whether the <application>User Switcher</application> will attempt to lock the screen after switching to another user or login screen. If this option is enabled, your password must be entered to regain access to your desktop. If this option is disabled, then anyone on your computer may access your desktop without any passwords by switching back to your desktop.
	</para>
	<para>
	  When disabled, this option will disable security when switching users, so unless you explicitly trust everyone with access to the computer, it's better to leave it enabled.
	</para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="fusa-config-options-nested">
	<title>Create new logins in nested windows</title>
	<para>
	  When this option is active, you will not actually switch screens when you log in as another user with the <application>User Switcher</application>. Instead, each new login will appear inside a window on your current screen. For obvious reasons, the current screen will not be locked when creating a new logins inside windows.
	</para>
	<para>
	  This option exists primarily to aid development of various desktop technologies, so most people won't have cause to enable it.
	</para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  <!-- ===========================  Notes  =========================== -->
  <sect1 id="fusa-notes">
    <title>Notes for Nerds</title>
    <sect2 id="fusa-notes-problems">
      <title>Common Problems</title>
      <qandaset>
        <qandaentry>
          <question>
            <para>
              User "faces" are not appearing in other users' menus.
            </para>
          </question>
          <answer>
            <para>
              In order for user faces to be visible, they must be readable by all users. Currently, faces are stored in image format in the file called <filename>~/.face</filename>. As a result, the <filename>~/.face</filename> file must have permissions which allow other users to read it (typically, a permissions mask of <computeroutput>0644</computeroutput> or <computeroutput>-rw-r--r--</computeroutput> will suffice), and the users home directories must allow listing by others (at minimum, <computeroutput>0711</computeroutput>, or <computeroutput>drwx--x--x</computeroutput> will suffice).
            </para>
          </answer>
        </qandaentry>
        <qandaentry>
          <question>
            <para>
              The <application>User Switcher</application> does not appear in the <guilabel>Add to Panel</guilabel> dialog.
            </para>
          </question>
          <answer>
            <para>
              The <application>User Switcher</application> must be installed to the same prefix as the <application>Panel</application>. That is, if the <application>Panel</application> is at <command>/usr/bin/panel</command>, the applet should be installed to the /usr prefix. If the applet was installed properly (for example, via your distribution), then try logging out and back in to refresh the <guilabel>Add to Panel</guilabel> list.
            </para>
          </answer>
        </qandaentry>
      </qandaset>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="fusa-notes-hidden">
      <title>Hidden Options</title>
      <para>
        The <application>User Switcher</application> applet contains some useful hidden options for geeks, nerds, administrators, and other misfits. These options require modifying the configuration using special tools like the <application>Configuration Editor</application> or <command>gconftool-2</command>, but they can cause some unexpected or undesired behavior. These options affect every instance of the <application>User Switcher</application> for a particular user, and can be locked by administrators.
      </para>
      <sect3 id="fusa-notes-hidden-show-active-users-only">
        <title>Show Active Users Only</title>
        <para>
          This key, in <filename>/apps/fast-user-switch-applet/show_active_users_only</filename> determines whether to show only those users who are currently logged in (when enabled), or all legal users (when disabled).
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="fusa-notes-hidden-show-screen-item">
        <title>Show Login Screen Menuitem</title>
        <para>
          This key, in <filename>/apps/fast-user-switch-applet/show_screen_item</filename> determines whether to show the <guimenuitem>Login Screen</guimenuitem> menu item at the bottom of the left-click menu (see <xref linkend="fusa-usage-left"/> for more information on this menu). This item is used to create a new, empty login screen. If this option is set to <computeroutput>always</computeroutput>, the item will always be shown. If this option is set to <computeroutput>auto</computeroutput>, then the item will be shown if the applet is configured to not use nested logins (see <xref linkend="fusa-config-options-nested"/> for more information). If this option is set to <computeroutput>never</computeroutput>, then the item will never be shown. 
        </para>
      </sect3>
      <sect3 id="fusa-notes-hidden-show-window-item">
        <title>Show Login Window Menuitem</title>
        <para>
          This key, in <filename>/apps/fast-user-switch-applet/show_window_item</filename> determines whether to show the <guimenuitem>Login Window</guimenuitem> menu item at the bottom of the left-click menu (see <xref linkend="fusa-usage-left"/> for more information on this menu). This item is used to create a new empty login screen inside a window on the current screen. If this option is set to <computeroutput>always</computeroutput>, the item will always be shown. If this option is set to <computeroutput>auto</computeroutput>, then the item will be shown if the applet is configured to use nested logins (see <xref linkend="fusa-config-options-nested"/> for more information). If this option is set to <computeroutput>never</computeroutput>, then the item will never be shown.
        </para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</article>
