<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Docbook XML V.4.3//EN"
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
	  <!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
	  %globalent;
	  <!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
	  %gnome-menus-C;
	  <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
	  %xinclude;
	  <!ENTITY language "en">
	  <!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
	  ]>
	  <?db.chunk.max_depth 4?>
<?yelp:chunk-depth 4?>
<chapter id="connecting" status="review">
	<title>Connecting</title>
	<para>NetworkManager manages wired, wireless, mobile broadband, vpn and dsl connections. It does not
	currently support dialup modem connections but there is help available in <xref linkend="modem"/>.</para>
	
	<sect1 id="connecting-wired" status="review">
		<title>Wired (LAN)</title>
		<para>DHCP connections (where settings are concfigured by your router) are automatically configured. 
		Wired network connections are selected as default when connected.</para>
		<sect2 id="connecting-wired-dhcp" status="review">
			<title>DHCP Connections</title>
			<para>Most routers use DHCP to allocate IP addresses.</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Click the NetworkManager icon in the system notification area.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Under <guilabel>Wired Network</guilabel> click the <guilabel>Radio Button</guilabel> 
				next to the network you want to connect to.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="connecting-wired-manual" status="review">
			<title>Static Connections</title>
			<para>If you don't use DHCP then you can configure a static connection.</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Right click the NetworkManager icon in the system notification area.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click <guilabel>Edit Connections</guilabel>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click the <guilabel>Wired</guilabel> tab.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Select the connection and click <guibutton>Edit</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click the <guilabel>IPv4</guilabel> tab.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Choose <guilabel>Manual</guilabel> from the <guilabel>Method</guilabel> drop down.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Enter your details and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click <guibutton>Close</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>			
		</sect2>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="connecting-wireless" status="review">
		<title>Wireless</title>
		<para>To connect to a wireless network:</para>
		<procedure>
			<step><para>Ensure that your wireless device is turned on.</para></step>
			<step><para>Click the <guiicon>NetworkManager</guiicon> icon in the system notification area.</para></step>
			<step><para>Under <guilabel>Wireless Network</guilabel> click the radio button next to the
			network you want to connect to.</para></step>
		</procedure>
		<para>If you have connected to the network previously, Ubuntu will automatically connect to the network where it is available.</para>
		<para>If you are connecting to a network for the first time, security details may be needed. If so, a dialog box will open. Enter your security details as follows.</para>
		<procedure>
			<step><para>In most cases the security type will be detected automatically. If not, select the security type from the <guilabel>Wireless Security</guilabel> drop-down box. This will depend on how the wireless network is set up. Examples of security types are WEP, WPA and LEAP.</para></step>
			<step><para>Enter the password, key or other authentication details as appropriate.</para></step>
			<step><para>Click <guibutton>Connect</guibutton>.</para></step>
		</procedure>
		<note>
		<para>If you have a wired network connection as well as an wireless connection, 
		the wired connection will be used by default.</para>
		</note>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="connecting-mobile" status="review">
		<title>Mobile Broadband</title>
		<para><emphasis>Mobile Broadband</emphasis> means any kind of high speed internet connection which is provided by an external device such as a 3G usb stick or mobile phone with built-in HSPA/UMTS/GPRS data connection. Some laptops have recently been produced with mobile broadband devices already inside them.</para>
		<para>Most Mobile Broadband devices should be recognised automatically when you connect them to your computer. Ubuntu will prompt you to configure the device.</para>
		<procedure>
		<step><para>The <guilabel>New Mobile Broadband Connection</guilabel> Wizard will open automatically when you connect the device.</para></step>
		<step><para>Click <guibutton>Forward</guibutton> and insert your details, including the country where your Mobile Broadband device was issued, the network provider and type of connection (for example, <emphasis>Contract</emphasis> or <emphasis>pre-pay</emphasis>).</para></step>
		<step><para>Give your connection a name (it is up to you what name you choose) and click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton>.</para></step>
		<step><para>Your connection is now ready to use. To connect, left click the <guiicon>NetworkManager</guiicon> icon in the top right of the panel and select your new connection.</para></step>
		<step><para>To disconnect, left click the <guiicon>NetworkManager</guiicon> icon in the top right of the panel and click <guibutton>Disconnect</guibutton>.</para></step>
		</procedure>
		<para>If you are not prompted to configure the device when you connect it, it may still be recognised by Ubuntu. In such cases you can add the connection manually.</para>
		<procedure>
			<step><para>Right click the <guiicon>NetworkManager</guiicon> icon in the top right of the panel and click <guilabel>Edit Connections...</guilabel></para></step>
			<step><para>Select the <guilabel>Mobile Broadband</guilabel> tab.</para></step>
			<step><para>Click <guibutton>Add</guibutton>.</para></step>
			<step><para>This should open the <guilabel>New Mobile Broadband Connection</guilabel> Wizard. Enter your details as described above.</para></step>
		</procedure>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="connecting-vpn" status="review">
		<title>Virtual Private Networks</title>
		<para>There are three types of Virtual Private Networks (VPNs) that are currently supported by NetworkManager (NM).  It is important to know which type of VPN network you are attempting to connect to. 
		</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Begin by installing <ulink url="apt:network-manager-openvpn">network-manager-openvpn</ulink>, <ulink url="apt:network-manager-pptp">network-manager-pptp</ulink> and/or <ulink url="apt:network-manager-vpnc">network-manager-vpnc</ulink>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Left click the <guiicon>NetworkManager</guiicon> icon and click <guilabel>Configure VPN...</guilabel> from the <guilabel>VPN Connections</guilabel> option.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Click <guibutton>Add</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect1>

	<sect1 id="connecting-dsl" status="review">
		<title>DSL</title>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Right click the <guiicon>NetworkManager</guiicon> icon and click <guilabel>Edit connections...</guilabel></para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Click <guilabel>DSL</guilabel>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Click <guibutton>Add</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
