<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<gnome-version>
  <platform>2</platform>
  <minor>26</minor>
  <micro>1</micro>
  <distributor>Ubuntu</distributor>
  <date>2009-05-06</date>
  <description>
    
    <p>GNOME is a Free, usable, stable, accessible desktop environment for the Unix-like family of operating systems.</p>
    <p xml:lang="af">GNOME is 'n Vrye, bruikbare, stabiele, toeganklike werkareaomgewing vir die Unix-agtige familie van bedryfstelsels.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ar">جنوم بيئة سطح مكتب لعائلة نظم التشغيل المشابهة ليونكس، حرّة، وسهلة الاستخدام، وسهلة المنال.</p>
    <p xml:lang="as">Unix-পৰিবাৰৰ বিভিন্ন কাৰ্য্যকৰ প্ৰণালীত ব্যৱহাৰৰ বাবে GNOME এটা মুক্ত, ব্যৱহাৰযোগ্য, স্থায়ী আৰু সহজলভ্য ডেস্কট'প ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="ast">GNOME ye un entornu d'escritoriu Llibre, afayadizu, estable y accesible pa los sistemes operativos de la familia UNIX y asemeyaos.</p>
    <p xml:lang="az">GNOME, Unix-bənzəri əməliyyat sistemləri ailələri üçün sərbəst, işlədilməsi asand, güclü, yetişmə qabiliyyətli masa üstü mühitidir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="be">GNOME - вольнае, карыснае, магутнае, даступнае працоўнае асяродзьде для UNIX-падобных апэрацыйных сыстэм.</p>
    <p xml:lang="be@latin">GNOME jość svabodnym, zručnym, stabilnym asiarodździem dla aperacyjnych systemaŭ ź siamji Unix.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bg">GNOME е свободна, лесна, стабилна и достъпна работна среда за операционни системи сходни с Unix.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bn">ইউনিক্স-পরিবারের মতো অপারেটিং সিস্টেমের জন্য গনোম বিনামূল্যে,ব্যবহার উপযোগী, প্রতিষ্ঠিত, সমর্থিত একটি ডেস্কটপ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="bn_IN">Unix-পরিবারের বিভিন্ন অপারেটিং সিস্টেমে ব্যবহারের জন্য GNOME একটি মুক্ত, ব্যবহারযোগ্য, স্থায়ী ও সহজলভ্য ডেস্কটপ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="br">Un endro gorretaol haezadus, divrall, frank hag arveradus eo GNOME evit savennoù ar familh Unix.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bs">GNOME je slobodno, upotrebljivo, moćno i pristupačno radno okruženje za operativne sisteme nalik Unixu.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca">El GNOME és un entorn d'escriptori lliure, usable, estable i accessible per a la família de sistemes operatius tipus Unix.</p>
    <p xml:lang="crh">GNOME, Unix-vari işletim sistemleri ailesi içün Serbest, qullanışlı, istiqrarlı, irişilebilir bir masaüstü çevresidir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="cs">GNOME je svobodné, snadno použitelné, stabilní a přístupné pracovní prostředí, určené pro rodinu operačních systémů podobných Unixu.</p>
    <p xml:lang="cy">Mae GNOME yn amgylchedd penbwrdd Rhydd, defnyddiadwy, pwerus, sefydlog, hygyrch ar gyfer y teulu systemau gweithredu sy'n debyg i Unix.</p>
    <p xml:lang="da">Gnome er et frit og brugbart, stabilt og tilgængeligt skrivebordsmiljø til Unixlignende familie af styresystemer.</p>
    <p xml:lang="de">GNOME ist eine freie, einfach bedienbare, stabile und barrierefreie Desktop-Umgebung für die Familie UNIX-artiger Betriebssysteme.</p>
    <p xml:lang="dz">ཇི་ནོམ་འདི་ ཡུ་ནིགསི་བཟུམ་མའི་ རིགས་ཚན་གྱི་ གློག་རིག་བཀོལ་སྤྱོད་རིམ་ལུགས་ཚུ་གི་དོན་ལུ་ སྟོང་པར་དང་ ལག་ལེན་འཐབ་བཏུབ་ གཏན་ཏོག་ཏོ་ འཛུལ་སྤྱོད་འབད་བཏུབ་པའི་ ཌེཀསི་ཊོཔ་མཐའ་འཁོར་ཅིག་ཨིན།</p>
    <p xml:lang="el">Το Gnome, είναι ένα Ελεύθερο, σταθερό, εύχρηστο και προσβάσιμο περιβάλλον επιφάνειας εργασίας για την οικογένεια των λειτουργικών συστημάτων Unix.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en_CA">GNOME is a Free, usable, stable, accessible desktop environment for the Unix-like family of operating systems.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en_GB">GNOME is a Free, usable, stable, accessible desktop environment for the Unix-like family of operating systems.</p>
    <p xml:lang="eo">GNOME estas Libera, uzebla, stabila, alirebla tabula medio por la Uniksa familio de mastruma sistemo.</p>
    <p xml:lang="es">GNOME es un entorno de escritorio libre, útil, estable y accesible para la familia de sistemas operativos UNIX y similares.</p>
    <p xml:lang="et">GNOME on vaba, hõlpsasti kasutatav, stabiilne ning hõlbus töölauakeskkond Unixilaadsetele operatsioonisüsteemidele.</p>
    <p xml:lang="eu">GNOME mahaigaineko ingurune librea, erabilgarria eta egonkorra da, eta Unix-en antzeko sistema eragileen familiek erabil dezakete.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fa">گنوم یک محیط رومیزی آزاد، کارآ، باثبات و قابل دسترسی برای خانواده‌ی سیستم‌عامل‌های شبیه یونیکس است.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fi">Gnome on Vapaa, käytettävä, vakaa ja esteetön työpöytäympäristö Unix-tyyppisille käyttöjärjestelmille.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">GNOME est un environnement de bureau Libre, utilisable, stable et accessible pour les systèmes d'exploitations de type Un*x.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fur">GNOME al è un ambient desktop libar, doprabil, stabil e acessibil di bande di dute la famèe dai sistemis operatîfs tipo UNIX.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gl">O Gnome é un contorno de escritorio libre, usábel, estábel e accesíbel para a familia de sistemas operativos do estilo Unix.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gu">જીનોમ એ મુક્ત, વાપરી શકાય તેવુ, એક જગ્યાએ સ્થિત, યુનિક્સ જેવી ડેસ્કટોપ પર્યાવરણ સુલભ થાય તેવી ઓપરેટીંગ સિસ્ટમ છે.</p>
    <p xml:lang="he">‏GNOME הוא סביבת עבודה חופשית, שמישה, יציבה ונגישה למשפחת מערכות ההפעלה דמויות UNIX.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hi">यूनिक्स जैसे आपरेटिंग सिस्टम घरानों के लिए गनोम एक मुफ्त, उपयोगी, स्थिर, पंहुच योग्य डेस्कटॉप वातावरण है.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hr">GNOME je slobodano, korisno i stabilno radno okruženje za Unixoidne operativne sustave.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hu">A GNOME szabad, jól használható, megbízható és könnyen kezelhető asztali környezet a Unix-szerű operációs rendszerekhez.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hy">Գնոմը ազատ, օգտագործելի, կայուն հնարավորություններով աշխատանքային էկրան ունեցող միջավայր է գործարկվող համակարգերի Unix ընտանիքի համար։</p>
    <p xml:lang="id">GNOME program desktop yang bersifat bebas, berdaya guna, stabil, mudah diakses, yang dibuat khusus untuk sistem operasi keluarga Unix.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ig">GNOME bụ efu, dị̄ ōmúmé, kwụrụ chịm, dịkwa mfe mbanye nke desktọọpụ ebe maka dịka-Yuniksị ezinụlọ nke sistem usoroomumeihe.</p>
    <p xml:lang="is">GNOME er frjálst, nýtanlegt, stöðugt, aðgengilegt skjáviðmót fyrir Unix-skyldar fjölskyldur stýrikerfa.</p>
    <p xml:lang="it">GNOME è un ambiente desktop libero, usabile, stabile e accessibile per la famiglia di sistemi operativi tipo UNIX.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ja">GNOME は、UNIX ライクなオペレーティング・システム向けのフリーで使い勝手の良い、安定した、分かりやすいデスクトップ環境です。</p>
    <p xml:lang="ka">გნომი არის თავისუფალი, მარტივი, სტაბილური და ხელმისაწვდომი სამუშაო გარემო Unix-ის მაგვარი ოპერაციული სისტემებისათვის.</p>
    <p xml:lang="kk">GNOME - еркін, тұрақты, қолдануға қолайлы UNIX-like отбасылық оперативті система (ОС).</p>
    <p xml:lang="kn">GNOME ಯುನಿಕ್ಸ್‌ ಪಂಗಡದ ಕಾರ್ಯವ್ಯವಸ್ಥೆಗಳಲ್ಲಿನ ಉಚಿತವಾದ, ಬಳಸಬಹುದಾದ, ಸ್ಥಿರವಾದ, ನಿಲುಕಬಲ್ಲ ಒಂದು ಗಣಕತೆರೆ ಪರಿಸರವಾಗಿದೆ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ko">그놈은 유닉스와 같은 운영체제를 위한 자유롭고, 사용 가능하고, 안정적이고, 누구나 접근할 수 있는 데스크탑 환경입니다.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ku">GNOME, ji bo malbatên pergalên xebitandinê yên wekî Unix'ê derdoreke sermasê ya azad, bikêrhatî û bibiryar e.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ky">GNOME чөйрөсү UNIX-сыяктуу аракеттер системасы тутуму үчүн эркин, стабилдүү, колдонууда ыңгайлуу (анын ичинде мүмкүнчүлүктөрү чектелген адамдар үчүн да) иш чөйрөсү болуп эсептелет.</p>
    <p xml:lang="lt">GNOME yra Laisva, naši, stabili, prieinama darbo aplinka, skirta UNIX šeimos operacinėms sistemoms.</p>
    <p xml:lang="lv">GNOME ir brīva, lietojama, stabila un visiem pieejama darba vide UNIX tipa operētājsistēmām.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mai">यूनिक्स जहिना आपरेटिंग सिस्टम घराना क' लेल गनोम एकटा मुफ्त, उपयोगी, स्थिर, पहुँच योग्य डेस्कटाप वातावरण अछि.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mg">GNOME dia sehatr'asa maimaimpoana, azo ampiasaina tsara, marim-pototra ary mora ampiasaina amin'ny karazan-drafitra mitovy amin'ny Unix.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mk">GNOME е слободна, корисна, стабилна, пристапна работна околина за „Unix-like“ оперативните системи.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ml">യുണിക്സ് കുടുംബത്തിലെ പ്രവര്‍ത്തകസംവിധാനങ്ങള്‍ക്കായുള്ള ഒരു സ്വതന്ത്രവും ഉപയോഗയോഗ്യവും ഈടുറ്റതും സാമീപ്യവുമായ പണിയിട പരിസ്ഥിതിയാണു് ഗ്നോം.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mn">ГНОМЕ үнэгүй, хэрэглээ сайтай, тогтвортой, хялбархан Юникс төст төрлийн үйлдлийн системүүдэд зориулсан дэлгэцийн систем.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mr">GNOME मुक्त, वापरण्यायोग्य, स्थिर, मिळवण्याजोगे Unix सारख्या कार्यकारी प्रणालींसाठी कार्यस्थळ पर्यावरण आहे.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ms">GNOME adalah persekitaran desktop yang Bebas, bolehguna, stabil, bolehcapai bagu sistem pengoperasian keluarga seperti-Unix.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nb">GNOME er et fritt, brukervennlig, tilgjengelig og stabilt skrivebordsmiljø for UNIX-lignende operativsystemer.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ne">सञ्चालन प्रणालीको युनिक्स-जस्तै परिवारका लागि जीनोम स्वतन्त्र, उपयोगी, स्थायी, पहुँचयोग्य डेस्कटप परिवेश हो ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="nl">Gnome is een vrije (Libre), gebruiksvriendelijke, krachtige en toegankelijke werkomgeving voor de besturingssystemen die tot de Unix-familie behoren.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nn">GNOME er eit fritt, lettbrukt, stabilt og tilgjengeleg skrivebordsmiljø for UNIX-liknande operativsystem.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nso">GNOME ke tikologo ya teseke ya Bolokologi, e diriegago, e sa uthego, e tsenegago bakeng sa lapa le swanago le Unix la ditshepedio te omago.</p>
    <p xml:lang="oc">GNOME es un entorn de burèu liure, utilisable, estable e accessible per la familha dels sistèmas d'esplech del tipe Unix.</p>
    <p xml:lang="or">ୟୂନିକ୍ସ ଭଳି ପ୍ରଚାଳନ ତନ୍ତ୍ରର ପାଇଁ ନୋମ ଗୋଟିଏ ମୁକ୍ତ, ସୁସ୍ଥିର, ସୁଗମ ଡେସ୍କଟପ୍ ପରିବେଶ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pa">ਗਨੋਮ ਯੂਨੈਕਸ ਵਰਗੇ ਓਪਰੇਟਿੰਗ ਸਿਸਟਮ ਲਈ ਇਕ ਮੁਫਤ, ਇਸਤੇਮਾਲ ਲਈ ਤਿਆਰ, ਟਿਕਾਊ ਵੇਹੜਾ ਹੈ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="pl">GNOME jest wolnodostępnym, użytecznym, stabilnym, dostępnym środowiskiem graficznym dla systemów operacyjnych z rodziny Unix.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt">O GNOME é um ambiente de trabalho Livre, utilizável, estável e com acessibilidade para a familia Unix de sistemas operativos.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt_BR">O GNOME é um ambiente de trabalho livre, estável, acessível, e com boa usabilidade para sistemas operacionais da família dos Unix e similares.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ro">GNOME este un desktop liber, accesibil și stabil pentru familia de sisteme de operare Unix.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ru">Среда GNOME является свободным, стабильным, удобным для использования  окружением рабочего стола для семейства UNIX-подобных операционных систем.</p>
    <p xml:lang="si">GNOME යනු Unix හා සමාන මෙහෙයුම් පද්ධති සඳහා ස්වාධීන, ස්ථායි, වන භාවිතා කළහැකි, ලඟාවිය හැකි තිරමුහුණත් පරිසරයකි.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk">GNOME je slobodné, použiteľné, stabilné a dostupné prostredie pre rodinu operačných systémov Unix.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sl">GNOME je prosto, uporabno, stabilno in dostopno namizje za Unixu podobne operacijske sisteme.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sq">GNOME është një ambient pune për familjen e sistemeve operativë Unix-like, i përdorueshëm me lehtësi, i qëndrueshëm, i fuqishëm dhe i Lirë.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sr">Гном је слободно, употребљиво, моћно и приступачно радно окружење за оперативне системе налик Униксу.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sr@latin">Gnom je slobodno, upotrebljivo, moćno i pristupačno radno okruženje za operativne sisteme nalik Uniksu.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sv">GNOME är en fri, användbar, stabil och åtkomlig skrivbordsmiljö för den Unix-liknande familjen av operativsystem.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ta">GNOM இலவசமானது,நிலையானது,இயக்ககூடிய மேசை சூழல் யூணிக்ஸ் போன்ற குடும்ப இயக்க முறைமைகள்.</p>
    <p xml:lang="te">గ్నోమ్ అనేది ఒక యునిక్స్ లాంటి కార్యవ్యవస్థల కోసం  వాడు ఒక స్వతంత్ర, వినియోగకరమైన, స్థిర, సాంగత్య రంగస్థల పరిసరం.</p>
    <p xml:lang="th">GNOME เป็นระบบเดสก์ท็อปที่ให้เสรีภาพ สะดวกใช้ เสถียร และมีสิ่งอำนวยความสะดวกผู้ใช้ประเภทต่างๆ สำหรับระบบปฏิบัติการตระกูลยูนิกซ์</p>
    <p xml:lang="tk">GNOME Unix ýaly öpereýting sistemler üçin bir azat, peýdalanib boljok, gaýymwe el ýeterli desktap halkasy dir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="tr">GNOME, Unix benzeri işletim sistemleri ailesi için özgür, kullanılabilir, kararlı ve erişilebilir masaüstü ortamıdır.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">Середовище GNOME є вільним, стабільним, зручним (в тому числі й для людей з обмеженими можливостями) середовищем робочого столу для Юнікс-подібних операційних систем.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uz">GNOME UNIX oilasidagi operatsion tizimlar uchun erkin, moʻʼtadil, qulay ish stoli muhitidir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uz@cyrillic">GNOME UNIX оиласидаги операцион тизимлар учун эркин, мўътадил, қулай иш столи муҳитидир.</p>
    <p xml:lang="vi">GNOME là môi trường bàn làm việc tự do, khả dụng, ổn định, dễ truy cập cho các hệ điều hành họ Unix.</p>
    <p xml:lang="wa">Gnome est on libe, ahessåve, sitocaesse,eyet accessibe evironmint di scribanne po les sistinmes d' operance del famile des rshonnants a Unix.</p>
    <p xml:lang="xh">I-GNOME Yimeko eguqukayo elungeleneyo yolwazi olukwiskrini ekhululekileyo, esebenzisekayo, engagungqiyo, nefikelelekayo ukwenzela usapho olufana nolwe-Unix lweenkqubo zokusebenza.</p>
    <p xml:lang="yo">GNOME Jẹ oun tí ò gbààyè, tì o ṣé lò, tí o fẹsẹ múlẹ, abánirẹ àyíká ìlànà kọmpútà fún ojúlùmọ Unix ti ìdarí kọmpútà</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_CN">对于类 Unix 家族操作系统来说，GNOME 桌面环境完全自由、可用性强、功能强劲。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_HK">GNOME 是一套自由、易用而且穩定的桌面環境，支援無障礙環境，可在 Unix 類型的作業系統中運行。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_TW">GNOME 是一套自由、易用而且穩定的桌面環境，支援無障礙環境，可在 Unix 類型的作業系統中運行。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zu">GNOME imahala, iyasebenziseka, iyangenela endwaweni yokusentshenzelwa ebusweni besiga-nyezi njengomndeni we UNIX.</p>
    <p>GNOME includes most of what you see on your computer, including the file manager, web browser, menus, and many applications.</p>
    <p xml:lang="af">GNOME sluit meeste van dit wat jy op jou rekenaar sien in, insluitend die lêerbestuurder, webblaaier, kieslyste en vele toepassings.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ar">يتضمن جنوم معظم ما تراه على حاسوبك شاملة مدير الملفّات و متصفّح الوِب و القوائم و العديد من التطبيقات.</p>
    <p xml:lang="as">কম্পিউটাৰৰ প্ৰেক্ষাপটে প্ৰদৰ্শিত অধিকাংশ বিষয়বস্তু যিনে নথিপত্ৰ পৰিচালন ব্যৱস্থা, ৱেব চৰক, মেনু প্ৰভৃতি অন্যান্য এপ্লিকেশন GNOME-ত অন্তৰ্ভুক্ত আছে ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="ast">GNOME inclúi la mayoría de lo que pues atopar nel to ordenador, como l'alministrador de ficheros, el navegador web y delles más aplicaciones.</p>
    <p xml:lang="az">Kompüterinizdə ehtiyacınız olan hər şeyi GNOME daxil edir. Bunun içində fayl idarəçisi, menyular və veb səyyahı kimi bir çox proqram daxildir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="be">GNOME уключае ў сябе большую частку таго, што вы бачыце на сваім кампутары: кіраўнік фаўлаў, вандроўнік павуціньня, мэню і многія іншыя дастасаваньні.</p>
    <p xml:lang="be@latin">GNOME uklučaje bolšaść z taho, čym ty karystajeśsia na kamputary, u tym liku kiraŭnika fajłaŭ, web-hartača, menu i inšyja aplikacyi.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bg">GNOME включва повечето от това, което виждате на компютъра си, включително файлов мениджър и браузър за Интернет, менюта и много програми.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bn">ফাইল ম্যানেজার, ওয়েব ব্রাউজার, মেনু এবং অন্যান্য অ্যাপলিকেশন, আপনি যা-ই আপনারকম্পিঊটারে দেখতে চান তার সবই গনোমে সংযুক্ত করা হয়েছে।</p>
    <p xml:lang="bn_IN">কম্পিউটারের প্রেক্ষাপটে প্রদর্শিত অধিকাংশ বিষয়বস্তু যেমন ফাইল পরিচালন ব্যবস্থা, ওয়েব ব্রাউজার, মেনু প্রভৃতি অন্যান্য অ্যাপ্লিকেশন GNOME-র মধ্যে অন্তর্ভুক্ত রয়েছে।</p>
    <p xml:lang="br">Kavet 'vez 'barzh GNOME pep tra 'benn implijout ho urzhiataer, an evezhier restroù, an diskouezer web, bouestigoù dibab, ha lod a poelladoù mezianteg a bep seurt.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bs">GNOME sadrži većinu onoga što vidite na vašem računaru, uključujući i menadžer datoteka, preglednik weba, menije i mnoge programe.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca">El GNOME inclou gairebé tot el que veieu al vostre ordinador: el gestor de fitxers, navegador de web, menús i moltes altres aplicacions.</p>
    <p xml:lang="crh">GNOME, dosye idarecisi, ağ kezicisi, menüler ve çoq uyğulama dahil, bilgisayarıñızda körgenleriñizniñ ekseriyetini kirsete.</p>
    <p xml:lang="cs">GNOME zahrnuje většinu z toho, co ve svém počítači vidíte, včetně správce souborů, webového prohlížeče, nabídek a mnoha aplikací.</p>
    <p xml:lang="cy">Mae GNOME yn cynnwys y rhan fwyaf o beth rydych chi'n ei weld ar eich cyfrifiadur, yn cynnwys y rhelolydd ffeiliau, dewislenni, a llawer o rhaglenni.</p>
    <p xml:lang="da">Gnome er det meste af det du ser på dit system, inklusive filhåndteringen, webbrowser, menuerne og alle de andre programmer.</p>
    <p xml:lang="de">GNOME schließt das meiste von dem ein, was Sie auf Ihrem Computer sehen, einschließlich eines Dateimanagers, eines Webbrowsers, der Menüs und vieler Anwendungen.</p>
    <p xml:lang="dz">ཇི་ནོམ་ནང་ལུ་ ཡིག་སྣོད་འཛིན་སྐྱོང་པ་དང་ ཝེབ་བའརུ་ཟར དཀར་ཆག་ དེ་ལས་ གློག་རིམ་ལེ་ཤ་བརྩིས་ཏེ་ ང་བཅས་རའི་གློག་རིག་ནང་ མཐོང་མི་མང་ཤོས་རང་ཚུད་དེ་ཡོད།</p>
    <p xml:lang="el">Το GNOME περιλαμβάνει τα περισσότερα από όσα βλέπετε στον υπολογιστή σας, συμπεριλαμβανομένου του διαχειριστή αρχείων, του περιηγητή στο διαδίκτυο, των μενού και πολλών εφαρμογών.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en_CA">GNOME includes most of what you see on your computer, including the file manager, web browser, menus, and many applications.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en_GB">GNOME includes most of what you see on your computer, including the file manager, web browser, menus, and many applications.</p>
    <p xml:lang="eo">GNOME enhavas plejmulton de kio vi vidas en via komputilo, kiel la dosieradministrilo, TTT-retumilo, menuoj, kaj multaj aplikaĵoj.</p>
    <p xml:lang="es">GNOME incluye la mayoría de lo que ve en su equipo, incluyendo el administrador de archivos, navegador web, los menús y muchas aplicaciones.</p>
    <p xml:lang="et">GNOME sisaldab enamust, mida sul võib oma arvutis vaja minna, kaasa arvatud failihaldur, veebibrauser, menüüd ja paljud rakendused.</p>
    <p xml:lang="eu">GNOMEk ordenagailuan ikusten dituzun gauza gehienak ditu, baita fitxategi-kudeatzailea, web arakatzailea, menuak eta hainbat aplikazio ere.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fa">گنوم بیشتر چیزهایی را که در کامپیوتر خود می‌بینید در بر دارد، از جمله مرورگر پرونده، مرورگر وب، منوها و تعداد زیادی برنامه.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fi">Gnomeen kuuluu suurin osa siitä, mitä tietokoneen ruudulla yleensä näkyy, kuten tiedostonhallinta, WWW-selain, valikot ja monet sovellukset.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">GNOME inclut la plupart de ce que vous voyez sur votre ordinateur, y compris le gestionnaire de fichiers, le navigateur Web, les menus et la plupart des applications.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fur">GNOME al inclût scuasite dut di ce ch'a si viôt sul computer, comprendût il file manager, un sgarfad pal web, i menu e cetantis aplicazions.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gl">O Gnome inclúe a maioría do que pode encontrar nun computador, como o xestor de ficheiros, o navegador web, os menús e moitas aplicacións.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gu">જીનોમ ફાઈલ વ્યવસ્થાપક, વેબ બ્રાઉઝર, મેનુઓ, અને ઘણા બધા કાર્યક્રમો ઉપરાંત મોટા ભાગની વસ્તુઓ કે જે તમારા ડેસ્કટોપ પર દેખાય છે તેનો સમાવેશ કરે છે.</p>
    <p xml:lang="he">‏GNOME כולל את רוב הדברים שאתה רואה במחשב שלך, כולל את מנהל הקבצים, דפדפן האינטרנט, תפריטים ויישומים רבים.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hi">जो भी आप अपने कम्प्यूटर में देखते हैं, उनमें से अधिकतर गनोम में सम्मिलित हैं, जिनमें शामिल हैं- फ़ाइल मैनेजर, वेब ब्राउज़र, मेन्यू तथा और भी ढेरों अनुप्रयोग.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hr">GNOME uključuje većinu onoga što vidite na računalu, uključujući upravitelja datotekama, web preglednik, izbornike i mnoge aplikacije.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hu">A GNOME tartalmazza mindazt, ami a számítógépen látszik, beleértve a fájlkezelőt, a webböngészőt, a menüket és sok alkalmazást.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hy">Գնոմը ընդգրկում է այն ամենը, ինչ դուք տեսնում եք ձեր համակարգչի վրա, ներառելով ֆայլ մենեջերին, ցանցի բրաուզերն, մենյուները և շատ կիրառական ծրագրեր։</p>
    <p xml:lang="id">GNOME menyertakan hampir semua yang Anda lihat dalam komputer ini, termasuk pengatur berkas, perambah web, menu-menu, dan aplikasi lainnya.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ig">GNOME na-etinye ụfọdụ ihe ị na-ahụ na kọmputa gị, tinyere onyenlekọta faịlụ, omenchọgharị weebụ, menus, nakwa ọtụtụ usoroiheomume ndị ahụ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="is">GNOME inniheldur stóran hluta af því sem þú sérð í tölvunni þinni. Þar má nefna skráarstjóra, vefvafra, valmyndir og fjöldan allan af forritum.</p>
    <p xml:lang="it">GNOME include la maggior parte di quello che è visibile sul computer, compresi il file manager, il web browser, i menù e molte applicazioni.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ja">GNOME ではお使いのコンピュータで目に見えるもののほとんどを提供し、ファイル・マネージャ、ウェブ・ブラウザ、メニュー、そしてたくさんのアプリケーションがあります。</p>
    <p xml:lang="ka">გნომი შეიცავს თქვენი კომპიუტერისთვის საჭირო ძირითად გადაწყვეტებს, მათ შორის ფაილ მენეჯერს, ვებ-ბრაუზერს, მენიუებს და მრავალ პროგრამას.</p>
    <p xml:lang="kk">GNOME ортасының құамында файл мереджерін, веб-беттерді ашатын браузерді, мәзір панелін және т.б. кездестіре аласыз.</p>
    <p xml:lang="kn">GNOME ನಲ್ಲಿ ಗಣಕದಲ್ಲಿ ಕಾಣಸಿಗುವ ಕಡತವ್ವವಸ್ಥಾಪಕ, ಜಾಲ ವೀಕ್ಷಕ, ಮೆನುಗಳು, ಹಾಗು ಇನ್ನಿತರೆ ಎಲ್ಲಾ ಅನ್ವಯಗಳನ್ನು ಒಳಗೊಂಡಿದೆ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ko">그놈에는 컴퓨터에서 할 수 있는 모든 것이 들어 있습니다. 파일 관리자, 웹 브라우저, 메뉴, 그리고 많은 응용 프로그램들까지.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ku">GNOME; rêvebira pelan, vegêroka webê, pêşekan û gelek sepanên din ku di komputera xwe de dibînî, di nava xwe de dihewîne.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ky">GNOME чөйрөсү файл менеджери, веб-барактарды аралагыч, меню панели ж.б.у.с. эң керектүү иштемелерди көпчүлүгүн камтыйт.</p>
    <p xml:lang="lt">GNOME aplinkoje yra dauguma norimų programų: failų naršyklė, interneto naršyklė, įvairūs meniu ir daug kitų programų.</p>
    <p xml:lang="lv">GNOME sevī iekļauj lielāko daļu no tā, ko jūs redzat uz datora, ieskaitot failu pārvaldnieku, tīkla pārlūku, izvēlnes un daudzas programmas.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mai">जेहो अहाँ अपन कम्प्यूटरमे देखैत छी, ओकरासँ बेसी गनोममे सम्मिलित अछि, जकरामे सामिल अछि - फाइल मैनेजर, वेब ब्राउज़र, मेनूसभ आ आओर ढ़ेरी अनुप्रयोगसभ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mg">Misy ao amin'ny GNOME ny ankabiazan'ireo zavatra hitanao amin'ny solosainao, toy ny mpandrindra rakitra, ny mpizaha tranonkala, ny karazan-tsafidy, ary rindran'asa maro samihafa.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mk">GNOME ги вклучува повеќето работи што ги гледате на Вашиот компјутер, заедно со менаџерите за датотеки, веб прелистувачите, менијата и многу апликации.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ml">ഫയല്‍ മാനേജ്മെന്റ്, വെബ് ബ്രൌസര്‍, മെനുകള്‍ കൂടാതെ പല പ്രയോഗങ്ങളും ഉള്‍‌പ്പെ‌ടെ നിങ്ങളുടെ കമ്പ്യൂട്ടറില്‍ കാണുന്നതിലധികവും ഉള്‍‌ക്കൊള്ളുന്നതാണു് ഗ്നോം.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mn">ГНОМЕ таны компьютер харагдах ихэнх програмууд болох файл хянагч, вэб хөтөч, цэснүүд болон өөр олон х.програмуудыг агуулна.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mr">GNOME मध्ये तुम्ही तुमच्या संगणकावरील दृश्य अशा बहुतांश बाबींचा समावेश होतो, जसे फाइल व्यवस्थापक, वेब ब्राउझर, मेनू, आणि अनेक अनुप्रयोग.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ms">GNOME disertakan kebanyakan drpd apa yang anda lihat pada komputer anda, termasuk pengurus fail, pelungsur web, menu dan banyak aplikasi.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nb">GNOME tilbyr det meste av det du vanligvis finner på en datamaskin; filhåndterer, nettleser, menyer og mange programmer.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ne">जिनोमले तपाईँले आफ्नो कम्प्युरटरमा देखेको फाइल प्रबन्धक, वेब ब्राउजर, मेनुहरू र धेरै अनुप्रयोगहरू समेत धेरै जसो समावेश गर्दछ ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="nl">Gnome is hetgeen waarmee u werkt en wat op uw computer zichtbaar is, waaronder het bestandsbeheer, de menu's, en diverse toepassingen zoals een web-browser.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nn">GNOME har det meste av det du ser på datamaskinen din, inkludert ein filhandsamar, ein nettlesar, menyar og mange applikasjonar.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nso">GNOME e akareta bontsi bja seo o se bonago khomphuthareng ya gago, go akareta le molaodi wa faele, go fetleka wepe, malokelelo a dikagare, le ditirio te dinti.</p>
    <p xml:lang="oc">GNOME conten la màger part de çò que vesètz sus vòstre ordenador, enclaus lo gestionari de fichièrs, lo navigador internet, los menuts e fòrça logicials.</p>
    <p xml:lang="or">ଆପଣଙ୍କ କମ୍ପ୍ଯୁଟରରେ ଅଧିକାଂଶ ଦୃଶ୍ଯମାନ ବସ୍ତୁ ନୋମରେ ସମ୍ମିଳିତ, ଫାଇଲ ପରିଚାଳକ, ୱେବ ଖୋଜାଳୀ, ମେନୁଗୁଡ଼ିକ ଓ ଅନେକ ପ୍ରୟୋଗ ସହ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pa">ਗਨੋਮ ਵਿੱਚ ਉਹ ਸਭ ਕੁਝ ਹੈ, ਜੋ ਤੁਸੀ ਆਪਣੀ ਮਸ਼ੀਨ ਤੇ ਵੇਖਣਾ ਚਾਹੋਗੇ, ਜਿਵੇਂ ਕਿ ਫਾਇਲ ਪਰਬੰਧਕ, ਵੈੱਬ ਝਲਕਾਰਾ, ਮੇਨੂ ਅਤੇ ਹੋਰ ਕੰਮ ਦੀਆਂ ਕਾਰਜ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="pl">GNOME zawiera większość tego co widać na ekranie komputera, włączając menedżera plików, przeglądarkę internetową, menu i wiele programów.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt">GNOME representa a maior parte do que vê no seu computador, incluindo o gestor de ficheiros, o navegador web, menus e muitas aplicações.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt_BR">O GNOME inclui a maior parte do que você vê no seu computador, como o gerenciador de arquivos, o navegador da Internet, e muitos aplicativos.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ro">GNOME include majoritatea aplicațiilor vizibile: managerul de fișiere, navigatorul web, meniurile și multe alte programe.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ru">Среда GNOME включает в себя большую часть того, что вы видите на вашем компьютере, в том числе файловый менеджер, браузер веб-страниц, панель меню и многое другое.</p>
    <p xml:lang="si">ඔබ පරිගණකයේ දකින, බොහෝ ගොනු කළමණාකරු, වියණු ජාලනය, මෙනු සහ බොහෝ යෙදුම් GNOME හි අඩංගුව ඇත.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk">GNOME obsahuje väčšinu toho, čo potrebujete na svojom počítači, ako je správca súborov, internetový prehliadač, ponuky a veľa aplikácií.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sl">GNOME vključuje večino stvari, ki jih vidite na zaslonu, vključno z upravljalnikom datotek, spletnim brskalnikom, meniji in mnogimi programi.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sq">GNOME përfshin pjesën më të madhe të çfarë shikoni në kompjuterin tuaj, përfshirë organizuesin e file, shfletuesin web, menutë, dhe shumë programe.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sr">Гном садржи већину онога што видите на вашем рачунару, укључујући и управљача датотекама, читач веба, меније, и многе програме.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sr@latin">Gnom sadrži većinu onoga što vidite na vašem računaru, uključujući i upravljača datotekama, čitač veba, menije, i mnoge programe.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sv">GNOME innehåller det mesta av vad du ser på din dator, inklusive filhanteraren, webbläsaren, menyer, och många program.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ta">GNOME உட்பட உங்கள் கணிப்பொறியில் உள்ளதை பாருங்கள் கோப்பு மேலாளர்,வலை உலாவி,பட்டைகள் மற்றும் பல பயன்பாடுகள். </p>
    <p xml:lang="te">గ్నోమ్ లో మీరు కంప్యూటర్ పై చూసే దస్త్ర నిర్వాహకి , మహాతల అన్వేషి , జాబితాలు మరియు అనేక కార్యక్షేత్రాలు మొదలగు  నవన్నీ వుండును</p>
    <p xml:lang="th">GNOME ประกอบไปด้วย สิ่งที่คุณเห็นอยู่บนจอเกือบทั้งหมด เช่น ตัวจัดการแฟ้ม เว็บเบราว์เซอร์ เมนู และ โปรแกรมอื่น ๆ อีกมากมาย</p>
    <p xml:lang="tk">Siz näme kampýuterdä görýan bolsaňiz meslen faýl mäneýjer, web browzer,menöwlar we yene kän äplikeýşenleri GNOME taýýarlapdir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="tr">GNOME bilgisayarınızda gördüğünüz; dosya yöneticisini, web tarayıcısını, menüleri, ve başka bir çok uygulamayı içerir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">GNOME включає в себе багато найпотрібніших програм, серед яких є файловий менеджер, веб-переглядач, панель меню і багато додатків.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uz">GNOME'da kompyuteringiz uchun kerak boʻlgan fayl boshqaruvchisi, veb brauzer, menyular va koʻplab boshqa dasturlar mavjud.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uz@cyrillic">GNOME'да компьютерингиз учун керак бўлган файл бошқарувчиси, веб браузер, менюлар ва кўплаб бошқа дастурлар мавжуд.</p>
    <p xml:lang="vi">GNOME bao gồm hầu hết mọi thứ mà bạn cần có trên máy của mình, bao gồm trình quản lí tập tin, trình duyệt mạng, các trình đơn và hàng loạt các ứng dụng.</p>
    <p xml:lang="wa">Gnome inclût li plupårt di çou k' vos voeyoz so vosse copiutrece, ça vout dire eto li manaedjeu di fitchîs, li betchteu waibe, les menus, et bråmint des programes.</p>
    <p xml:lang="xh">I-GNOME ibandakanya okona kuninzi okubona ekhompyutheni yakho, kubandakanywa umlawuli wefayili, isikhangeli se-web, iimenyu, neenkqubo eziliqela zekhompyutha.</p>
    <p xml:lang="yo">GNOME pẹlúu ọpọ àwọn ohun tí ó yọ lójú kọmpútà, tí ò pẹlú páálí ìwéolùdarí, ìbojúwo ìwunpọ, ètò, àti ọpọlọpọ ìdarí kọmpútà.</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_CN">GNOME 囊括了您计算机上最经常使用的软件，如文件管理器、菜单和像浏览器这样的应用程序。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_HK">GNOME 包括你最常用的東西，包括檔案總管、網頁瀏覽器、選單和許多應用程式。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_TW">GNOME 包括您最常用的東西，包括檔案總管、網頁瀏覽器、選單和許多應用程式。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zu">GNOME uphethe kwisiga-nyezi, njengomphathi hele, okulayaluza kwelwembu, uhlu, nezisentshenziso eziningi.</p>
    <p>GNOME also includes a complete development platform for applications programmers, allowing the creation of powerful and complex applications.</p>
    <p xml:lang="af">GNOME bevat ook 'n volledige ontwikkelingsplatform vir toepassings-programmeerders, wat die skep van kragtige en komplekse toepassings toelaat.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ar">يتضمّن جنوم كذلك منصّة تطوير كاملة لمبرمجي التطبيقات، ممّا يمكّنهم من إنشاء تطبيقات قوية و معقّدة.</p>
    <p xml:lang="as">GNOME-ত উন্নত ক্ষমতাসম্পন্ন আৰু জটিল এপ্লিকেশন নিৰ্মাণৰ বাবে বিভিন্ন উপকৰণসহ এপ্লিকেশন নিৰ্মাতাৰ বাবে সম্পূৰ্ণ বিকাশ প্লেটফৰ্ম উপস্থিত কৰা হৈছে ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="ast">GNOME inclúi tamién una completa plataforma de desendolcu pa los programadores d'aplicaciones, que permite la creación de potentes y complexos programes.</p>
    <p xml:lang="az">GNOME eyni zamanda inkişafçılara qarışıq və güclü tə'minatlar yaratma imkanı verən inkişaf platformunu da daxil edir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="be">Таксама GNOME уключае поўную плятформу для распрацоўкі, якая дазваляе праграмэрам ствараць магутныя і цэльныя дастасаваньні.</p>
    <p xml:lang="be@latin">GNOME taksama źjaŭlajecca samadastatkovaj platformaj raspracoŭvańnia aplikacyjaŭ, jakaja dazvalaje stvarać mahutnyja i składanyja prahramnyja kompleksy.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bg">GNOME включва и завършена платформа за разработка, която позволява създаването на сложни и мощни програми.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bn">শক্তিশালী ও জটিল অ্যাপলিকেশন সৃষ্টির অনুমতি দিয়ে, অ্যাপলিকেশন প্রোগ্রামারদের জন্য গনোম সম্পূর্ণ ডেভালপারদের একটি প্লাটফর্মের সঙ্গে যুক্ত করে।</p>
    <p xml:lang="bn_IN">GNOME-র মধ্যে উন্নত ক্ষমতাসম্পন্ন ও জটিল অ্যাপ্লিকেশন নির্মাণের জন্য বিভিন্ন উপকরণসহ অ্যাপ্লিকেশন নির্মাতাদের জন্য সম্পূর্ণ ডিভেলপমেন্ট প্ল্যাটফর্ম উপস্থিত করা হয়েছে।</p>
    <p xml:lang="br">GNOME a ginnig ur steudad klok a ostilhoù evit ar saverien meziantoù. Tu 'zo da grouiñ meziantoù luzius ha galloudus.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bs">GNOME sadrži i razvojnu platformu koja omogućava programerima da prave nove složene i moćne programe.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca">El GNOME també inclou una completa plataforma de desenvolupament per a programadors d'aplicacions, que permet crear-ne de tot tipus.</p>
    <p xml:lang="crh">GNOME bir de uyğulama programcıları içün quvetli ve pıtraqlı uyğulamalarnı icat ete bilecekleri tam bir inkişaf platformasını kirsete.</p>
    <p xml:lang="cs">GNOME také poskytuje úplnou vývojovou platformu pro programátory aplikací, umožňující tvorbu mocných a komplexních aplikací.</p>
    <p xml:lang="cy">Mae GNOME hefyd yn cynnwys llwyfan datblygaeth cyflawn ar gyfer rhaglennwyr rhaglennu, sy'n caniatau creu rhaglenni pwerus a chymleth.</p>
    <p xml:lang="da">Gnome er også en komplet udviklingsplatform for programmører der muliggør skabelsen af stærke og komplekse programmer.</p>
    <p xml:lang="de">GNOME umfasst auch eine vollständige Entwicklungsplattform für Anwendungsentwickler, die das Erstellen von mächtigen und komplexen Anwendungen erlaubt.</p>
    <p xml:lang="dz">ཇི་ནོམ་ནང་ལུ་ གློག་རིམ་ལས་རིམ་པ་ཚུ་གིས་ ནུས་ཤུགས་ཅན་དང་ རྒྱས་སྤྲོས་ལྡན་པའི་ གློག་རིམ་ཚུ་ གསར་བསྐྲུན་འབད་བཅུག་ནིའི་ གོང་འཕེལ་གོ་སྐབས་ཆ་ཚང་ཅིག་ཡང་ཡོདཔ་ཨིན།</p>
    <p xml:lang="el">Το GNOME ακόμα περιλαμβάνει μια πλήρη πλατφόρμα ανάπτυξης για προγραμματιστές εφαρμογών, και επιτρέπει τη δημιουργία δυναμικών και πολύπλοκων εφαρμογών.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en_CA">GNOME also includes a complete development platform for application programmers, allowing the creation of powerful and complex applications.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en_GB">GNOME also includes a complete development platform for applications programmers, allowing the creation of powerful and complex applications.</p>
    <p xml:lang="eo">GNOME ankaŭ inkludas kompletan programan ilaron por aplikaĵaj programistoj. Tiuj iloj ebligas la kreon de potencaj kaj kompleksaj aplikaĵoj.</p>
    <p xml:lang="es">GNOME también incluye una completa plataforma de desarrollo para los programadores de aplicaciones, permitiéndoles la creación de aplicaciones complejas y potentes.</p>
    <p xml:lang="et">GNOME sisaldab ühtlasi täielikku arendusplatvormi rakenduste programmeerijatele, võimaldades luua võimsaid ja keerukaid rakendusi.</p>
    <p xml:lang="eu">GNOMEk garapen-plataforma osoa ere badu, programatzaileek aplikazio ahaltsuak eta konplexuak sor ditzaten.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fa">گنوم همچنین دارای یک سکوی برنامه‌سازی کامل برای برنامه‌نویسان است، که به کار ایجاد برنامه‌های قوی و پیچیده می‌آید.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fi">Gnomessa on myös täydellinen ohjelmistokehitysympäristö, jolla voi luoda tehokkaita ja mutkikkaita ohjelmia.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">GNOME inclut aussi une plateforme complète de développement pour les développeurs d'applications leur permettant la création d'applications puissantes et complexes.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fur">Cun GNOME a ven furnide une plataforme complete di svilup par i programadôrs, rindint pussibil la creazion di aplicazions potentis e complessis.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gl">O Gnome inclúe tamén unha completa plataforma de desenvolvemento para os programadores. Así, permite crear aplicacións potentes e complexas.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gu">જીનોમ પણ કાર્યક્રમ પ્રોગ્રામરો માટે સંપૂર્ણ વિકાસનું પ્લેટફોર્મ પૂરું પાડે છે, કે જે તમને શક્તિશાળી અને જટિલ કાર્યક્રમો બનાવવાની પરવાનગી પરવાનગી આપે છે.</p>
    <p xml:lang="he">‏GNOME כולל גם פלטפורמת פיתוח שלמה למפתחי יישומים, המאפשרת יצירה של יישומים חזקים ומורכבים.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hi">अनुप्रयोग प्रोग्रामर्स के लिए एक संपूर्ण विकास मंच (डेवलपमेंट प्लेटफॉर्म) भी गनोम में सम्मिलित है, जो क्षमता युक्त जटिल अनुप्रयोगों की सृष्टि में सक्षम है.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hr">Gnome uključuje potpuno razvojno okruženje za programere aplikacija, omogućujući stvaranje moćnih i složenih aplikacija.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hu">A GNOME egyúttal teljes fejlesztőkörnyezet is az alkalmazásfejlesztők számára, segítségével sokoldalú és összetett programokat lehet létrehozni.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hy">Գնոմը նաև ընդգրկում է մշակման լիարժեք պլատֆորմ կիրառական ծրագրեր մշակողների համար, հնարավորություն ընձեռելով ստեղծել հզոր և կոմպլեքսային կիրառական ծրագրեր։</p>
    <p xml:lang="id">GNOME juga menyertakan sekumpulan aplikasi pembangunan yang komplet, yang dapat Anda gunakan untuk membuat aplikasi yang hebat dan rumit.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ig">GNOME na-etinyekwa ebenzipụta ntolite ozuzuoke maka ndị ọrụụ usoroiheomume kọmputa, na-ekwe nkewapụta nke usoroiheomume ndị siri ike na nke gbagwojuru anya.</p>
    <p xml:lang="is">GNOME inniheldur einnig upp á heilsteyptan þróunarverkvang fyrir þróendur forrita sem gerir þróendum kleyft að þróa öflug og flókin forrit. </p>
    <p xml:lang="it">Con GNOME viene fornita anche una completa piattaforma di sviluppo per i programmatori, rendendo possibile la creazione di applicazioni efficaci e complesse.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ja">さらに GNOME はアプリケーション開発者のために完成した開発用プラットフォームを提供し、強力で複雑なアプリケーションを開発することができます。</p>
    <p xml:lang="ka">გნომი აგრეთვე შეიცავს პროგრამირების სრულყოფილ პლატფორმას პროგრამისტებისათვის, რომელიც ძლიერი და კომპლექსური პროგრამების შექმნის საშუალებას იძლევა.</p>
    <p xml:lang="kk">GNOME-да тағы да дайын болған тұғырнама, программистерге мықты айқындауыштарды құруға мүмкіндік береді.</p>
    <p xml:lang="kn">GNOME ನಲ್ಲಿ ಅನ್ವಯಗಳ ಪ್ರೊಗ್ರಾಮರುಗಳಿಗಾಗು ಒಂದು ಸಂಪೂರ್ಣ ವಿಕಸನಾ ಪ್ಲಾಟ್‌ಫಾರ್ಮ್ ಇದ್ದು, ಅದು ಶಕ್ತಿಯುತವಾದ ಹಾಗು ಸಂಕೀರ್ಣವಾದ ಅನ್ವಯಗಳನ್ನು ನಿರ್ಮಿಸಲು ಅನುವು ಮಾಡಿಕೊಡುತ್ತದೆ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ko">그놈에는 응용 프로그램 개발자가 이용할 수 있는 완전한 개발 플랫폼이 들어 있습니다. 이 플랫폼으로 강력하고 방대한 응용 프로그램을 만들 수 있습니다.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ku">GNOME di nava xwe de, wekî din, platformeke bêkêmasî ya pêşxistinê ku pêşxistinkarên sepanan dikarin pê sepanên bihêz û tevlihev biafirînin, dihewîne.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ky">Ошондой эле GNOME чөйрөсү кубаттуу жана татаал иштемелерди түзүүгө жол берүүчү даяр платформаны камтыйт.</p>
    <p xml:lang="lt">GNOME aplinkoje taip pat yra išsami programavimo platforma programų kūrėjams, leidžianti kurti galingas ir sudėtingas programas.</p>
    <p xml:lang="lv">GNOME sevī iekļauj arī pilnvērtīgu programmatūras izstrādes platformu, kas ļauj veidot dažādas daudzfunkcionālas un sarežģītas programmas.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mai">अनुप्रयोग प्रोग्रामरसभक लेल एकटा संपूर्ण विकास मंच (डेवलपमेंट प्लेटफार्म) गनोममे सम्मिलितअछि, जे क्षमतायुक्त जटिल अनुप्रयोगक सृष्टिमे सक्षम अछि.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mg">GNOME dia manana sehatra famolavolana feno ho an'ireo mpamolavola rindran'asa, entina hamoronana rindran'asa matanjaka ary maro sosona.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mk">GNOME вклучува комплетна платформа за развивање на апликации со што се дозволува брзо создавање на моќни и комплексни апликации.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ml">ശക്തവും സങ്കീര്‍ണവുമായ പ്രയോഗങ്ങളുടെ സൃഷ്ടി അനുവദിച്ചു് കൊണ്ടു് പ്രയോഗരചയിതാക്കള്‍ക്കായി ഒരു സമ്പൂര്‍ണ്ണ വികസനവേദി ഗ്നോം ഉള്‍‌ക്കൊള്ളുന്നു.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mn">ГНОМЕ түүнчилэн бүрэн дүүрэн системийн болон хэрэглээний хүчирхэг хэцүү янз бүрийн програмууд хөгжүүлэх ба үүсгэх суурь агуулна.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mr">GNOME मध्ये अनुप्रयोग कार्यक्रमकांसाठी संपूर्ण विकास मंचाचा समावेश होतो, ज्यामुळे शक्तिशाली आणि संकीर्ण अनुप्रयोग निर्माण करता येतात.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ms">GNOME juga disertakan dengan satu platform pembangunan bagi pengaturcara aplikasi, membolehkan penciptaan aplikasi yang berkuasan dan kompleks.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nb">GNOME inkluderer også en komplett utviklingsplattform for programutviklere som gjør det mulig å lage kraftige og komplekse programmer.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ne">अनुप्रयोग कार्यक्रमहरूको लागि जिनोमले पनि शक्तिशाली र जटिल अनुप्रयोगहरूको सिर्जनालाई अनुमति दिँदै एउटा पुर्ण विकास मञ्च समावेश गर्दछ ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="nl">Gnome bevat tevens een compleet platform voor softwareontwikkelaars waarmee krachtige en complexe toepassingen kunnen worden gebouwd.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nn">GNOME har også ein komplett utviklingsplattform for applikasjonsutviklarar. Denne plattformen gjer det mogleg å laga kraftige og innfløkte applikasjonar.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nso">GNOME gape e akareta twelopele e feletego ya sethala bakeng sa barulaganyi ba ditirio, e dumelela go hlangwa ga ditirio te matla le te di raraganego.</p>
    <p xml:lang="oc">GNOME conten tanben una plataforma completa de desvolopament pels programaires de logicials, çò que permet de crear de programas potents e complèxes.</p>
    <p xml:lang="or">ପ୍ରୟୋଗ ଲେଖକ ପାଇଁ ଗୋଚିଏ ସମ୍ପୂର୍ଣ୍ଣ ବିକାସ ମଞ୍ଚ ମଧ୍ଯ ନୋମରେ ସମ୍ମିଳିତ, ଯେଉଁଟାକି ଶକ୍ତିଶାଳୀ ଓ ଜଟିଳ ପ୍ରୟୋଗ ସୃଷ୍ତି କରିବାକୁ ଦିଏ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pa">ਗਨੋਮ ਵਿੱਚ ਤਾਕਤਵਰ ਅਤੇ ਗੁੰਝਲਦਾਰ ਕਾਰਜ ਵਿਕਾਸ ਲਈ ਕਾਰਜ ਖੋਜੀਆਂ ਲਈ ਗੁੰਝਲਦਾਰ ਡਿਵੈਲਪਮੈਂਟ ਪਲੇਟਫਾਰਮ ਸ਼ਾਮਲ ਹੈ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="pl">GNOME także zawiera platformę programistyczną umożliwiającą programistom tworzenie złożonych i wydajnych programów.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt">GNOME também inclui uma completa plataforma de desenvolvimento para programadores, que lhes permite criarem complexas e poderosas aplicações.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt_BR">O GNOME também inclui uma plataforma de desenvolvimento completa para programadores, permitindo a criação de aplicativos complexos e poderosos.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ro">GNOME include o platformă de dezvoltare completă pentru programatorii de aplicații, permițând crearea unor programe complexe și eficiente.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ru">Среда GNOME также включает в себя законченную платформу для разработчиков, позволяющую создавать мощные и сложные приложения.</p>
    <p xml:lang="si">තවද, යෙදුම් සහ කේත රචකයන් සඳහා පූර්ණ සංවර්ධන වෙදිකාවක් GNOME සතු අතර, මෙය ප්‍රබල සහ ශක්තිමත් යෙදුම් නිර්මාණයට අවකාශ ලබාදෙයි.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk">GNOME obsahuje aj kompletnú vývojovú platformu pre aplikácie, ktorá umožňuje vývoj výkonných a zložitých programov.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sl">GNOME vključuje tudi popolno razvojno platformo za programerje, kar omogoča ustvarjanje močnih in zahtevnih programov.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sq">GNOME përfshin gjithashtu një piataformë të plotë zhvillimi në ndihmë të programuesve, duke mundësuar krijimin e programeve të fuqishëm dhe kompleksë.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sr">Гном такође садржи и развојну платформу која омогућава програмерима да праве нове сложене и моћне програме.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sr@latin">Gnom takođe sadrži i razvojnu platformu koja omogućava programerima da prave nove složene i moćne programe.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sv">GNOME innehåller också en utvecklingsplattform som för programmerare möjliggör skapandet av kraftfulla och komplexa program.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ta">GNOME கூட மொத்த மேம்படுத்து பனித்தகம் பயன்பாடுகள் நிரலர்,சக்திவாய்ந்த மற்றும் சிக்கல் பயன்பாடுகளின் உருவாக்கத்திற்க்கு அனுமதிக்கும்.</p>
    <p xml:lang="te">గ్నోమ్ లో కార్యక్షేత్ర రచయితలు క్లిష్టమైన మరియు   దృఢమైన కార్యక్షేత్రములను నిర్మించుట కొరకు సంపూర్ణ నిర్మాణ వేదిక కలదు.</p>
    <p xml:lang="th">นอกจากนี้ GNOME ยังมีระบบรองรับ ที่ช่วยให้นักเขียนโปรแกรม สามารถสร้างโปรแกรมที่ทรงพลัง และมีความสามารถ</p>
    <p xml:lang="tk">GNOMEniň äplikeýşenler programçilerinden üçin kuwwatly we çylşyrymlyäplikeýşenleri bejermek üçin bir tekmil östiriş plätförmi bar.</p>
    <p xml:lang="tr">GNOME ayrıca uygulama geliştiricilerinin güçlü ve karmaşık uygulamalar yaratmalarına olanak sağlayan eksiksiz bir geliştirme platformu içerir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">GNOME також включає в себе завершену платформу розробки, що дозволяє програмістам створювати потужні і складні додатки.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uz">Bundan tashqari GNOME'da dasturchilar uchun yetarlicha dasturlash vositalari mavjud.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uz@cyrillic">Бундан ташқари GNOME'да дастурчилар учун етарлича дастурлаш воситалари мавжуд.</p>
    <p xml:lang="vi">GNOME còn cung cấp một nền tảng phát triển hoàn chỉnh cho các nhà lập trình ứng dụng, cho phép tạo các ứng dụng phức tạp và mạnh mẽ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="wa">Gnome inclût eto ene platfôme di diswalpaedje complete, ki permete åzès diswalpeus di programes informatikes di fé des poûxhants et complesses programes.</p>
    <p xml:lang="xh">I-GNOME kananjalo ibandakanya iqonga elipheleleyo lophuhliso ukwenzela abahlohli bobucukubhede bekhompyutha, ukuze kuvunyelwe ukuyilwa kweenkqubo zekhompyutha ezinesakhono nezimbaxa.</p>
    <p xml:lang="yo">GNOME tún ní àpapọ ète ìdàgbàsókè fún ìdarí kọmpútà</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_CN">GNOME 同时还提供了一套完整的开发平台，以帮助程序员创建复杂强大的应用程序。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_HK">GNOME 也為開發者提供完整的開發平台，允許開發者編寫功能強大和複雜的程式。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_TW">GNOME 也為開發者提供完整的開發平台，允許開發者編寫功能強大和複雜的程式。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zu">GNOME unomganga wokuthuthukisa, wabahleli bezinhlelo zokusentshenziswa ezivumela ukwakhiwa kwezinhlelo ezilukhuni.</p>
    <p>GNOME's focus on usability and accessibility, regular release cycle, and strong corporate backing make it unique among Free Software desktops.</p>
    <p xml:lang="af">GNOME se fokus op bruikbaarheid en toeganklikheid, gereelde vrystellingsiklusse, en sterk korporatiewe ondersteuning maak dit uniek onder Vrye Sagteware-werkareas.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ar">تركيز جنوم على سهولة الاستعمال و الإتاحة و دورة الإصدار المنتظمة و دعم الشركات القوي له يجعله مميّزا بين أسطح مكتب البرامج الحرّة.</p>
    <p xml:lang="as">ব্যৱহাৰযোগ্যতা আৰু সহজলভ্যতা উপৰ বিশেষ গুৰুত্ব প্ৰদান, সুনিয়মিত নিৰ্মাণ আৰু প্ৰকাশনা সময় আৰু বিভিন্ন প্ৰতিষ্ঠানৰ দৃঢ় সমৰ্থন আৰু উৎসাহৰ ফলত GNOME অন্যান্য মুক্ত চালনাজ্ঞান ডেস্কট'পৰ তুলনাত নিজৰ অদ্বিতীয় স্থান প্ৰাপ্ত কৰিবলৈ সক্ষম হৈছে ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="ast">L'enfotu de GNOME na usabilidá y l'accesibilidá, con actualizaciones regulares y un fuerte sofitu corporativu, faenlu único pente los escritorios de Software Llibre.</p>
    <p xml:lang="az">GNOME'un istifadə asandlığı və yetişmə qabiliyyəti, müntəzəm buraxılış dövrəsi və güclü korporativ arxa ona diqər Sərbəst Tə'minatlı masa üstüləri arasında xüsusi yer verir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="be">GNOME засяроджаны на карыснасьці й даступнасьці, сталых цыклах выпуску й на моцнае падтрымке прамысловых карыстальнікаў, што робіць яго непаўторным між іншых Вольных асяродзяў.</p>
    <p xml:lang="be@latin">Kancentracyja GNOME na zručnaści i dastupnaści, rehularnym vydaŭničym cykle i mocnaj karparacyjnaj padtrymcy robić jaho ŭnikalnym siarod inšych svabodnych asiarodździaŭ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bg">GNOME е се стреми към използваемост и достъпност, редовен цикъл на пускане на нови версии и желанието да бъде уникален сред свободния софтуер.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bn">গনোমের দৃষ্টি হচ্ছে ব্যবহার উপযোগিতা এবং সহায়ক প্রযুক্তির দিকে, নিয়মিত মুক্তি চক্র, এবং শক্তিশালী কর্পোরেট সহায়তা এটাকে বিনামূল্যের ডেস্কটপগুলোর মধ্যে অদ্বিতীয় করে তুলেছে।</p>
    <p xml:lang="bn_IN">ব্যবহারযোগ্যতা ও সহজলভ্যতা উপর বিশেষ গুরুত্ব প্রদান, সুনিয়মিত নির্মাণ ও প্রকাশনা কাল ও বিভিন্ন প্রতিষ্ঠানের দৃঢ় সমর্থন ও উৎসাহের ফলে GNOME অন্যান্য মুক্ত সফ্টওয়্যার ডেস্কটপের তুলনায় নিজের অদ্বিতীয় স্থান প্রাপ্ত করতে সক্ষম হয়েছে।</p>
    <p xml:lang="br">Klask 'ra GNOME chom efedus hag aes da implijout. Kempennet 'vez alies gant tud a-vicher. Chom a  ra brudet e touez ar Burevioù mezianteg.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bs">Težnje GNOME-a ka upotrebljivosti i pristupačnosti, redovnom postupku izdavanja i snažna podrška preduzeća ga izdvajaju među desktop-ima slobodnog softvera.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca">El focus del GNOME en la usabilitat i accessibilitat, el seu cicle regular de llançaments, i un fort suport per part de corporacions el fan únic dins dels escriptoris del programari lliure.</p>
    <p xml:lang="crh">GNOME'nıñ qullanışlılıqqa ve irişilebilirlikke fokusı, muntazam çıqarılış döngüsi ve küçlü korporativ destegi, onı Serbest Yazılım masaüstüleri arasında emsalsiz yapar.</p>
    <p xml:lang="cs">Zaměření GNOME na snadnou použitelnost a přístupnost, pravidelný vývojový cyklus a silná podpora velkými společnostmi jsou jedinečné mezi svobodnými softwarovými pracovními prostředími.</p>
    <p xml:lang="cy">Mae canolbwyntiad GNOME ar ddefnyddioldeb a hygyrchedd, cylchdro rhyddhau rheolaidd, a chefnogaeth corffforaethol gref yn ei wneud e'n unigryw ymysg penbyrddau Meddalwedd Rhydd.</p>
    <p xml:lang="da">Gnomes fokus på brugervenlighed og tilgængelig, regelmæssige frigivelser af nye versioner og stærk erhvervsmæssig opbakning gør miljøet unikt mellem andre frie skrivebordsmiljøer.</p>
    <p xml:lang="de">Die Betonung liegt bei GNOME auf einfacher Bedienbarkeit und Barrierefreiheit, regelmäßigen Veröffentlichungszyklen und starkem Firmenrückhalt, was es einzigartig unter freien Software-Desktops macht.</p>
    <p xml:lang="dz">ཇི་ནོམ་གྱིས་ ལག་ལེན་འཐབ་ནི་དང་ འཛུལ་སྤྱོད་ དུས་རྒྱུན་གསར་བཏོན་འབད་ནི་དང་ ལས་ཁང་ལས་རྒྱབ་སྐྱོར་སྒྲིང་སྒྲིང་འབད་ནི་ལུ་ གཙོ་བོར་བཏོན་མི་ལུ་བརྟེན་ཏེ་ སྟོང་མར་འཐོབ་པའི་ ཌེཀསི་ཊོཔ་མཉེན་ཆས་ཚུ་གི་གྲས་ལས་ མཐུན་མོང་མ་ཡིན་པ་ཅིག་ལུ་གྱུར་ཏེ་ཡོད།</p>
    <p xml:lang="el">Η εστίαση του Gnome στη χρηστικότητα και προσβασιμότητα, στο σταθερό κύκλο εκδόσεων και τη δυναμική εταιρική υποστήριξη, το κάνουν μοναδικό ανάμεσα στις επιφάνειες εργασίας του Ελεύθερου λογισμικού.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en_CA">GNOME's focus on usability and accessibility, regular release cycle, and strong corporate backing make it unique among Free Software desktops.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en_GB">GNOME's focus on usability and accessibility, regular release cycle, and strong corporate backing make it unique among Free Software desktops.</p>
    <p xml:lang="eo">GNOME, enfokusigita pri uzebleco kaj alirebleco, regulaj novaj versioj, kaj fortaj societoj kiuj faras ĝin unika en la liberaj programaj tabuloj.</p>
    <p xml:lang="es">La énfasis de GNOME en la facilidad de uso y accesibilidad, un ciclo de lanzamiento regular, y fuerte respaldo corporativo lo hacen único entre los escritorios de Software Libre.</p>
    <p xml:lang="et">GNOME'i rõhuasetus kasutajamugavusele ning ligipääsetavusele, korrapärastele väljastustsüklile ja tugevale korporatiivtoele teevad temast erilise vaba tarkvara töökeskkondade hulgas.</p>
    <p xml:lang="eu">GNOMEren erabilgarritasun eta eskuragarritasunak, askatze-ziklo erregularrak eta laguntza korporatibo sendoari ematen dion garrantziak, software libreko mahaigainen artean apartekoa izatea eragiten dute.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fa">تمرکز گنوم بر کارآیی و در دسترس بودن، چرخه‌ی انتشار منظم، و پشتیبانی یکپارچه‌ی قوی آن را در میان رومیزی‌های نرم‌افزارهای آزاد بی‌همتا می‌سازد.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fi">Gnomen keskittyminen käytettävyyteen ja esteettömyyteen, säännöllinen julkaisutahti ja yhtiöiden tuki tekee Gnomesta ainutlaatuisen vapaaohjelmistoihin perustuvien työpöytien joukossa.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">L'attention de GNOME sur l'ergonomie et l'accessibilité, un cycle de distribution régulier, et le suivi de grandes entreprises le rend unique entre tous les environnements de bureau Libre.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fur">GNOME al è unic jenfri i desktops libars a jessi facil di doprâ, a vê acess universâl, a vê versions regolârs, e un grues supuart pes aziendis.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gl">O enfoque do Gnome na usabilidade e accesibilidade, o ciclo regular de publicación de versións e un forte apoio empresaria fai que sexa único entre os escritorios de Software Libre.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gu">જીનોમનું ઉપયોગિતાપણુ અને સુલભતાપણુ પરનું ફોક્સ, તથા નિયમિત પ્રકાશન ચક્ર અને મજબૂત બેકઅપનો આધાર તેને મુક્ત સોફ્ટવેર ડેસ્કટોપમાં અનન્ય બનાવે છે.</p>
    <p xml:lang="he">‏GNOME מתמקד על שמישות ונגישות, מחזור שחרור קבוע, וגיבוי מסחרי חזק העושה אותו ייחודי בין שולחנות העבודה של התוכנה החופשית.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hi">मुफ्त सॉफ्टवेयर डेस्कटॉप के बीच गनोम की ये विशेषताएँ इन्हें बेजोड़ बनाती हैं - उपयोगिता और पंहुच पर संकेंद्रीकरण, नियमित रिलीज चक्र तथा सशक्त निगमों का समर्थन.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hr">GNOME se usredotočuje na iskoristivost, pristupačnost, redovita izdanja novih verzija i snažnu korporativnu potporu koja ga čini jedinstvenim u slobodnim radnim okruženjima.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hu">A GNOME a használhatóságot és a könnyű kezelhetőséget helyezi a középpontba. A rendszeres kiadások és az erős vállalati háttér egyedülállóvá teszi a szabad szoftveres grafikus munkakörnyezetek között.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hy">Գնոմի օգտագործվող և լայն հնարավորություններ ունեցող համակարգը, կանոնավոր թողարկումները և կորպորատիվ ամուր պաշտպանությունը այն եզակի են դարձնում Ազատ ծրագրային աշխատանքային էկրանների շրջանում։</p>
    <p xml:lang="id">GNOME adalah desktop Perangkat Lunak Bebas yang unik, yang mana memiliki fokus agar berdaya guna, kemudahan akses yang besar, siklus rilis yang teratur, dan dukungan korporasi yang kuat.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ig">GNOME na-aka agbado ụkwụ na njieme na ikembanye, saịkụlụ nke a na-ahapụ mgbe ọbụla, nakwa nkwado mmekọrịta siri ike nke mere ka ọ kwụpụ iche n'etiti Free Softwịa desktop ndị ọzọ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="is">Skerpa GNOME á auðvelda notkun og aðgengi, stöðugt útgáfuferli og sterkur stuðningur frá stórfyrirtækjum gerir GNOME einstakt meðal ókeypis skjáborðs hugbúnaðar.</p>
    <p xml:lang="it">L'attenzione alla facilità d'uso e all'accesso universale, i cicli di rilasci regolari e il supporto delle aziende rendono GNOME unico tra gli ambienti desktop liberi.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ja">GNOME の焦点は使い勝手の良さと分かりやすさ、定期的なリリース・サイクルにあり、企業がフリーでユニークなデスクトップをいろいろ提供しています。</p>
    <p xml:lang="ka">გნომის მთავარი მიზანია სიმარტივე და მისაწვდომობა, რეგულარული განახლებები და მძლავრი კორპორატიული მხარდაჭერა. სწორედ ამიტომ ის უნიკალურია თავისუფალი დესკტოპ სისტემებს შორის.</p>
    <p xml:lang="kk">GNOME қолайлы меңгерілуіне (шектеулі мүмкіндіктері бар адамдарға да) аса үлкен көңіл бөледі. Бұған дәлел жүйелі шығып отыратын жаңа нұсқалары.</p>
    <p xml:lang="kn">ಬಳಕೆಗೆ ಯೋಗ್ಯವಾಗಿಸುವಿಕೆ ಹಾಗು ನಿಲುಕಣೆ, ಕಾಲಕಾಲಕ್ಕೆ ಬಿಡುಗಡೆಯ ಚಕ್ರ , ಹಾಗು ಶಕ್ತಿಯುತವಾದ ಕಾರ್ಪೋರೇಟ್ ಬೆಂಬಲದತ್ತ GNOME ಗಮನಹರಿಸುವುದರಿಂದ ಅದು Free Software desktops ನಲ್ಲೆ ವಿಶಿಷ್ಟವಾದುದು ಎಂದು ಹೆಸರು ಮಾಡಿದೆ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ko">그놈의 사용성과 접근성에 대한 관심, 정기적인 릴리즈 주기, 강력한 기업의 후원때문에 그놈은 자유 소프트웨어 데스크탑중에서도 비할 바가 없는 데스크탑입니다.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ku">GNOME bi başbûna bikarhatin û gihîştin, pêvajoya bipergal a berhemî û bi desteka bihêz a komî, di nava sermaseyên Nivîsbariya Azad de tekane ye.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ky">GNOME чөйрөсү колдонуудагы ыңгайлуулукка өзгөчө көңүл бурат (анын ичинде мүкүнчүлүгү чектелген адамдар үчүн да) жана анын жаңы версияларынын регулярдуу чыгуусу, күчтүү корпоративдик колдоосу башка эркин иш стол чөйрөлөрүнөн айырмалап турат.</p>
    <p xml:lang="lt">GNOME paprastumas naudoti, prieinamumas visiems naudotojams, reguliarus naujų leidimų ciklas bei stiprus korporatyvinis užnugario palaikymas išskiria GNOME iš kitų Laisvos Programinės Įrangos grafinių aplinkų.</p>
    <p xml:lang="lv">GNOMEs fokusēšanās uz lietojamību un pieejamību, regulārs jaunu versiju prezentēšanas cikls un spēcīgi korporatīvie sakari padara to unikālu starp Brīvās Programmatūras darbvidēm.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mai">मुफ्त सोफ्टवेयर डेस्कटाप क' बीच गनोमक ई विशेषतासभ एकरा बेजोड़ बनबैत अछि - उपयोगिता आओर पहुँच पर संकेंद्रीकरण, नियमित रिलीज चक्र आओर सशक्त निगम क' समर्थन.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mg">Ny fimasoan'ny GNOME amin'ny fahafahana mampiasa tsara sy ny fanamorana ny fampiasana ny rindran'asa, ny fisesen'ny famoahana kinova, ary ny fanohanana mafonja avy amin'ny orinasa vaventy no tena mampiavaka azy amin'ireo rindran'asa desktop maimaimpoana misy.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mk">GNOME се фокусира на користност и пристапност. Регуларниот циклус на објавување на нови верзии го прави GNOME уникатен помеѓу слободните работни околини.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ml">ഉപയോഗയോഗ്യത , സാമീപ്യത , കൃത്യതയാര്‍ന്ന പ്രസാധനക്രമം എന്നിവയിലുള്ള ഗ്നോമിന്റെ നിഷ്ഠയും ശക്തമായ കോര്‍പറേറ്റ് പിന്തുണയും ഇതിനെ സ്വതന്ത്ര സോഫ്റ്റ്‌വെയര്‍ പണിയിടങ്ങളില്‍ തനിമയോടെ നിര്‍ത്തുന്നു.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mn">ГНОМЕ ашигтай, хэрэглээ хялбар, тогтмол сайжруулалтад анхаардаг чөлөөт програм хангамжуудын хүчирхэг нэгдэл юм.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mr">GNOME चा उपयुक्तता आणि उपलब्धतेवर जोर, नियमित प्रकाशन चक्र, आणि मजबूत व्यापारी समर्थन हे त्यास मुक्त सॉफ्टवेअर डेस्कटॉप्समध्ये अद्वितीय बनवते.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ms">Tumpuan GNOME pada kebolehgunaan dan kebolehcapaian, kitaran keluaran biasa, dan sokongan korporat yang kuat membuatkan ia unik di antara desktop Perisian Bebas.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nb">GNOME fokuserer på brukervennlighet og tilgjengelighet, tidsbasert utviklingssyklus og hjelp fra sterke bedrifter for å bli unikt blant skrivebordsmiljøene i fri programvare.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ne">प्रयोगात्मकता र पहुँचतामा जीनोमको फोकस, नियमित निष्कासन चक्र, र वलियो संगठित समर्थनले यसलाई स्वतन्त्र सफ्टवेयर डेस्कटपहरू मध्ये अद्वितीय बनाउँदछ ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="nl">Gnome richt zich op gebruiksvriendelijkheid en toegankelijkheid, het regelmatig uitbrengen van verbeterde versies, en een krachtige ondersteuning vanuit het bedrijfsleven. Dit alles zorgt dat Gnome uniek is binnen de werkomgevingen van de vrije software.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nn">GNOME fokuserer på å vera brukarvennleg og tilgjengeleg, å koma i nye utgåver med jamne mellomrom, og å bruka støtte frå sterke verksemder til å verta unik blant skrivebordsmiljøa i fri programvare-miljøet.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nso">Go lebia tlhokomelo ga GNOME tabeng ya go diriwa le go fihlelelega, modikologo wa go lokolla ka mehla le thekgo ya tiriano e matla go dira gore e be ya moswana-noi gare ga diteseke ta Software ya Bolokologi.</p>
    <p xml:lang="oc">L'atencion de GNOME sus l'utilisabilitat e l'accessibilitat, un cicle de distribucion regulièr e lo sosten de grandas entrepresas fan d'el un environament de burèu liure unenc.</p>
    <p xml:lang="or">ନୋମର ବ୍ଯବହାରଯୋଗ୍ଯତା ଓ ସୁଗମତା ପ୍ରତି ଧ୍ଯାନ, ନିୟମିତ ପ୍ରକାଶନ, ଓ ଦୃଢ଼ ବାଣିଜ୍ଯ ସହଯୋଗ ତାହାକୁ ମୁକ୍ତ ସଫ୍ଟୱେର ଡେସ୍କଟପ ମଧ୍ଯରେ ଅନନ୍ଯ ସ୍ଥାନ ପ୍ରଦାନ କରେ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pa">ਗਨੋਮ ਨੂੰ ਇਸ ਦੀ ਸਹੂਲਤਾਂ ਅਤੇ ਪਹੁੰਚ ਉੱਤੇ ਕੇਂਦਰਿਤ ਰਹਿਣਾ, ਨਿਯਮਿਤ ਜਾਰੀ ਕਰਨਾ ਅਤੇ ਸ਼ਕਤੀਸ਼ਾਲੀ ਸਹਿਕਾਰੀ ਸਹਿਯੋਗ , ਇਸ ਨੂੰ ਮੁਫਤ ਸਾਫਟਵੇਅਰ ਵੇਹੜਿਆਂ ਵਿੱਚੋਂ ਵੱਖਰਾ ਕਰਦਾ ਹੈ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="pl">Koncentracja GNOME na użyteczności i dostępności, regularnym cyklu wydawniczym i silnym wsparciu korporacyjnym, czyni je unikalnym pośród innych wolnodostępnych środowisk.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt">O foco do GNOME na usabilidade e acessibilidade, ciclos regulares de novas versões e forte apoio empresarial tornam-no único entre os ambientes de trabalho de Aplicações Livres.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt_BR">O foco do GNOME em usabilidade, acessibilidade, um ciclo regular de lançamentos e um forte apoio corporativo o torna único entre os ambientes de trabalho livres.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ro">GNOME pune un accent deosebit pe uşurința în utilizare și accesibilitate, pe un ciclu scurt de lansare de noi versiuni și pe suportul din partea marilor corporații, ceea ce îl face unic printre desktop-urile Free Software.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ru">Среда GNOME уделяет особое внимание удобству использования (в том числе и для людей с ограниченными возможностями), регулярности выхода новых версий и сильной корпоративной поддержке, что выделяет её из ряда свободных окружений рабочего стола.</p>
    <p xml:lang="si">GNOME භාවිතා කිරිමේ හැකියාව සහ ලඟාවීමේ හැකියාව, ඒකාකාරී මුදාහැරීමේ චක්‍රය, සහ ශක්තිමත් ඒකාබද්ධතාව පිළිබඳව නාභිගතවේ, එහෙයින් එය ස්වාදීන මෘදුකාංග තිරමුහුණත් අතර අද්විතීය වේ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk">GNOME je zamerané na použiteľnosť, prístupnosť, pravidelné uvoľňovanie nových verzií a silné firemné zázemie. Tým je toto prostredie jedinečné medzi ostatnými slobodnými prostrediami.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sl">GNOME poudarek na uporabnosti in dostopnosti, rednih izdajah in močni podpori podjetij ga postavlja na edinstveno mesto med prosto dostopnimi namizji.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sq">Interesi në lehtësinë dhe mundësinë e përdorimit, në ciklin e rregullt të lëshimeve dhe suporti i afruar nga korporatat bëjnë që GNOME të jetë më i veçanti midis desktop-ëve të lirë.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sr">Гномове тежње ка употребљивости и приступачности, редовном поступку издавања и снажна подршка предузећа га издвајају међу радним окружењима слободног софтвера.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sr@latin">Gnomove težnje ka upotrebljivosti i pristupačnosti, redovnom postupku izdavanja i snažna podrška preduzeća ga izdvajaju među radnim okruženjima slobodnog softvera.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sv">GNOME:s fokus på användbarhet och åtkomlighet, regelbundna utgåvecykel och starka stöd från företag gör den unik bland skrivbordsmiljöer inom fri programvara.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ta">GNOME's முன்னிறுத்து உபயோகப்படுத்தல் மற்றும் செயல்படுத்தல்,வழக்கமான வெளியீடு வண்டி, மற்றும் வலுவான இலவச மென்பொருள் மேசைகள்.</p>
    <p xml:lang="te">ఉపయోగికత, సాంగ్యత్యకత  , క్రమ విడుదల చట్రం మరియు దృఢ సంస్థాగత దన్నులపై గ్నోమ్ దృష్టి దీనిని స్వతంత్ర   సాఫ్ట్వేర్ రంగాలలో సాటిలేనిదిగా చేస్తుంది.</p>
    <p xml:lang="th">GNOME เน้นความง่ายในการใช้ คอยพัฒนารุ่นใหม่สม่ำเสมอ และได้รับการอุปถัมภ์จากองค์กรธุรกิจอย่างต่อเนื่อง ทั้งหมดนี้ทำให้ GNOME เป็นระบบเดสก์ท็อปที่ไม่เหมือนใครในหมู่เดสก์ท็อปที่เป็นซอฟต์แวร์เสรี</p>
    <p xml:lang="tr">GNOME'un kullanılabilirliğe ve erişilebilirliğe odaklanması, düzenli ürün sürecine ve güçlü takım desteğine sahip olması onu Özgür Yazılım masaüstleri arasında tek yapar.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">Середовище GNOME звертає особливу увагу на зручність користування (в тому числі й для людей з обмеженими можливостями), регулярність виходу нових версій і сильну корпоративну підтримку, що вирізняє її з ряду вільних середовищ робочих столів.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uz">GNOME asosiy eʼtiborni qulayliklarga (shu bilan birga imkoniyati cheklangan insonlar uchun) qaratgani va kuchli korporativ koʻmak tizimiga egaligi bilan boshqa ish stollaridan ajralib turadi.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uz@cyrillic">GNOME асосий эътиборни қулайликларга (шу билан бирга имконияти чекланган инсонлар учун) қаратгани ва кучли корпоратив кўмак тизимига эгалиги билан бошқа иш столларидан ажралиб туради.</p>
    <p xml:lang="vi">GNOME tập trung vào khả năng tiếp cận và khả dụng, chu kì phát triển đều đặn, tính cộng tác mạnh làm nó trở nên duy nhất trong các phần mềm tự do về môi trường bàn làm việc.</p>
    <p xml:lang="wa">Gnome vize l' accessibilité eyet esse åjhey a-z eployî; des erîlés cikes di rexhowe des nouvès modêyes et on foirt aspalaedje do monde des eterprijhes fijhèt d' lu ene sacwè d' unike emey les scribannes e libe programe.</p>
    <p xml:lang="xh">Ukujolisa kwe-GNOME ekusebenzisekeni nasekufikeleleni, kumjikelo wobonelelo osoloko ukho, nenkxaso esemva eyomeleleyo eyenza ukuba ifane yodwa phakathi kolwazi lwezikrini Zobucukubhede Bekhompyutha Obukhululekileyo.</p>
    <p xml:lang="yo">Ìfojúsí GNOME Lórí lílò àti ìbánirẹ , ìlọ-dédé, àti àtìlẹyìn ìgbóra àjọṣepọ mú kí ó ní ìyàtọ  láàrin ojú ìdarí kọmpútà</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_CN">GNOME 专注于可用性和辅助功能，规范的版本释放循环，以及强劲的合作机制，使得它在自由软件桌面领域独树一帜。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_HK">GNOME 着重於可用性、無障礙環境，會準時推出新版本，而且得到企業的全面支援，這些都令它在各種屬於自由軟件的桌面環境中享有特殊地位。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_TW">GNOME 著重於可用性、無障礙環境，會準時推出新版本，而且得到企業的全面支援，這些都令它在各種屬於自由軟體的桌面環境中享有特殊地位。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zu">ukusebenziseka nokungeniseka nokuyingiliza, nokusekelwa kwe GNOME kuyenze yaba ekhethekile kosoftware abakhululekiyo bobuso beziga-nyezi.</p>
    <p>GNOME's greatest strength is our strong community. Virtually anyone, with or without coding skills, can contribute to making GNOME better.</p>
    <p xml:lang="af">GNOME se sterkste punt is ons sterk gemeenskap. Feitlik elkeen, met of sonder programmeervaardighede, kan 'n bydrae lewer tot die verbetering van GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ar">أعظم قوّة لجنوم هي جمهورنا العظيم. نظريا يمكن لأي شخص بمهارات برمجة أو بدونها المساهمة في جعل جنوم أفضل.</p>
    <p xml:lang="as">শক্তিশালী সম্প্ৰদায়ৰ উপস্থিতি GNOME-ৰ মূল্যবান বৈশিষ্ট্য । কোড কৰাৰ ক্ষমতা নিৰ্বিশেষে যি কোনো ব্যক্তি GNOME ডেস্কট'প উন্নত কৰিবলৈ সহায় কৰিবলৈ পাৰিব ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="ast">La mayor fuercia de GNOME ye la fuerte comunidá de nueso. Dafechu tol mundu, con o sin conocimientos de programación, podría echar un gabitu pa facer un GNOME meyor.</p>
    <p xml:lang="az">GNOME'un ən böyük gücü onun güclü cəmiyyətidir. Proqramlaşdırma qabiliyyəti olan və olmayan hamı GNOME layihəsini daha da gözəlləşdirmək üçün ona dəstək verə bilər.</p>
    <p xml:lang="be">Галоўная сіла GNOME - у нашай моцнай супольнасьці. Практычна кожны, хто мае ці ня мае здольнасьці да напісаньня праграмнага коду, можа зрабіць свой унёсак у GNOME, зрабіўшы яго яшчэ лепшым.</p>
    <p xml:lang="be@latin">Najvialikšaj siłaj GNOME jość našaja mocnaja supolnaść. Amal kožny, niezaležna ad umieńnia prahramavać, moža ŭdzielničać u raźvićci GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bg">Най-голямата сила на GNOME е нашата силна общност. Теоретично всеки със или без способности да програмира, може да помогне и да направи GNOME по-добър.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bn">গনোমের সবচেয়ে বড় শক্তি হচ্ছে আমাদের শক্তিশালী গোষ্ঠী। কোডিং দক্ষতা আছে বা নেইএমন যে কেউ গুহ্‌নোমকে সমৃদ্ধ করার কাজে ভার্চুয়ালি অবদান রাখতে পারে।</p>
    <p xml:lang="bn_IN">শক্তিশালী সম্প্রদায়ের উপস্থিতি GNOME-র সবচেয়ে মূল্যবান বৈশিষ্ট্য। কোড করার ক্ষমতা নির্বিশেষে যে কোনো ব্যক্তি GNOME ডেস্কটপ উন্নত করতে সাহায্যে করতে পারবেন।</p>
    <p xml:lang="br">Nerzh pouezusañ GNOME a zo hon bedig-bed kreñv. Forzh pehini gant gouiziegezh war ar programmiñ pe get a c'hell kas traoù a benn gwelaat GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bs">Najveća snaga GNOME-a je naša čvrsta zajednica. Gotovo svako, sa ili bez programerskih sposobnosti, može doprinijeti da GNOME bude još bolji.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca">El punt més fort del GNOME és la seva gran comunitat. Gairebé tothom, amb o sense coneixements de programació, pot contribuir a millorar el GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="crh">GNOME'nıñ eñ büyük küçü bizim küçlü toplulığımızdır. Herkes deyerlik, kodlama melekeleri olsa da olmasa da, GNOME'nı daa yahşı yapmaq içün isse qoşa bilir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="cs">Největší silou GNOME je jeho silná komunita. Téměř kdokoliv, ať už s nebo bez znalosti programování, se může podílet na vylepšování GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="cy">Cryfder mwyaf GNOME yw ein cymuned gref. Gall bron unrhywun, gyda neu heb sgiliau rhaglennu, gyfrannu at wella GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="da">Gnomes største styrke er vores stærke bruger- og udviklerfællesskab. Enhver, med eller uden programmørfærdigheder, kan bidrage til at gøre Gnome bedre.</p>
    <p xml:lang="de">GNOMEs größte Stärke ist unsere starke Gemeinschaft. Nahezu jeder, ob mit oder ohne Programmierfähigkeiten, kann zur Verbesserung von GNOME beitragen.</p>
    <p xml:lang="dz">ཇི་ནོམ་གྱི་སྟོབས་ཤུགས་སྦོམ་ཤོས་དེ་རང་ མི་སྡེ་སྒྲིང་སྒྲིང་ཡོད་མི་འདི་ཨིན། དེ་ཡང་ ངོ་བོ་ལུ་ ཀོ་ཌིང་གི་རིག་རྩལ་ཡོད་རུང་མེད་རུང་ མི་ག་གིས་ཡང་ ཇི་ནོམ་ལེགས་བཅོས་གཏང་ནི་ལུ་ ཕན་ཐབས་འབད་ཚུགས།</p>
    <p xml:lang="el">Η μεγαλύτερη δύναμη του Gnome είναι η ίδια η δυνατή μας κοινότητα. Ο καθένας με ή χωρίς ικανότητες προγραμματιστή, μπορεί να συμβάλλει στο να κάνει το Gnome καλύτερο.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en_CA">GNOME's greatest strength is its strong community. Virtually anyone, with or without coding skills, can contribute to making GNOME better.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en_GB">GNOME's greatest strength is our strong community. Virtually anyone, with or without coding skills, can contribute to making GNOME better.</p>
    <p xml:lang="eo">La plej granda potenco de GNOME estas nia forta komunumo. Iu ajn, kun aŭ sen programa lerteco povas helpi por fari GNOME plej bona.</p>
    <p xml:lang="es">La mayor fortaleza de GNOME reside en su fuerte comunidad. Virtualmente cualquiera, con o sin habilidades de programación, puede contribuir a hacer GNOME mejor.</p>
    <p xml:lang="et">GNOME'i tugevamaid külgi on kasutajate kogukond. Praktiliselt igaüks, programmeerimisoskusega või -oskuseta, võib GNOME'i paremaksmuutmisele kaasa aidata.</p>
    <p xml:lang="eu">GNOMEren indar handiena gure komunitate indartsua da. Ia edonork, programazioan trebetasunak eduki ala ez, parte har dezake GNOME hobetzen.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fa">بزرگترین قدرت گنوم اجتماع قوی ماست. عملاً هر کس، چه مهارت‌های کد نویسی داشته باشد و چه نداشته باشد، می‌تواند در بهتر کردن گنوم همکاری کند.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fi">Gnomen suurin vahvuus on vahva yhteisö. Käytännössä kuka tahansa, ohjelmointitaitoinen tai ei, voi osallistua Gnomen kehittämiseen.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">La plus grande force de GNOME est sa puissante communauté. À peu près n'importe qui, avec ou sans compétence en programmation, peut contribuer à rendre GNOME meilleur.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fur">Il pont di fuarce di GNOME a je la sô comunitât. Ognidun, plui o mancul scuelât in programazion, al pos contribuî a rindi GNOME ancjemò miôr di ce ch'al è.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gl">A maior fortaleza do Gnome é a nosa grande comunidade. Virtualmente calquera persoa, con ou sen habilidades para programar, pode contribuír á mellora do Gnome.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gu">જીનોમની શ્રેષ્ઠ મજબૂતાઈ એ આપણી મજબૂત જાતિ છે. વર્ચ્યુઅલ રીતે, કોઈપણ કોડીંગ કરવાની જાણકારી વિના અથવા તેની સાથે જીનોમને વધુ સારું બનાવવા માટે ફાળો આપી શકે છે.</p>
    <p xml:lang="he">העוצמה הגדולה ביותר של GNOME היא הקהילה החזקה שלו. למעשה כל אחד, עם או בלי כישורי כתיבת קוד, יכול לתרום כדי לעשות את GNOME טוב יותר.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hi">गनोम की विशाल शक्ति है हमारा मजबूत समुदाय. वास्तव में कोई भी,  कोडिंग कौशल हो या न हो, गनोम को बेहतर बनाने में अपना योगदान दे सकता है.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hr">GNOME-ova najveća snaga je zajednica okupljena oko njega. Gotovo svatko, s ili bez vještina programiranja, može doprinijeti poboljšnju GNOME-a.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hu">A GNOME legnagyobb erőssége a közösségben rejlik. Gyakorlatilag bárki, akár tud programozni, akár nem, hozzájárulhat a GNOME jobbá tételéhez.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hy">Գնոմի մեծագույն ուժը մեր ամուր համայնքն է։ Իրականում յուրաքանչյուր ոք, ունենալով կամ չունենալով կոդավորման հմտություններ, կարող է իր ավանդը ներդնելԳնոմը առավել լավը դարձնելու գործում։</p>
    <p xml:lang="id">Kekuatan GNOME ada pada komunitasnya yang kuat. Setiap orang, tidak peduli dapat memprogram atau tidak, boleh membantu agar GNOME dapat menjadi lebih baik lagi.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ig">Ike GNOME bụ nkwekọrịta ndị mmadụ gbasara ya. Ọbụnagodi onye ọbụla, má mọọbụ amaghị usoromumeihe ọrụ ǹkà ya, ga-enwenwu ike inyeaka n'ọdị mma GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="is">Styrkleiki GNOME samanstendur meðal annars af sterku samfélagi. Persónur með lágmarks tölvu og forritunarkunnáttu hafa möguleika á að bæta og aðstoða við þróun GNOME skjáborðsins.</p>
    <p xml:lang="it">Il punto di forza di GNOME è la sua solida comunità. Chiunque, dotato o meno di capacità di programmazione, può contribuire a rendere GNOME migliore.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ja">GNOME の最も偉大な強みは力強いコミュニティにあります。実際のところ、プログラムを作成する能力のありなしに関わらず、誰もが GNOME をより素晴らしいものにするよう貢献できるようになっています。</p>
    <p xml:lang="ka">გნომის მთავარი ძალა თვით მომხმარებლებშია, ყველას შეუძლია პროგრამირების ცოდნის გარეშე გააუმჯობესოს გნომი.</p>
    <p xml:lang="kk">GNOME-ның ерекшеліктерінен бірі - программа құра алмайтын адам да оны көркейтуде өз үлесін қоса алады.</p>
    <p xml:lang="kn">GNOME ನ ಅತ್ಯಂತ ಹೆಚ್ಚಿನ ಬಲವೆಂದರೆ ನಮ್ಮ ಶಕ್ತಿಯುತ ಸಮುದಾಯ. ಕೋಡಿಂಗ್‌ನ ಕುಶಲತೆ ಇರಲಿ ಇಲ್ಲದೆ ಇರಲಿ, ವಾಸ್ತವವಾಗಿ ಯಾರು ಬೇಕಿದ್ದರೂ GNOME ಅನ್ನು ಉತ್ತಮಗೊಳಿಸಲು ನೆರವಾಗಬಹುದು.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ko">그놈의 최고의 힘은 우리의 강력한 커뮤니티입니다. 코딩 기술이 있던, 없던, 그 누구든 간에 그놈을 더 낫게 만드는 데 공헌할 수 있습니다.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ku">Hêza herî mezin a GNOME'yê, koma me ya zexm e. Hemû kesên ku xwedî hunera kodkirinê ya nîgaşî ne an jî ne xwediyê vê hunerê ne, dikarin piştgiriyê bidin pêşxistina GNOME'yê.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ky">GNOME чөйрөсүнүн артыкчылык жагы анын күчтүү колдонуучулар коомчулугунда. Ар бир адам программалоодо тажрыйбасы бар болсо да, тажрыйбасы жок болсо да, чөйрөнү жакшыртууга өз салымын кошо алат.</p>
    <p xml:lang="lt">Didžiausia GNOME stiprybė yra labai stipri bendruomenė. Faktiškai kiekvienas, turintis ar neturintis programavimo įgudžių, gali prisidėti prie GNOME tobulinimo.</p>
    <p xml:lang="lv">GNOME lielākais spēks slēpjas kopienā. Praktiski, jebkurš, ar vai bez programmēšanas iemaņām, var līdzdarboties, lai padarītu GNOME labāku.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mai">गनोमक विशाल शक्ति अछि हमर मजगूत समुदाय. बास्तवमे कोनो, कोडिंग कौशल हुए अथवा नहि हुए, गनोमकेँ बेहतर बनाबैमे अहाँ अपन जोगदान दए सकैत अछि.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mg">Ny tena herin'ny GNOME dia ny tanjaky ny fivondronan'ireo mpankafy azy. Azo lazaina hoe ny rehetrarehetra mihitsy no afaka mandray anjara amin'ny fanatsarana ny GNOME, na mahafehy ny fanafangoana izy na tsia.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mk">Најголемата сила на GNOME е во јаката заедница. Скоро секој со или без програмерски способности може да придонесе во подобрувањето на GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ml">ഗ്നോമിന്റെ എറ്റവും വലിയ ശക്തി ഞങ്ങളുടെ കരുത്തുറ്റ കൂട്ടായ്മയാണു്. കോഡെഴുത്ത് കഴിവുകളുള്ളവരോ ഇല്ലാത്തവരോ എന്ന ഭേദമില്ലാതെ ആര്‍ക്കും ഗ്നോം മെച്ചപ്പെടുത്താന്‍ സംഭാവന ചെയ്യാവുന്നതാണു്.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mn">ГНОМЕ бол манай хүчирхэг нийгэмлэгийн хамгийн том бүтээл. Коде бичиж чаддаг чаддаггүй хэн бүхэн ГНОМыг улам сайжруулахад хувь нэмрээ оруулж чадна.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mr">GNOME ची सर्वात मोठी शक्ती आहे आमचा सशक्त समाज. जवळजवळ कोणीही, कोडिंगचे नैपुण्य असो वा नसो, GNOME च्या सुधारणेस हातभार लावू शकतो.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ms">Kekuatan GNOME terkuat adalah komuniti yang kuat. Secara virtual semua orang, dengan atau tanpa kemahiran mengkod, boleh menyumbang untuk menjadukan GNOME lebih baik.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nb">GNOME's største styrke er det sterke miljøet rundt det. Hvem som helst, med og uten programmeringskunnskap kan bidra til å gjøre GNOME bedre.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ne">जीनोमको सबै भन्दा ठूलो आधार भनेको हाम्रो बलियो समुदाय नै हो । वास्तविक रूपमा जो कोहीले, सङ्केतन दक्षता वा दक्षता बिना नै, जीनोमलाई राम्रो बनाउन योगदान गर्न सक्दछ । </p>
    <p xml:lang="nl">De grootste kracht van Gnome is onze hechte gemeenschap. Bijna iedereen kan bijdragen aan het verbeteren van Gnome, ook degenen die niet kunnen programmeren.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nn">Den største styrka med GNOME er det sterke miljøet rundt. Så å seia alle, med eller utan programmeringskunnskap, kan bidra til å gjera GNOME betre.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nso">Thekgo e kgolo yeo GNOME e nago le yona ke sethaba sa rena se matla. Motho le ge e le ofe yo mongwe tweletong ya go itiragalela, a ka ba a e na le bokgoni bja ta molao goba a se na bjona, a ka tsenya letsogo go kaonafateng GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="oc">La fòrça màger de GNOME es nòstra comunitat potenta. Gaireben totes, amb o sens competéncias de programacion, pòdon ajudar a melhorar GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="or">ନୋମର ସବୁଠାରୁ ବଡ଼ ଶକ୍ତି ହେଲା ଆମର ଦୃଢ଼ ଗୋଷ୍ଠୀ. ପ୍ରାୟ ଯେ କେହି ନୋମର ଉନ୍ନତିରେ ଯୋଗଦାନ ଦେଇ ପାରନ୍ତି, କାରିକା ଲେଖିବାର ଦକ୍ଷତା ଥାଉ କି ନାହିଁ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pa">ਗਨੋਮ ਦੀ ਅਸਲੀ ਮਜ਼ਬੂਤੀ ਇਸ ਦਾ ਮਜ਼ਬੂਤ ਸੰਗਠਨ ਹੈ। ਸਹੀ ਤਾਂ ਇਹ ਹੈ ਕਿ ਕੋਈ ਵੀ, ਭਾਵੇਂ ਉਹ ਜਾਣਕਾਰ ਹੈ ਜਾਂ ਨਹੀ, ਗਨੋਮ ਨੂੰ ਚੰਗਾ ਬਣਾਉਣ ਲਈ ਕੰਮ ਕਰ ਸਕਦਾ ਹੈ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="pl">Największą siłą GNOME jest nasza energiczna społeczność. Prawie każdy, potrafiący programować lub nie, może przyczynić się do rozwoju GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt">A maior força do GNOME está na sua forte comunidade. Vitualmente qualquer um, com ou sem conhecimentos de programação, pode contribuir para melhorar o GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt_BR">A maior vantagem do GNOME é a nossa comunidade. Praticamente qualquer um, sendo ou não um programador, pode contribuir para fazer o GNOME melhor.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ro">Puterea desktopului GNOME se datoreaza eforturilor comunității proprii. Practic oricine, cu sau fără abilități de programare, poate contribui la perfecționarea mediului GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ru">Наибольшая сила среды GNOME заключается в сильном сообществе. Каждый, неважно с опытом программирования или без, может внести свой вклад в улучшение среды.</p>
    <p xml:lang="si">අපගේ ප්‍රජාව GNOME's අනගිභවනීය ශක්තිය වෙයි. සැබවින්ම කේත රචන කුසලතාවය ඇති හෝ නැති ඕනැම කෙනෙකුට GNOME හි සාර්ථකත්වය සඳහා උරදිය හැකිය.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk">Najväčšia sila GNOME je veľká komunita. Skoro každý, programátor alebo neprogramátor, sa môže zapojiť do vylepšovania GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sl">Največja moč namizja GNOME je moč skupnosti. Praktično vsak, z ali brez programerskih izkušenj, lahko pomaga pri izboljševanju namizja GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sq">Fuqia e GNOME është komuniteti që na përkrah. Virtualisht kushdo, me apo pa aftësi kodimi, mund të kontribojë në përmirësimin e GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sr">Највећа снага Гнома је наша чврста заједница. Готово свако, са или без програмерских способности, може допринети да Гном буде још бољи.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sr@latin">Najveća snaga Gnoma je naša čvrsta zajednica. Gotovo svako, sa ili bez programerskih sposobnosti, može doprineti da Gnom bude još bolji.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sv">GNOME:s största styrka är vår starka gemenskap. Nästan alla, med eller utan programmeringskunskaper, kan bidra till att förbättra GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ta">GNOME's உயர்வான வலிமை நமது உறுதி குழுமம்.மெய்நிகர் ஏதாவது,குறிமுறை உடன் அல்லத் இல்லாது, GNOME வழங்கலாம்.</p>
    <p xml:lang="te">మా దృఢమైన సంఘమే గ్నోమ్ యొక్క శక్తి. వాస్తవానికి గ్నోమ్ క్రోడీకరణ నిపుణత వున్నవాళ్ళయినా , లేనివాళ్ళయినా  దీని అభివృద్ధిపథంలో సహాయపడగలరు.</p>
    <p xml:lang="th">จุดที่แข็งแกร่งที่สุดของ GNOME ก็คือชุมชนที่เข้มแข็ง ทุก ๆ คน ไม่ว่าจะเป็นใคร ถนัดเขียนโปรแกรมหรือไม่ ก็สามารถร่วมกันพัฒนา GNOME ให้ดีขึ้นได้</p>
    <p xml:lang="tk">GNOMEniň iň beýyk güýçi biziň daýaw jamygamyz dir. Her kim, programçilikdä ökda bolsa bolmasa GNOMEni oňotlamak üçin kömeklap başarar.</p>
    <p xml:lang="tr">GNOME'un en büyük gücü bizim sağlam topluluğumuzdur. Sanal olarak kodlama yeteneğine sahip ya da sahip olmayan herkes GNOME'u daha iyi yapmak için katılımda bulunabilir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">Найсильнішою особливістю середовища GNOME полягає у сильній спільноті. Кожен, не важливо, з досвідом програмування, чи ні, може внести свій вклад в покращення середовища.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uz">GNOME'ning eng kuchi bizning mustahkam jamoamizdadir. Har kim, xoh dasturlashni bilsin, xoh bilmasin, GNOME muhitini rivojlantirish oʻz hissasini qoʻsha oladi.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uz@cyrillic">GNOME'нинг энг кучи бизнинг мустаҳкам жамоамиздадир. Ҳар ким, хоҳ дастурлашни билсин, хоҳ билмасин, GNOME муҳитини ривожлантириш ўз ҳиссасини қўша олади.</p>
    <p xml:lang="vi">Sức mạnh lớn nhất của GNOME chính là cộng đồng vững mạnh của chúng ta. Bất kì ai, dù có kĩ năng lập trình hay không, cũng có thể góp phần làm cho GNOME tốt hơn.</p>
    <p xml:lang="wa">Li pus grande foice di Gnome c' est nosse cominålté. Tot l' minme kî, avou ou sins cnoxhances di programaedje, pout apoirter si ptite pire eyet contribuwer po fé ki Gnome soeye meyeu.</p>
    <p xml:lang="xh">Isakhono esisona sikhulu se-GNOME kukomelela kwabahlali bethu. Enyanisweni nabani, onobuchule bokufaka iikhowudi okanye ongenabo, unakho ukwenza igalelo lokuyiphucula i-GNOME.</p>
    <p xml:lang="yo">Ipa pàtàkì GNOME Jẹ ìgbóra àgbèègbè wa. Ódàbì pé ẹnikẹni tí ó ní ìmọ ojútùú tàbí tí kò ní, lè sapa àti mú GNOME dára si.</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_CN">GNOME 最引以自豪的，就是其强大的社区。任何人都可以为 GNOME 贡献力量，而不管他是否懂得编程。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_HK">GNOME 最優勝的地方在於我們的社羣。無論任何人，不論懂不懂編程，都可以作出貢獻，令 GNOME 不斷進步。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_TW">GNOME 最優勝的地方在於我們的社群。無論任何人，不論懂不懂編程，都可以作出貢獻，令 GNOME 不斷進步。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zu">Amandla e GNOME asemandleni omphakathi wethu. Empeleni wonke umuntu, onokuhlakanipha kokubhala izinhelo nongenakho, angabanomthelele ukwenza ngcono GNOME.</p>
    <p>Hundreds of people have contributed code to GNOME since it was started in 1997; many more have contributed in other important ways, including translations, documentation, and quality assurance.</p>
    <p xml:lang="af">Honderde mense het kode tot GNOME bygedra sedert dit in 1997 ontstaan het; nog meer het op ander belangrike maniere bydraes gelewer, insluitend vertalings, dokumentasie en kwaliteitsversekering.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ar">المئات من الناس ساهموا بشفرات لجنوم منذ إنشائه في سنة 1997، العديد الآخرون ساهموا بطرق أخرى مهمّة مثل الترجمة و التوثيق و التأكد من الجودة.</p>
    <p xml:lang="as">১৯৯৭ চনত GNOME আৰম্ভ হোৱাৰ পিছত শতশত মানুহে এই ডেস্কট'প নিৰ্মাণৰ কামত নিজৰ লেখা কোড  অন্তৰ্ভুক্ত কৰিছে; অন্যান্য অনেক বিভিন্ন কৰ্ম যেনে অনুবাদ, নথিপত্ৰ লিখা আৰু গুণমান পৰীক্ষণ কৰি গুৰুপূৰ্ণ যোগদান কৰিছে ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="ast">Cientos de persones contribuyeron al códigu de GNOME dende que s'entamara en 1997; munchos más sofitaronlu d'una bayura maneres, incluyendo tornes, documentación y afitando la so seguridá.</p>
    <p xml:lang="az">1997 ilində GNOME layihəsinin yaradılmasından bu günə dək minlərlə insan GNOME kodlarına dəstək vermişdir, onlardan çoxu da tərcümə, sənədlər, keyfiyyət  kimi daha fərqli sahələrdə dəstəklərini əsirgəməmişdir.</p>
    <p xml:lang="be">Сотні людзей зрабілі свой унёсак у код GNOME, пачынаючы зь яго нараджэньня ў 1997; яшчэ больш тых, што дапамагалі разьвіваць асяродзьдзе іншымі неабходнымі справамі: пераклады, напісаньне дакумэнтацыі, назіраньне за якасьцю.</p>
    <p xml:lang="be@latin">Sotni roznych ludziej dapamahali i dapamahajuć napisańniem prahramnaha kodu dla GNOME ad pačatku prajektu ŭ 1987; jašče bolš ludziej pryniali ŭdzieł u pierakładzie, dakumentavańni, testavańni.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bg">Стотици хора допринасят за разработката на GNOME, откакто проектът стартира през 1997-ма и още повече допринасят чрез преводи, документация и контрол на качеството.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bn">শতশত মানুষ সেই ১৯৯৭ সালে গুহ্‌নোম শুরু হওয়ার পর থেকে এর কোডিং-এ অবদান রেখেছে; আরও অনেকে ভাষানুবাদ, ডকুমেন্টেশন এবং গুণগতমানের নিশ্চয়তা সহ অন্যান্য গুরুত্বপূর্ণভাবে অবদান রেখেছে।</p>
    <p xml:lang="bn_IN">১৯৯৭ সালে GNOME আরম্ভ হওয়ার পরে শতশত মানুষ এই ডেস্কটপ নির্মাণের কাজে নিজেদের লেখা কোড  অন্তর্ভুক্ত করেছেন; অন্যান্য অনেকে বিভিন্ন কর্ম যেমন অনুবাদ, নথিপত্র লিখুন ও গুণমান পরীক্ষণে গুরুপূর্ণ যোগদান করেছেন।</p>
    <p xml:lang="br">Kantadoù a dud 'deus kresket danvez diazez  GNOME abaoe m'e bet krouet e 1997; kalz muioc'h ez eus bet o kenlabourat war tachennoù pouezhus all, troidigezhioù, diellerezh, surentezh ha savadur en o zouez.</p>
    <p xml:lang="bs">Stotine ljudi su napisali ponešto koda za GNOME od samog početka 1997. godine; mnogi su doprinijeli i na druge značajne načine, kao što su prijevodi, dokumentacija i kontrola kvaliteta.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ca">Centenars de persones han contribuït codi al GNOME des de que es va començar el 1997; molts més hi han contribuït d'altres maneres importants, que inclouen traduccions, documentació i control de qualitat.</p>
    <p xml:lang="crh">1997'de başlatılğanından berli yüzlerce insan GNOME'ğa kod issesi qoştı; çoq daası, tercimeler, vesiqalandırma ve keyfiyet kontroli dahil olmaq üzre, başqa müim yollar ile isse qoştılar.</p>
    <p xml:lang="cs">Od počátků GNOME v roce 1997 k němu přispěly kódem stovky lidí; mnoho dalších přispělo jinými důležitými způsoby, včetně překladů, dokumentace a kontroly kvality.</p>
    <p xml:lang="cy">Mae cannoedd o bobl wedi cyfrannu côd i GNOME ers iddo gychwyn yn 1997; mae llawer eraill wedi cyfrannu mewn ffyrdd pwysig eraill, yn cynnwys cyfieithiadau, dogfenniaeth, a sicrhau ansawdd.</p>
    <p xml:lang="da">Hundreder af personer har bidraget kode til Gnome siden starten i 1997. Mange flere har bidraget på andre vigtige områder, som f.eks. oversættelse, dokumentation og test.</p>
    <p xml:lang="de">Hunderte von Menschen haben am Quelltext von GNOME mitgewirkt, seit es 1997 ins Leben gerufen wurde; viele weitere haben auf anderem Wege maßgeblich mitgewirkt, einschließlich Übersetzung, Dokumentation und Qualitätssicherung.</p>
    <p xml:lang="dz">ཇི་ནོམ་འདི་ སྤྱི་ལོ་༡༩༩༧ ལུ་ འགོ་བཙུགས་ཞིནམ་ལས་ཚུར་ མི་བརྒྱ་ཕྲག་ལེ་ཤ་ཅིག་གིས་ ཇི་ནོམ་གྱི་ཀོཌི་ལུ་ ཕན་ཐབས་འབད་ཡོདཔ་མ་ཚད་ ལེ་ཤ་ཅིག་གིས་ སྐད་བསྒྱུར་དང་ ཡིག་བཀོད་ སྤུས་ཚད་ལེགས་བཅོས་ཚུ་བརྩིས་ཏེ་ གལ་ཆེའི་ཐབས་ལམ་ གཞན་གྱི་ཐོག་ལས་ ཕན་ཐབས་འབད་ཡི།</p>
    <p xml:lang="el">Εκατοντάδες άνθρωποι έχουν συμβάλλει κώδικα στο Gnome από τότε που ξεκίνησε το 1997. Ακόμη πάρα πολλοί έχουν συμβάλλει με άλλους σημαντικούς τρόπους, συμπεριλαμβανομένων των μεταφράσεων, της τεκμηρίωσης και του έλεγχου ποιότητας.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en_CA">Hundreds of people have contributed code to GNOME since it was started in 1997; many more have contributed in other important ways, including translations, documentation, and quality assurance.</p>
    <p xml:lang="en_GB">Hundreds of people have contributed code to GNOME since it was started in 1997; many more have contributed in other important ways, including translations, documentation, and quality assurance.</p>
    <p xml:lang="eo">Centoj da homoj kontribuis per kodo al GNOME ekde ties komenco en 1997; multaj aliaj kontribuis per aliaj gravaj manieroj kiel tradukoj, dokumentaro, kaj kvalita asekuro.</p>
    <p xml:lang="es">Cientos de personas han contribuido con código a GNOME desde que se inició en 1997, muchísimos otros han contribuido de otras maneras importantes, incluyendo traducciones, documentación y garantizando la calidad.</p>
    <p xml:lang="et">GNOME töölauakeskkonna loomist alustati 1997. aastal, alates sellest ajast on sajad inimesed on GNOME'le koodi kirjutanud ja paljud teised on mitmel muul moel kaasa aidanud: näiteks tõlkimise, dokumentatsiooni kirjutamise ning kvaliteedikontrolliga.</p>
    <p xml:lang="eu">Ehunka lagunek parte hartu dute GNOME kodetzen, 1997an hasi zenetik; beste askok beste modu garrantzitsu batean hartu dute parte, adibidez, itzulpenekin, dokumentazioarekin edo kalitatea bermatuz.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fa">از زمان شروع پروژه‌ی گنوم در سال ۱۹۹۷ صدها نفر در نوشتن کد آن، و تعداد بسیار بیشتری به روش‌های مهم دیگری، از جمله ترجمه، تهیه‌ی مستندات و تضمین کیفیت با آن همکاری کرده‌اند.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fi">Sadat ihmiset ovat ohjelmoineet Gnomen hyväksi projektin käynnistyttyä vuonna 1997, ja monet muut ovat osallistuneet muilla tärkeillä tavoin, kuten kääntämällä sitä toisille kielille, kirjoittamalla ohjeita ja tarkkailemalla laatua.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fr">Des centaines de personnes ont contribué du code au projet GNOME depuis sa naissance en 1997 ; encore plus ont contribué dans d'autres domaines importants tel que les traductions, la documentation, et l'assurance qualité.</p>
    <p xml:lang="fur">Cetancj di lôr e an scrit codifichis par GNOME di cuant che il progjiet al è partît tal 1997; cetancj di plui e an contribuît in altris mûts impuartants, come traduzions, documentazion e control da cualitât.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gl">Centos de persoas levan contribuído con código ao Gnome desde que se iniciou en 1997; moitos máis contribuíron doutras maneiras importantes, que inclúen traducións, documentación e a comprobación de calidade.</p>
    <p xml:lang="gu">જીનોમ ૧૯૯૭ માં શરુ થયુ ત્યારથી અત્યાર સુધી હજારો લોકોએ તેને પોતાનો કોડ ફાળવ્યો છે; બીજા ઘણા બધાએ પોતાનો ફાળો બીજા અનુવાદ, દસ્તાવેજીકરણ, અને ગુણવત્તાની ચકાસણી જેવા મહત્વના માર્ગોએ પૂરો પાડ્યો છે.</p>
    <p xml:lang="he">מאות אנשים תרמו קוד ל GNOME מאז שהוא התחיל ב 1997; רבים אחרים תרמו בדרכים חשובות אחרות, הכוללות תרגומים, תיעוד, וביטחון איכותי.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hi">सन् 1997 से, जब से यह शुरू हुआ है, सैकड़ों लोगों ने कोड का योगदान गनोम को किया है;  बहुत से लोगों ने अन्य महत्वपूर्ण तरीके से योगदान दिया है, जिसमें भाषानुवाद, दस्तावेज़ीकरण तथा गुणवत्ता भरोसा सम्मिलित है.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hr">Stotine ljudi dale su doprinos GNOME kodu od početka 1997; mnogi drugi doprinijeli su na druge važne načine, uključujući prijevode, dokumentaciju i osiguranje kvalitete.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hu">Több száz ember adott hozzá kódot a GNOME-hoz az 1997-es kezdet óta. Sokan más, nem kevésbé fontos módon segítettek, többek között fordítással, dokumentációírással és teszteléssel.</p>
    <p xml:lang="hy">Հարյուրավոր մարդիկ իրենց ավանդն են ներդրել Գնոմը կոդավորելու այն օրից, երբ այդ գործընթացը սկսվեց 1997թ։ Շատերը օժանդակել են այլ կերպ, ներառյալ թարգմանությունները, փաստաթղթերի ձևակերպումը և որակի վերահսկումը։</p>
    <p xml:lang="id">Ratusan orang telah menyumbangkan kode-kode ke proyek GNOME sejak dimulai pada tahun 1997. Belum lagi para penyumbang penting lainnya, termasuk alih bahasa, dokumentasi, dan uji kualitas yang jumlahnya bahkan lebih banyak lagi.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ig">Ọtụtụ ndị mmadụ enyela aka iwebata okwunzobe na GNOME kamgbe ọ bidoro n'afọ 1997; ọtụtụkwa enyekwala n'ụzọ ndị ọzọ dịgasị mkpa, tinyere ntụgharị, dọkumenteshiọn, nakwa ezi ntụkwasaobi.</p>
    <p xml:lang="is">Hundruðir persóna hafa lagt kóða af mörkum síðan GNOME var stofnað 1997. Margir hafa lagt af mörkum á annan hátt þar á meðal með þýðingum, ritun hjálpargagna og gæðastjórnun.</p>
    <p xml:lang="it">Centinaia di persone hanno scritto codice per GNOME fin da quando il progetto è partito nel 1997; molti di più hanno contribuito in altri modi importanti, come traduzioni, documentazione e controllo della qualità.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ja">GNOME プロジェクトが立ち上がった 1997 年以来、プログラム開発に貢献してくれた人達は 数 100 人にものぼります; その多くの人達は、メッセージ翻訳、ドキュメント作成、品質向上のためのバグ報告といったプログラム開発以外の重要な部分で貢献してくれました。</p>
    <p xml:lang="ka">1997 წლიდან ასობით ადამიანმა ინტერნეტის მეშვეობით მიიღო მონაწილეობა გნომის პროექტში, არა მარტო პროგრამირებით, არამედ თარგმნით, მისი ტესტირებით და შეცდომათა გასწორებით.</p>
    <p xml:lang="kk">GNOME жобасы 1997 басталғаннан бері бастпқы кодты жазуда жүздеген адам еңбек етті, бірақ оны аудару мен көркейтуде одан да көп адам атсалысты.</p>
    <p xml:lang="kn">GNOME ಅನ್ನು 1997ರಲ್ಲಿ ಆರಂಭಿಸಿದ ನಂತರ ನೂರಾರು ಜನ ಅದರ ಕೋಡ್‌ ಬರೆಯುವಲ್ಲಿ ನೆರವಾಗಿದ್ದಾರೆ; ಹಲವಾರು ಜನರು, ಅನುವಾದಗಳು, ದಸ್ತಾವೇಜು ಬರೆಯುವಿಕೆ, ಹಾಗು ಗುಣಮಟ್ಟದ ಭರವಸೆ ಕಾರ್ಯ ಹಾಗು ಇನ್ನೂ ಅನೇಕ ರೀತಿಯಲ್ಲಿ ನೆರವಾಗಿದ್ದಾರೆ.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ko">1997년에 시작된 이래로 수백명이 사람들이 그놈의 코드에 공헌했습니다; 그보다 훨씬 많은 사람들이 번역, 문서화, 품질 보증 등의 다른 중요한 방식으로 그놈에 공헌했습니다.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ku">Ji sala 1997an ku GNOME dest pê kir, bi sedan kes piştgiriyê dan kodkirina GNOME'yê; wekî din gelek kesên din bi wergerandin, belgekirin, kontrolkirina kalîteyê û bi gelek riyên din piştgiriyê dan GNOME'yê.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ky">GNOME проекти 1997-жылы башталгандан тартып анын башат кодун жүздөгөн адамдар жазды, бирок андан да көп адамдар башка маанилүү жолдор менен б.а. которуу, документациялоо жана сапатын текшерүү аркылуу өз салымдарын кошушту.</p>
    <p xml:lang="lt">Nuo GNOME projekto pradžios, 1997 metais, prie GNOME savo parašytu kodu prisidėjo šimtai žmonių; daug daugiau žmonių prisidėjo prie jo kitais labai svarbiais būdais: vertimu, dokumentacijos rašymu ir kokybės tikrinimu.</p>
    <p xml:lang="lv">Simtiem cilvēku ir dalījušies ar savu izstrādes kodu, jau no pašiem GNOME sākumiem kopš 1997. gada; vēl vairāk cilvēku ir palīdzējuši citos nozīmīgos veidos, kā tulkošana, dokumentācijas rakstīšana, un kvalitātes pārbaude.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mai">सन् 1997 सँ, जखन सँ ई शुरू भेल अछि सैकड़ासभ लोकनिसभ कोड क' योगदान गनोमकेँ केने अछि बहुते लोकनिसभ आन महत्वपूर्ण रूपेँ योगदान देने अछि जकरामे भाषानुवाद, दस्ताबेजीकरण आओरगुणवत्ता भरोसा सामिल अछि.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mg"> Olona aman-jatony no efa nanome fango an'ny GNOME hatramin'ny namoronana azy tamin'ny 1997. Maro toraka izany koa ireo olona nitondra fanampiana isan-karazany, toy ny fandikan-teny, ny loharanon-kevitra, ary ny fiantohana kalitao.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mk">Во создавањето на GNOME имаат удел стотици луѓе. Уште од кога е започнат проектот во 1997, многу луѓе имаат помогнато на разни начини вклучувајќи и преведување, изработување на документација и проверка на квалитетот.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ml">1997 ല്‍ ഗ്നോം തുടങ്ങിയതു് മുതല്‍ നൂറുകണക്കിനു് ആളുകള്‍ ഗ്നോമിലേയ്ക്കു് കോഡ് സംഭാവന ചെയ്തിട്ടുണ്ടു്; ഇതിലും എത്രയോ അധികം ആളുകള്‍ പരിഭാഷ, വിവരണം, ഗുണനിലവാരം ഉറപ്പുവരുത്തല്‍ എന്നിവയുള്‍‌പ്പെടെയുള്ള മറ്റു് പ്രധാന വഴികളിലൂടെ സംഭാവന ചെയ്തിട്ടുണ്ടു്.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mn">ГНОМЕ 1997 онд үүссэнээс хойш зуу зуун хүн код нэмэрлэсэн ба түүнээс олон хүн түүний орчуулга, баримтжуулалт болон чанарын баталгаанд хувь нэмрээ оруулсан юм.</p>
    <p xml:lang="mr">१९९७ मध्ये सुरू झाल्यापासून आजवर शेकडो लोकांनी GNOME साठी कोडचे योगदान केले आहे; इतर अनेकांनी निरनिराळ्या महत्वाच्या मार्गांनी योगदान केले आहे, ज्यात अनुवाद, दस्तऐवजीकरण, आणि दर्जा हमी यांचा समावेश होतो.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ms">Beratus-ratus orang telah menyumbangkan kod ke GNOME sejak ia ditubuhkan pada 1997, banyak lagi telah menyumbangkan dalam bentuk penting lain, termasuk terjemahan, dokumentasi, dan pemeriksaan kualiti.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nb">Hundrevis av mennesker har bidratt kode til GNOME siden prosjektet ble startet i 1997. Mange flere har bidratt på andre viktige måter som oversettelse, dokumentasjon og kvalitetssikring.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ne">१९९७ मा जीनोम सुरआत भए देखि नै सयौं मानिसहरूले जीनोममा कोड योगदान गर्नुभएको छ; धेरै धेरैले अनुवाद, मिसिलिकरण, र गुणात्मक आश्वासन समेत गरेर अन्य महत्वपूर्ण तरिकाले योगदान गर्नुभएको छ,</p>
    <p xml:lang="nl">Sinds de start van Gnome in 1997 hebben al honderden mensen programmacode voor Gnome geschreven. Nog meer mensen hebben bijgedragen op een andere belangrijke manier door bijvoorbeeld te vertalen, te documenteren, en te zorgen voor kwaliteit.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nn">Hundrevis av menneske har vore med og programmert GNOME sidan prosjektet starta i 1997. Mange fleire har hjelpt til på andre viktige måtar, t.d. omsetjing, dokumentasjon og kvalitetssikring.</p>
    <p xml:lang="nso">Batho ba makgolo ba tsenthite letsogo khoutung go GNOME ga e sa le e thoma ka 1997; ba banti ba tsenthite letsogo ka ditsela te dingwe te bohlokwa, go akaretwa diphetolelo, ditweleto, le kgonthieto ya khwaliti.</p>
    <p xml:lang="oc">Centenats de personas participèron al còde del projècte GNOME dempuèi sa creacion en 1997 ; encara mai participèron d'autres biaisses  importants, coma las reviradas, la documentacion e l'assegurança qualitat.</p>
    <p xml:lang="or">୧୯୯୭ ମସିହାରୁ ନୋମର ଆରମ୍ଭଠାରୁ, ଶହ ଶହ ଲୋକ କାରିକା ଲେଖିବାରେ ଯୋଗଦାନ ଦେଇଛନ୍ତି; ଆହୁରି ଅନେକ ଲୋକ ଅନ୍ଯ ମହତ୍ତ୍ବପୂର୍ଣ ଭାବରେ ଯୋଗଦାନ ଦେଇଛନ୍ତି, ଯେପରି କି ଅନୁବାଦ, ଦଲିଲିକରଣ, ଓ ଗୁଣବତ୍ତା ସ୍ବୀକୃତି.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pa">੧੯੯੭ ਤੋਂ ਕਈ ਸੈਂਕਡ਼ੈ ਲੋਕ ਗਨੋਮ ਨੂੰ ਕੋਡ ਬਣਾਉਣ ਲਈ ਸਹਿਯੋਗ ਕਰ ਰਹੇ ਹਨ, ਕਈ ਹੋਰ ਲੋਕ ਹੋਰ ਤਰ੍ਹਾਂ ਸਹਿਯੋਗ ਕਰ ਰਹੇ ਹਨ ਜਿਵੇਂ ਕਿ ਭਾਸ਼ਾ ਅਨੁਵਾਦ, ਦਸਤਾਵੇਜ਼ ਜਾਂ ਕੁਆਲਟੀ ਚੈੱਕ ਲਈ।</p>
    <p xml:lang="pl">Od rozpoczęcia projektu GNOME w 1997 roku, współudział w tworzeniu kodu miało setki osób; dużo więcej brało udział na inne ważne sposoby, włączając tłumaczenia, dokumentację oraz zapewnienie jakości.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt">Centenas de pessoas contribuiram com código para o GNOME desde que este foi iniciado, em 1997; muitos mais contribuiram de outras formas importantes, incluindo traduções, documentação e controlo de qualidade.</p>
    <p xml:lang="pt_BR">Centenas de pessoas contribuíram código para o GNOME desde o seu início em 1997; muitos outros contribuíram de outras formas importantes, como incluindo traduções, documentação e garantia de qualidade.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ro">Sute de oameni au contribuit la realizarea mediului GNOME încă de la lansarea sa în 1997. Chiar mai mulți au contribuit în alte moduri, precum documentația, traducerile și testarea calităţii.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ru">Сотни человек писали исходный код среды GNOME с момента старта проекта в 1997 году, но гораздо больше людей внесли свой вклад в развитие среды другими важными путями, такими как перевод, документирование и контроль качества.</p>
    <p xml:lang="si">1997 දි GNOME ආරම්භ කළ දිනසිට සිය ගණනක් පිරිස් කේත රචනය සඳහා දායකත්වය සැපයූහ; තවත් බොහෝ දෙනා පරිවර්තනය, ලේඛණාරූඩ කිරීම සහ තත්ව පාලනය ඇතුලු වැදගත් අයුරින් දායක විය.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sk">Stovky ľudí vytvorili GNOME od doby, ako projekt vznikol v roku 1997. Veľa ďalších prispelo iným spôsobom, napríklad prekladmi, dokumentáciou a kontrolou kvality.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sl">GNOME je od svojega začetka leta 1997 združeval na stotine programerjev; veliko več jih je pomagalo na drugačne pomembne načine; prevajanje, dokumentiranje in zagotavljanje kakovosti.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sq">Qindra persona kanë kontribuar duke shkruar kod në GNOME që nga fillimi i projektit në 1997; shumë të tjerë kanë kontribuar në menyra të tjera të rendësishme, si përkthime, dokumentime, dhe në kontrollin e cilësisë.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sr">Стотине људи су написали понешто кода за Гном од његовог зачећа 1997. године; многи су допринели и на друге значајне начине, као што су преводи, документација, и контрола квалитета.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sr@latin">Stotine ljudi su napisali ponešto koda za Gnom od njegovog začeća 1997. godine; mnogi su doprineli i na druge značajne načine, kao što su prevodi, dokumentacija, i kontrola kvaliteta.</p>
    <p xml:lang="sv">Hundratals personer har bidragit med kod till GNOME sedan projektet startades 1997. Långt flera har bidragit på andra viktiga sätt, inklusive översättningar, dokumentation, och kvalitetssäkring.</p>
    <p xml:lang="ta">1997இல் தொடங்கியதிலிருந்து பல நூற்றுக்கனக்கானோர் கனோமுக்கு மூலக் குறிமுறை வழங்கியுல்லார்கள்; பலர் மொழிப்பெயர்ப்பு, ஆவணம் மற்றும் தரக் கட்டுப்பாடு மூலமாக ஆதரவளித்துள்ளனர்.</p>
    <p xml:lang="te">గ్నోమ్ ను 1997లో ప్రారంభించినప్పట్నుంచి  వందలాదిమంది  దీని    సంకేత రచనలో సహాయపడ్డారు.చాలామంది అనువదీకరణలో, వివరణపత్రాన్ని రచించడంలో మరియు నాణ్యతా ప్రమాణాలను సాధించడంలో సహాయపడ్డారు.</p>
    <p xml:lang="th">ผู้คนหลายร้อยได้ร่วมกันพัฒนาโปรแกรมสำหรับ GNOME นับแต่เริ่มโครงการเมื่อปี 2540 และยังมีอีกมาก ที่ช่วยส่งเสริมในทางอื่น ๆ เช่น การแปล เขียนเอกสารคู่มือ และ ตรวจสอบคุณภาพ</p>
    <p xml:lang="tk">Ýüzlerçe adamlar 1997 da GNOME başlanany bäri öniň cödina kömekleyärlä; ýene kän adamlar başga möhüm ýollardan meselen terjime, dökümentlemä weýaramlylik itminanlamak kömekleyärlä.</p>
    <p xml:lang="tr">1997'de başladığından beri yüzlerce insan GNOME'un kodlamasına katkıda bulundu; çok daha fazlası tercümeyi, belgelendirmeyi ve kalite kontrolünü kapsayan başka önemli yollarla katkıda bulundular.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uk">Сотні людей долучили свій код до проекту GNOME, який було засновано у 1997 році. Значно більше людей долучилися до проекту іншими способами, включаючи переклади, документування і контроль якості.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uz">1997 yil GNOME loyihasi boshlangandan beri, yuzlab insonlar uning asl kodiga oʻz hissalarini qoʻshdilar, ammo bundan ham koʻp insonlar tarjimalar, qoʻllanmalar va sifatni oshirish boʻyicha oʻz hissalarini qoʻshdilar.</p>
    <p xml:lang="uz@cyrillic">1997 йил GNOME лойиҳаси бошлангандан бери, юзлаб инсонлар унинг асл кодига ўз ҳиссаларини қўшдилар, аммо бундан ҳам кўп инсонлар таржималар, қўлланмалар ва сифатни ошириш бўйича ўз ҳиссаларини қўшдилар.</p>
    <p xml:lang="vi">Hàng trăm người đã đóng góp mã cho GNOME kể từ năm 1997, rất nhiều người đóng góp vào các phần quan trọng khác như dịch thuật, viết tài liệu và quản lí chất lượng.</p>
    <p xml:lang="wa">Des cints et des cints di djins ont contribuwé å côde di Gnome dispoy k' il a stî enondé e 1997; co bén pus ont contribuwé dins ds ôtes manires, tot ossu impôrtantes, come li ratournaedje, li scrijhaedje del documintåcion, eyet li contrôle del cwålité.</p>
    <p xml:lang="xh">Amakhulu abantu abe negalelo kwikhowudi ye-GNOME ukususela ekuqalisweni kwayo ngowe-1997; baninzi ababe negalelo ngeendlela ezizezinye ezibalulekileyo, kubandakanywa uguqulelo, ugcino kumaxwebhu, nokuqinisekiswa kodidi.</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_CN">自 GNOME 项目 1997 年启动一来，数以百计的人不断地贡献出他们编写的代码。此外，还有更多人在其它方面做出了重要努力，包括翻译、文档和质量控制。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_HK">在 1997 年創立後，數以百計的人都在編寫 GNOME 方面作出貢獻；還有更多人以其它方式貢獻，包括翻譯、撰寫文件和進行品質測試。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zh_TW">在 1997 年創立後，數以百計的人都在編寫 GNOME 方面作出貢獻；還有更多人以其它方式貢獻，包括翻譯、撰寫文件和進行品質測試。</p>
    <p xml:lang="zu">Amakhulukhlu abantu anikele ukubhalwa kwezinhlelo ku GNOME kususela iqanjwa ngo-1997; abanye abaningi banikele ngezinye izindlela ezibalulekile, kufakwa nokuhunyushwa, ukubhalwa, nokugcizelela okuhle.</p>
  </description>
</gnome-version>