<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
<article id="add-applications" status="review">
	<articleinfo>
	<title>Adding, Removing and Updating Applications</title>
    	&legalnotice;
	</articleinfo>
	<para>This section discusses how applications are installed, removed and kept up-to-date. Also covered are how packages are stored by Ubuntu and made available for download.</para>

<sect1 id="installation-windows-ubuntu" status="draft">
    <title>How is software installation on Ubuntu different from on Windows?</title>
    <para>
    Ubuntu handles software installation in a very different way to Windows.
    </para>
    <para>
    If you want to install an application on Windows, you must normally buy a 
    CD containing the software, or download an installer package from the 
    Internet. You then run the installer program, which guides you through the 
    installation process.
    </para>
    <para>
    On Ubuntu, you simply open a <emphasis>package manager</emphasis>, search 
    for the application that you want and click a button to install it. 
    Removing an application is just as simple.
    </para>
    <para>
    The package manager downloads applications from a <emphasis>software 
    repository</emphasis>, which is a location on the Internet which stores a 
    collection of applications. These applications come bundled in 
    <emphasis>packages</emphasis>, which contain all of the information needed 
    for installation. You can download packages yourself, using your web 
    browser, if you like, but it is generally much more convenient to let the 
    package manager handle this for you.
    </para>
    <para>
    Some packages depend on other packages being installed in order to work. 
    For example, a word processing package may require a printing package to be 
    installed. The package manager automatically installs these 
    <emphasis>dependencies</emphasis> for you.
    </para>
    <para>
    By default, only applications from the official Ubuntu software 
    repositories are available in your package manager. If you cannot find the 
    application that you want in the default repositories, you can add other 
    (<quote>third-party</quote>) repositories and install it from there.
    </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="installing" status="draft">
    <title>Installing an application</title>
    <procedure>
    <step>
        <para>Click &gnome-app-install;.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Search for an application, or select a category and find an 
        application from the list.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Check the box next to the application that you want to install. 
        Do this for all of the applications that you want to install.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Click <guibutton>Apply Changes</guibutton>, then click 
        <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> to start the installation.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Enter your password if prompted. The applications that you chose 
        will be downloaded and installed.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Once installation has finished, your new applications should be 
        available from the Applications menu.</para>
    </step>
    </procedure>

<sect2 id="installing-others" status="draft">
    <title>Other methods of installing applications</title>

<sect3 id="installing-synaptic" status="draft">
    <title>Using Synaptic Package Manager</title>
    <para>
    Synaptic can be used to manage advanced software packages (such as server 
    applications) which Add/Remove Applications does not manage.
    </para>
    <procedure>
    <step>
        <para>Click &synaptic;. Enter your password if prompted.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Click <guibutton>Search</guibutton> to search for an application, 
        or click <guibutton>Sections</guibutton> and look through the 
        categories to find one.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Right-click the application that you want to install and select 
        <guilabel>Mark for Installation</guilabel>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>If you are asked if you would like to mark additional changes, 
        click <guibutton>Mark</guibutton>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Select any other applications that you would like to 
        install.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Click <guibutton>Apply</guibutton>, and then click 
        <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> in the window that appears. The 
        applications that you chose will be downloaded and installed.</para>
    </step>
    </procedure>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="installing-deb" status="draft">
    <title>Downloading and installing a .deb package</title>
    <para>
    You can download and install applications from websites. These applications 
    are contained in Debian (.deb) packages. To install a Debian package:
    </para>
    <procedure>
    <step>
        <para>Download the package from a website.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Double-click the package. It will be opened in the Package 
        Installer.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Click <guibutton>Install</guibutton> to install the 
        package.</para>
    </step>
    </procedure>
    
    <para>
    Installing single packages in this way is not recommended, for the 
    following reasons:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
        <para>The packages have not been checked for security by Ubuntu 
        members, and could contain software which harms your computer. You 
        should only download single packages from websites that you trust.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
        <para>The package may require some extra software to run, which cannot 
        be installed automatically. You will have to find and install this 
        software yourself.</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</sect3>

<sect3 id="installing-webpage" status="draft">
    <title>Clicking a link on a web page</title>
    <para>
    Some web pages have links which install applications when you click them. 
    These are known as <quote>apt:</quote> links. After clicking the link, you 
    will be asked if you would like to install additional software. Click 
    <guibutton>Install</guibutton> to start the installation process.
    </para>
    <para>
    The application can only be downloaded and installed if it is available in 
    a software repository which is currently enabled on your computer. This 
    means that websites cannot trick you into installing software which is 
    potentially harmful to your computer.
    </para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="removing" status="draft">
    <title>Removing an application</title>
    <procedure>
    <step>
        <para>Click &gnome-app-install;.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Find the application that you want to remove by finding it in 
        the list or by searching for it.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Uncheck the box next to the application that you want to remove. 
        Do this for all of the applications you want to remove.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Click <guibutton>Apply Changes</guibutton>, then click 
        <guibutton>Apply</guibutton> to remove the applications. Enter your 
        password if prompted.</para>
    </step>
    </procedure>
    <para>
    Some applications depend on others being installed in order to work 
    properly. If you try to remove an application which is required by another 
    application, both of those applications will be removed. You will be asked 
    to confirm that this is what you want to happen before the applications 
    are removed.</para>
    <para>
    If the application that you want to uninstall is not available in 
    Add/Remove Applications, use Synaptic (&synaptic;) to remove it instead.
    </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="adding-repos" status="draft">
    <title>Adding a software repository</title>
    <para>
    Software is available from third-party sources, as well as from the default 
    Ubuntu software repositories. If you want to install software from a 
    third-party software repository, you must add it to the package manager's 
    list of available repositories.
    </para>
    <caution>
    <para>
    Only add software repositories from sources that you trust. Third-party 
    software repositories are not checked for security by Ubuntu members, so 
    could contain software which is harmful to your computer.
    </para>
    </caution>
    <procedure>
    <step>
        <para>Open &software-sources; and select <guilabel>Third Party 
        Software</guilabel>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Click <guibutton>Add</guibutton> to add a new repository.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Enter the APT line for the extra repository. This should be 
        available from the website of the repository, and should look similar 
        to the following:</para>
        <screen>deb http://ftp.debian.org etch main</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Click <guibutton>Add Source</guibutton> and then click 
        <guibutton>Close</guibutton> to save your changes.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>You will be notified that the information about available 
        software is out-of-date. Click <guibutton>Reload</guibutton>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Packages from the new repository should now be available in your 
        package manager.</para>
    </step>
    </procedure>
    <para>
    As a security measure, most software repositories use a GPG key to 
    digitally sign the files they provide. This makes it easy to check that the 
    files have not been tampered with since their creation. In order for your 
    package manager to be able to check this, you need the public key that 
    corresponds to the signatures. The key should be available for download on 
    the repository's website.
    </para>
    <para>
    Download the GPG key. Then, click &software-sources;, select the 
    <guilabel>Authentication</guilabel> tab, click <guibutton>Import Key 
    File</guibutton> and select the GPG key to be imported.
    </para>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="offline" status="draft">
    <title>Installing software packages without an Internet connection</title>
    <para>
    If you are not connected to the Internet, you can use a CD containing 
    package files to install applications on your computer. The Ubuntu 
    installation CD can be used for this purpose, and other CDs with different 
    packages are available as well. Additionally, the program 
    <application>APTonCD</application> can automatically backup installed 
    packages on your system, and create CDs with the contents of various 
    repositories on them.
    </para>
    
<sect2 id="ubuntu-installation-cd" status="review">
    <title>Installing packages using the Ubuntu installation CD</title>
    <para>
    Some packages from the <emphasis>main</emphasis> and 
    <emphasis>restricted</emphasis> Ubuntu package repositories can be 
    installed from the Ubuntu installation CD. Simply insert your Ubuntu 
    installation CD and open &synaptic;. To list only packages on the 
    Ubuntu installation CD, click on the <guibutton>Origin</guibutton> 
    button in the lower left corner of the Synaptic window. The packages 
    should be listed under the 
    <guimenuitem>&distro-apt-cd-name;</guimenuitem> section.
    </para>
    <para>
    If the packages are not listed, it may be because the CD is not listed 
    as a package repository (the CD should be listed as a repository by 
    default). To add the CD as a package repository, follow the 
    instructions in <xref linkend="repository-cds"/>, below.
    </para>	
</sect2>

<sect2 id="repository-cds" status="review">
    <title>Enabling other CDs that can be used to install packages</title>
    <para>
    To enable Synaptic and other package managers to install software from 
    CDs which contain packages:
    </para>
    <procedure>
    <step>
        <para>Click &software-sources;.</para> 
    </step>
    <step>
        <para>Select <guilabel>Third Party Software</guilabel> and click on 
        the <guibutton>Add CD-ROM</guibutton> button.</para>
    </step> 
    <step>
        <para>Insert the CD.</para>
    </step>
    </procedure>
    <para>
    The packages should then be listed. To have Synaptic only list packages 
    from the CD, click the <guibutton>Origin</guibutton> button on the 
    lower left corner of the Synaptic window and then find the name of the 
    CD in the list in the upper left corner the window.
    </para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="aptoncd" status="review">
    <title>Using APTonCD to install packages</title>
    <para>
    <application>APTonCD</application> can be used to create a CD that 
    contains all the packages you have on your system, or it can create 
    CDs with packages or entire repositories of your choice. In a package 
    manager such as <application>Synaptic</application>, find the 
    <emphasis>aptoncd</emphasis> package and install it.
    </para>
    <para>
    Further documentation on APTonCD can be found on its website, 
    <ulink url="http://aptoncd.sourceforge.net">
    aptoncd.sourceforge.net</ulink>
    </para>
</sect2>
</sect1>


<sect1 id="restricted-software" status="draft">
    <title>What are restricted and non-free software?</title>
    <para>
    Most of the software available for Ubuntu is free, open-source software. 
    This software is free for anyone to install and use, and people can modify 
    the software and redistribute it if they like. Ubuntu is built from this 
    type of software.
    </para>
    <para>
    <emphasis role='strong'>Non-free software</emphasis> is software which is 
    not freely redistributable or modifiable. This makes it difficult for the 
    Ubuntu developers to improve the software and correct problems, so it is 
    normally recommended that you use <ulink url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">
    free software</ulink> instead.
    </para>
    <para>
    <emphasis role='strong'>Restricted software</emphasis> is software which 
    has restrictions on its use, preventing it from being classed as free 
    software. Non-free software is a type of restricted software, where the 
    restrictions are due to the software having a non-free license. Other 
    reasons for software being classed as restricted include legal issues (use 
    of some types of software is illegal in some countries) and patent issues 
    (some software requires a patent license to be used legally).
    </para>
    <para>
    In some cases, restricted software is the only option. Such cases include 
    software for the playback of certain audio and video formats, some fonts 
    and <ulink type='help' url="ghelp:hardware#restricted-manager">drivers for 
    some graphics cards</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
    You should be warned by the package manager when you try to install 
    restricted software. If the restricted software cannot be used legally in 
    your country then there is little you can do; you should not install the 
    software. If the software is restricted simply because it is non-free, you 
    may choose to use it (for example, in the case of graphics card drivers). 
    Be aware that most restricted software is not supported in Ubuntu, and 
    problems with such software often cannot be corrected by Ubuntu developers.
    </para>
    
    <warning>
    <para>
    Sometimes it is difficult to determine why a particular software package is 
    restricted. If this is the case, seek advice on the 
    <ulink url="http://ubuntuforums.org/">Ubuntu Forums</ulink>. If you are 
    still unable to determine why a package is restricted, err on the side 
    of caution and do not install it; it may be illegal to use it in your 
    country.
    </para>
    </warning>
</sect1>

<sect1 id="default-repos" status="draft">
    <title>Overview of the default Ubuntu software repositories</title>
    <para>
    When you install software on Ubuntu, the package manager automatically 
    downloads the required software packages from a 
    <emphasis>software repository</emphasis>, a location on the Internet which 
    stores collections of packages ready to be downloaded.
    </para>
    <para>
    There are thousands of programs available to install on Ubuntu. These 
    programs are stored in software repositories and are made freely available 
    for all Ubuntu users. This makes it very easy to install new programs, and 
    it is also very secure because each program you install is built specially 
    for Ubuntu and checked before it is allowed into the repositories.
    </para>

<sect2 id="default-repos-main" status="draft">
    <title>Software repositories</title>
    <para>
    To organize the software, Ubuntu repositories are categorized into four 
    groups: <emphasis>Main</emphasis>, <emphasis>Restricted</emphasis>, 
    <emphasis>Universe</emphasis>, and <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis>. The 
    rationale used to determine which software goes into which category is 
    based on the level of support that software development teams provide for a 
    program and the level of compliance the program has to the 
    <ulink url="&ubuntu-philosophy;">Free Software Philosophy</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
    The standard Ubuntu Install CD contains some software from the 
    <emphasis>Main</emphasis> and <emphasis>Restricted</emphasis> categories.
    </para>
    <para>
    If your system is connected to the Internet, many more software programs 
    are made available for installation. For example, the 
    <quote>Universe</quote> and <quote>Multiverse</quote> repositories are only 
    available over the Internet.
    </para>
    <warning>
        <para>
        The <emphasis>Multiverse</emphasis> repository contains software which 
        has been classified as <emphasis>non-free</emphasis>. This software 
        may not be permitted in some jurisdictions. When installing each 
        package from this repository, you should verify that the laws of your 
        country permit you to use it. Also, this software may not include 
        security updates.
        </para>
    </warning>
</sect2>

<sect2 id="default-repos-update" status="draft">
    <title>Update repositories</title>
    <para>
    The Update Manager automatically finds software updates for your computer 
    when they are available. It regularly gathers information on potential 
    updates from a number of online update sources.
    </para>
    <para>
    If you click &software-properties; and select the 
    <guilabel>Updates</guilabel> tab, you will notice that four update sources 
    are available. An explanation for each of these is provided below:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Important security updates:</emphasis>
        Updates which fix critical security flaws are made available through 
        this source. It is recommended that all users leave this source enabled 
        (it should be enabled by default).
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Recommended updates:</emphasis>
        Updates which fix serious software problems (which are not security 
        flaws) are made available through this source. Most users will want to 
        leave this source enabled as common and annoying problems are often 
        fixed with these updates.
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Pre-released updates:</emphasis>
        Updates which are currently being tested before being released to 
        everyone are provided through this update source. If you would like to 
        help test new updates (and get fixes for problems more quickly), enable 
        this source. Be aware that these updates may not yet be well tested; it 
        is not recommended that you enable this source unless you are prepared 
        to experience occasional problems.
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <emphasis role='strong'>Unsupported updates:</emphasis>
        When new versions of popular software are released they are sometimes 
        <quote>back-ported</quote> to an older version of Ubuntu so that users 
        can benefit from new features and fixes for problems. These backports 
        are unsupported, may cause problems when installed and should only be 
        used by people who are in desperate need of a new version of a software 
        package which they know has been backported.
        </para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1>

</article>
