<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY gnomeversion "2.24">
<!ENTITY manrevision "2.24.0">
<!ENTITY date "September 2008">
<!ENTITY LEGAL SYSTEM "legal.xml">
<!ENTITY accessintro SYSTEM "accessintro.xml">
<!ENTITY sysadmin SYSTEM "sysadmin.xml">
<!ENTITY low-vision SYSTEM "low-vision.xml">
<!ENTITY mobility SYSTEM "mobility.xml">
<!ENTITY general SYSTEM "general.xml">
<!ENTITY author1 "Sun">
<!ENTITY author2 "Java Desktop System Documentation Team">
]>
<?db.chunk.max_depth 4?>
<book id="index" lang="ja"> 
<title>支援ツール</title> 
<bookinfo> 
<abstract role="description">
<para>
This guide is for users, system administrators, and anyone who is interested in how Ubuntu supports people with disabilities and addresses the requirements of Section 508 of the U.S. Rehabilitation Act.
</para>
</abstract>
<copyright> 
<year>2006</year>
<holder>Don Scorgie</holder>
</copyright>
<copyright> 
<year>2006</year>
<holder>Brent Smith</holder>
</copyright>
<copyright> 
<year>2005</year>
<year>2004</year>
<year>2003</year>
<year>2002</year>
<holder>Sun Microsystems, Inc.</holder> 
</copyright>

<!--  translators: uncomment this:
  <copyright>
   <year>2002</year>
   <holder>ME-THE-TRANSLATOR (Latin translation)</holder>
  </copyright>
-->

<publisher role="maintainer"> 
<publishername>GNOME Documentation Project</publishername> 
</publisher>

<legalnotice id="legalnotice">
<para>
Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License (GFDL), Version 1.1 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. You can find a copy of the GFDL 
<ulink type="help" url="ghelp:fdl"> here</ulink> or in the file COPYING-DOCS distributed with this manual.
</para>
<para> 
This manual is part of a collection of GNOME manuals distributed under the GFDL. If you want to distribute this manual separately from the collection, you can do so by adding a copy of the license to the manual, as 
described in Section 6 of the license.
</para>
<para>
Many of the names used by companies to distinguish their products and services are claimed as trademarks. Where those names appear in any GNOME documentation, and the members of the GNOME Documentation Project are made aware of those trademarks, then the names are in capital letters or initial capital letters.
</para>
<para>DOCUMENT AND MODIFIED VERSIONS OF THE DOCUMENT ARE PROVIDED UNDER THE TERMS OF THE GNU FREE DOCUMENTATION LICENSE WITH THE FURTHER UNDERSTANDING THAT: <orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>DOCUMENT IS PROVIDED ON AN "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, EITHER EXPRESSED OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, WARRANTIES THAT THE DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED VERSION OF THE DOCUMENT IS FREE OF DEFECTS MERCHANTABLE, FIT FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE OR NON-INFRINGING. THE ENTIRE RISK AS TO THE QUALITY, ACCURACY, AND PERFORMANCE OF THE DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED VERSION OF THE DOCUMENT IS WITH YOU. SHOULD ANY DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED VERSION PROVE DEFECTIVE IN ANY RESPECT, YOU (NOT THE INITIAL WRITER, AUTHOR OR ANY CONTRIBUTOR) ASSUME THE COST OF ANY NECESSARY SERVICING, REPAIR OR CORRECTION. THIS DISCLAIMER OF WARRANTY CONSTITUTES AN ESSENTIAL PART OF THIS LICENSE. NO USE OF ANY DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED VERSION OF THE DOCUMENT IS AUTHORIZED HEREUNDER EXCEPT UNDER THIS DISCLAIMER; AND</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>UNDER NO CIRCUMSTANCES AND UNDER NO LEGAL THEORY, WHETHER IN TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE), CONTRACT, OR OTHERWISE, SHALL THE AUTHOR, INITIAL WRITER, ANY CONTRIBUTOR, OR ANY DISTRIBUTOR OF THE DOCUMENT OR MODIFIED VERSION OF THE DOCUMENT, OR ANY SUPPLIER OF ANY OF SUCH PARTIES, BE LIABLE TO ANY PERSON FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, SPECIAL, INCIDENTAL, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES OF ANY CHARACTER INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, DAMAGES FOR LOSS OF GOODWILL, WORK STOPPAGE, COMPUTER FAILURE OR MALFUNCTION, OR ANY AND ALL OTHER DAMAGES OR LOSSES ARISING OUT OF OR RELATING TO USE OF THE DOCUMENT AND MODIFIED VERSIONS OF THE DOCUMENT, EVEN IF SUCH PARTY SHALL HAVE BEEN INFORMED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGES.</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist></para>
</legalnotice>
 

<authorgroup> 
<author>
<firstname>Vincent</firstname>
<surname>Alexander</surname>
<affiliation>
<orgname>GNOME Documentation Project</orgname>
</affiliation>
</author>

<author>
<firstname>Don</firstname>
<surname>Scorgie</surname>
<affiliation>
<orgname>GNOME Documentation Project</orgname>
</affiliation>
</author>

<author>
<firstname>Brent</firstname>
<surname>Smith</surname>
<affiliation>
<orgname>GNOME Documentation Project</orgname>
</affiliation>
</author>

<author> 
<firstname>Sun</firstname> 
<surname>Java Desktop System Documentation Team</surname> 
<affiliation> 
<orgname>Sun Microsystems, Inc.</orgname>  
</affiliation> 
</author> 
</authorgroup>

<revhistory>
<revision> 
<revnumber>
GNOME 2.24
Desktop Accessibility Guide V2.24.0
</revnumber> 
<date>September 2008</date> 
<revdescription> 
<para role="author">GNOME Documentation Project</para> 
<para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para> 
</revdescription> 
</revision>

<revision> 
<revnumber>
GNOME 2.24
Desktop Accessibility Guide V2.24.0
</revnumber> 
<date>September 2008</date> 
<revdescription> 
<para role="author">GNOME Documentation Project</para> 
<para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para> 
</revdescription> 
</revision>

<revision> 
<revnumber>
GNOME 2.10 Desktop Accessibility Guide V2.10.1
</revnumber> 
<date>2005年7月</date> 
<revdescription> 
<para role="author">
Sun Java Desktop System Documentation Team
</para> 
<para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para> 
</revdescription> 
</revision>

<revision> 
<revnumber>GNOME 2.10 デスクトップ操作ガイド V2.10.0</revnumber> 
<date>2005年3月</date> 
<revdescription> 
<para role="author">
Sun Java Desktop System Documentation Team
</para> 
<para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para> 
</revdescription> 
</revision>

<revision> 
<revnumber>
GNOME 2.8 Desktop Accessibility Guide V2.8.0
</revnumber> 
<date>2004年9月</date> 
<revdescription> 
<para role="author">
Sun Java Desktop System Documentation Team
</para> 
<para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para> 
</revdescription> 

</revision>
<revision> 
<revnumber>
GNOME 2.6 Desktop Accessibility Guide V2.6.0
</revnumber> 
<date>2004年3月</date> 
<revdescription> 
<para role="author">Sun Microsystems</para> 
<para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para> 
</revdescription> 
</revision>

<revision> 
<revnumber>
GNOME 2.4 Desktop Accessibility Guide V2.4.0
</revnumber> 
<date>2003年10月</date> 
<revdescription> 
<para role="author">
Sun Microsystems
</para> 
<para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para> 
</revdescription> 
</revision>

<revision> 
<revnumber>
GNOME 2.2 Desktop Accessibility Guide V2.2.0
</revnumber> 
<date>2003年2月</date> 
<revdescription> 
<para role="author">
Sun Microsystems
</para> 
<para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para> 
</revdescription> 
</revision>

<revision> 
<revnumber>
GNOME 2.0 Desktop for the Solaris Operating Environment 
Accessibility Guide V2.1
</revnumber> 
<date>2003年1月</date> 
<revdescription> 
<para role="author">Sun Microsystems</para> 
<para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para> 
</revdescription> 
</revision>

<revision> 
<revnumber>
GNOME 2.0 Desktop for the Solaris Operating Environment 
Accessibility Guide V2.0
</revnumber> 
<date>2002年12月</date> 
<revdescription> 
<para role="author">
Sun Microsystems
</para> 
<para role="publisher">GNOME Documentation Project</para> 
</revdescription> 
</revision>  
</revhistory>
 
<releaseinfo> 
This manual describes version 2.24 of the GNOME Desktop.
</releaseinfo>
 
<legalnotice> 
<title>フィードバック</title> 
<para>Ubuntuドキュメントに関して提案や不具合を報告するには、<ulink url="https://bugs.launchpad.net/ubuntu-doc/+bugs">バグ追跡システムを</ulink>を確認してください。</para>
</legalnotice> 
</bookinfo>

<chapter id="accessintro-1">

<title>ユーザ補助の紹介</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>セクション508</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>この章ではGNOMEデスクトップのアクセシビリティについて紹介します。</para>
<para>すべてのソフトウェアは、障害を持つ人々が簡単かつ効果的にソフトウェアを利用するためアクセシビリティ機能を組み込むべきでしょう。近代のアメリカ合衆国リハビリテーション条例であるセクション508のような法律が、利用しやすいソフトウェアを提供する必要性の意識を高めています。</para>
<para>
The GNOME Desktop is easy to use and incorporates many accessibility features. Every supported application and utility in the GNOME Desktop is designed with accessibility and usability in mind. Users with physical disabilities such as low vision or impaired motor skills can use all of the functionality of the GNOME Desktop thanks to the customization tools that are available. These customization tools enable you to fine-tune the appearance and behavior of the desktop.
</para>
<para>
The ability to easily customize the GNOME Desktop contributes greatly to the accessibility of the desktop. This guide describes the various options available to
meet your particular needs.
</para>

<section id="quickref">
<title>Quick Reference</title>
<para>
To jump to a specific topic, follow these quick reference links:
</para>
<para>
To hear screen elements spoken to you, see the <link linkend="enable-orca">Orca</link> section.
</para>
<para>
If you need large print, read about <link linkend="themes-4">Choosing Themes</link> and <link linkend="themes-10">Customizing Fonts</link>.
</para>
<para>
To have some or all of the screen magnified, see the <link linkend="ats-2">Magnifier</link> section.
</para>
<para>
If you prefer a pointing device over the keyboard, you can configure an on-screen keyboard for point-and-click typing; see the <link linkend="gok">GNOME Onscreen Keyboard (gok)</link> section.
</para>
<para>
If you can only press one key at a time, see the Sticky Keys portion of the <link linkend="dtconfig-14">Configuring an Accessible Keyboard</link> section.
</para>
<para>
If you tend to press keys for too long a time (normally causing inadvertant extra keys), see the Slow Keys portion of the <link linkend="dtconfig-14">Configuring an Accessible Keyboard</link> section.
</para>
<para>
If you tend to press keys multiple times (normally causing inadvertant extra keys), see the Bounce Keys portion of the <link linkend="dtconfig-14">Configuring an Accessible Keyboard</link> section.
</para>
<para>
For further mouse- or pointer-based accessibility support, see the <link linkend="mousetweaks">MouseTweaks</link> and <link linkend="dtconfig-14">Configuring an Accessible Keyboard</link> sections. These tools supply several accessibility aids for pointer devices and keyboards.
</para>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter id="general">
<title>一般的なアクセシビリティTips</title>
<para>多くの技術が異なる種類の障害を持つ人々の役に立つことができます。これらの内容がこの章にて補われています。具体的には:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>
Essential Keyboard Commands
</emphasis>
 - covers some basic keyboard commands.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>
Keyboard Desktop Navigation
</emphasis>
 - allows users to navigate the desktop without using a mouse or pointer device.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>
Accessible Login
</emphasis>
 - users can configure the login screen to be more accessible. 
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<section>
<title>Essential Keyboard Commands</title>
<para>
Before moving forward, be sure you are familiar with these essential GNOME commands:
</para>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F1</keycap></keycombo> [Debian] - display and activate the GNOME Desktop menu bar. This grants access to the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu>, <guimenu>Places</guimenu> and <guimenu>System</guimenu> menu bar items.
</para>
<note>
<para>
For Solaris and Windows systems, this key is <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Esc</keycap></keycombo>.
</para>
</note>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo> or <keycombo><keycap>Meta</keycap><keycap>R</keycap></keycombo> - summons the <application>Run</application> dialog, where you can issue terminal commands with or without parameters. If a file needs to be passed as one of these parameters, use the <guilabel>Run With File</guilabel> button to easily locate the file needed. This dialog also presents an alternate list of known applications which may be easier to navigate than the Debian system desktop menu (<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F1</keycap></keycombo>) approach.
</para>
<note>
<para>
For Solaris systems, this key is <keycombo><keycap>Meta</keycap><keycap>R</keycap></keycombo> (as with Microsoft Windows). A meta- or super-key is an OS-logo shift key.
</para>
</note>
<para>
<keycap>Tab</keycap> and <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo> - move focus within an application between controls; use <keycap>Tab</keycap> to cycle forward through controls and <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo> to cycle backwards. Controls are any user-interactive element that you can manipulate, such as buttons, drop-down lists, text fields, etc. <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo> and <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo> are used instead where <keycap>Tab</keycap> and <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo> are reserved for use by the focused control.
</para>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo> and <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo> - switches between currently running applications. If you have multiple programs running, use <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo> to cycle forward through the applications and <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo> to cycle backwards. <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Esc</keycap></keycombo> and <keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Esc</keycap></keycombo> also cycle between applications, but without an application preview window.
</para>
</section>

<section id="sysadmin-27">
<title>アクセシビリティログイン</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>アクセシビリティログイン機能</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The GNOME Desktop includes an Accessible Login feature, enabling users to:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>いつものようにスクリーンやマウスやキーボードを簡単に使えなくてもデスクトップにログインする事ができます。</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Launch assistive technologies at login time by
associating a user action with an assistive technology application. The user can perform the user action from the standard keyboard, or from a keyboard, pointing device, or switch device that is attached to the USB or
PS/2 mouse port. These user actions are called <emphasis>gestures</emphasis>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Change the visual appearance of the login dialog before the user logs in; for example, using a high-contrast theme for better visibility.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<note>
<para>
Accessible login features are presently 100% functioning for Solaris only.
</para>
</note>

<section id="sysadmin-34">
<title>Enabling Accessible Login</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>GDM</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
In order to use the accessibility support for GNOME, the accessibility infrastructure must be enabled. To enable GNOME accessibility features from the command line, type the following command and then log out:
</para>
<para>
<userinput>gconftool-2 --set "/desktop/gnome/interface/accessibility" --type boolean "True"</userinput>
</para>
<para>
To enable GNOME accessibility features from a GUI, run the <menuchoice>
<guimenuitem>System</guimenuitem>
<guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
<guimenuitem>Assistive Technology</guimenuitem>
</menuchoice> command from the top level menu.  Select the <guilabel>"Enable assistive technologies"</guilabel> checkbox and then press the <guilabel>"Close and Log Out"</guilabel> button.
</para>
<para>
The next time you log in, assistive technology support will be enabled for the desktop.
</para>
<para>
To configure GDM by using the GUI (the preferred method), perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para><literal>root</literal>ユーザでログインしてください。</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Run <application>gdmsetup</application> from a terminal; you may be advised to reboot after exiting the application.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
To configure GDM if you cannot access the GUI environment, you will need to navigate the file system and modify files:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para><literal>root</literal>ユーザでログインしてください。</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Open the file <filename>/etc/X11/gdm/custom.conf</filename>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>以下の行を検索してください:</para>
<para>
<literal>#AddGtkModules=false</literal>
</para>
<para>そして、その行を以下に置き換えてください:</para>
<para>
<literal>AddGtkModules=true</literal>
</para>
<para>この方法はGtkModulesを有効化します。</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>以下の行を検索してください:</para>
<para>
<literal>#GtkModulesList=gail:atk-bridge:dwellmouselistener:keymouselistener</literal>
</para>
<para>そして、その行を読めるように、先頭から<literal>#</literal>を削除してください:</para>
<para>
<literal>GtkModulesList=gail:atk-bridge:dwellmouselistener:keymouselistener</literal>
</para>
<note>
<para>
The above lines must be displayed as single lines in the <filename>custom.conf</filename> file without line breaks. The formatting of this guide may display the lines as being longer than two lines.
</para>
</note>
<para>
This step loads all of the GtkModules to enable assistive technologies such as 
<application>On-Screen Keyboard</application>
and <application>Screen Reader and Magnifier
</application>. You can edit the line above further to load only the GtkModules that you require to support the user base. For example: 
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
If you need to use the <application>
Screen Reader and Magnifier</application>, include <literal>gail</literal> and <literal>atk-bridge</literal>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
If you need to use a pointing device without buttons or switches, include <literal>gail</literal>, <literal>atk-bridge</literal> and 
<literal>dwellmouselistener</literal>. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>もし、ポインティング・デバイスのスイッチを使い、物理キーボードの代替またはスイッチやボタン・デバイスの代替とするなら、<literal>keymouselistener</literal>を含めてください。</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<application>On-Screen Keyboard</application> can operate without <literal>gail</literal> and <literal>atk-bridge</literal>, but with a reduced feature set. 
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>最適なアクセシビリティのために、<literal>gail</literal>と<literal>atk-bridge</literal>を含めます。</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Save the <filename>/etc/X11/gdm/custom.conf</filename> file.
</para>
<note>
<para>
If you make any changes to the 
<filename>/etc/X11/gdm/custom.conf</filename> file after you enable GDM, you can execute the following command to restart GDM and activate the changes:
</para>
<para>
<command>gdm-restart</command>
</para>
</note>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><filename>/etc/group</filename>を編集し、以下を<literal>audio</literal>行に追加します:</para>
<para>
<literal>,gdm</literal>
</para>
<para>このステップでスピーチがGDMにて確実に動作します。</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>システムを再起動してください。</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
<application>Xserver</application> is required for all distributions; for Linux and OpenSolaris, it should be <application>Xorg</application>. You can find them in both <filename>/etc/X11</filename> and <filename>/usr/bin</filename>. Generally for Linux there will be a symbol link in <filename>/etc/X11/X</filename> and it is always linked to the binary <filename>Xorg</filename> in <filename>/usr/bin/Xorg</filename>. For OpenSolaris, you can find this process with the command <userinput>ps -ef | grep X</userinput>.
</para>
<para>
To enable or disable <application>Xorg</application> extensions, you can edit the file
<filename>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</filename> and add the following parameters to enable different
extensions:
</para>
<programlisting>
<computeroutput>
Section "Extensions"
  Option "Composite"         "Enable"
  Option "other extensions"  "Enable/Disable"
EndSection
</computeroutput>
</programlisting>
</section>

<section id="sysadmin-29">
<title>Starting Assistive Technologies at Login</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>ジェスチャー</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
If you load the <literal>keymouselistener</literal> and <literal>dwellmouselistener</literal> GtkModules in the GDM configuration file, you can assign user actions to launch specific assistive technologies at login time. These user actions are called gestures. The gesture associations are contained in the following GDM configuration files: 
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>/etc/X11/gdm/modules/AccessKeyMouseEvents</filename>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<filename>/etc/X11/gdm/modules/AccessDwellMouseEvents</filename>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<note>
<para>これらファイルを修正したなら、変更を有効にする前にシステムを再起動しなければいけません。</para>
</note>
<para>以下の章はGDM設定ファイルに追加することができるジェスチャーの例が含まれています。</para>
<note>
<para>
The gestures must be contained in a single line in the <filename>AccessKeyMouseEvents
</filename> file without line breaks. The formatting of this guide might display the examples in the following sections across multiple lines. 
</para>
</note>

<section id="sysadmin-30">
<title>Starting the Screen Reader Using a Keyboard Shortcut</title>
<para>
Edit the <filename>AccessKeyMouseEvents</filename> file to associate keyboard shortcuts with assistive technologies. For example, the following lines enable you to press and hold <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>S</keycap></keycombo> or <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>M</keycap></keycombo> for one second to either start speech or magnification:
</para>
<para>
<literal>
&lt;Control&gt;s 1 1000 10000 /usr/bin/orca -n -d main-window
</literal>
</para>
<para>
<literal>
&lt;Control&gt;m 1 1000 10000 /usr/bin/orca -n -d main-window -e magnifier
</literal>
</para>
</section>

<section id="sysadmin-31">
<title>Starting On-Screen Keyboard Using a Switch or Button Gesture</title>
<para><filename>AccessKeyMouseEvents</filename>ファイルに支援技術のスイッチやキー、またはボタン・ジェスチャーを関連付けて編集してください。多くの<application>オンスクリーン・キーボード</application>ユーザのための主な入力デバイスはスイッチか、ボタンであるため、ログイン時に<application>オンスクリーン・キーボード</application>を始めるための早道です。</para>
<para>
If there is a tendency for a user to start an 
application unintentionally, you can associate the gestures with multiple switch presses or minimum durations. For example, the following line starts <application>On-Screen Keyboard</application> in inverse scanning mode when the user presses the 
switch that is defined as Switch 2 three times within two seconds, for a minimum of 100 milliseconds for each press:
</para>
<para>
<literal>&lt;Switch2&gt;3 100 2000 gok --login --accessmethod=inversescanning --scan-action=switch1 --select-action=switch2</literal>
</para>
<para>
Users who use single switches may prefer to start <application>On-Screen Keyboard</application> in automatic scanning mode. The following line starts <application>On-Screen Keyboard</application> in automatic scanning mode when the user presses the switch on an alternative access device for more than four seconds:
</para>
<para>
<literal>&lt;Switch&gt;1 4000 5000 gok --login --accessmethod=automaticscanning --scan-action=switch1 --select-action=switch1</literal>
</para>
<para>
For information about the <application>On-Screen Keyboard</application> operating modes, see the online help for <application>On-Screen Keyboard</application>.
</para>
</section>

<section id="sysadmin-32">
<title>Starting On-Screen Keyboard Using a Motion-Only Gesture</title>
<para>マウスのようなポインティング・デバイスやヘッドポインターやトラックボールのような代替ポインティング・デバイスの動きだけを伴うジェスチャーを定義することができます。ジェスチャーの構文はマウスや代替ポインティング・デバイスの利用かどうかに依存して変化することはありません。支援技術のモーション・ジェスチャーを関連付ける<filename>AccessKeyMouseEvents</filename>ファイルを編集してください。</para>
<para>
If the <literal>dwellmouselistener</literal> GtkModule is loaded, alternative pointing devices are temporarily latched to the core pointer. This means that if the user moves the alternative pointing device, the on-screen pointer moves.
</para>
<para>
For example, the following line starts 
<application>On-Screen Keyboard</application> in dwell mode when the user moves the on-screen pointer from inside the login dialog through the top edge, back into the dialog through the top edge, out of the dialog through the left edge, back into the dialog through the left edge, and similarly through the bottom and right edges of the dialog in a cross pattern:
</para>
<para>
<literal>TTLLBBRR O 10000 gok --login --access-method=dwellselection --input-device=MOUSE[3]</literal>
</para>
<para><filename>/etc/X11/XF86Config</filename>内に定義される<literal>--input-device</literal>パラメータは、ヘッドポインタやトラックボールなどの拡張ユーザ入力デバイスの名称と合致しなければならないジェスチャーとして規定されていることに注意してください。</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="sysadmin-33">
<title>アクセス可能なログインへの追加要件</title>
<para>
To enable the Accessible Login feature to use 
alternative pointing devices and switch devices such as sip-and-puff switches, wheelchair-mounted switches or trackballs, you might need to modify your X server system configuration to recognize these devices. You can use most devices that emulate mouse buttons with the Accessible Login feature and <application>On-Screen Keyboard</application>, including USB single switches and mouse-like pointing devices.
</para>
<note>
<para>
You should not configure an alternative input device to control the primary on-screen pointer. This might result in undesirable behavior or cause situations from which 
the user of the alternate input device cannot recover without using the primary keyboard or mouse. To prevent this problem, remove any occurrences of the attributes 
<literal>SendCore</literal> or <literal>AlwaysCore</literal> from any of the 
<literal>InputDevice</literal> lines in the X Server configuration file.
</para>
</note>
</section>
</section>

<section id="keynav-0">
<title>キーボード・デスクトップ・ナビゲーション</title>
<para>この章は、キーボードだけでGNOME Desktopをどのようにして操作するかを記載しています。マウスや他のポインティング・デバイスを使うことが困難なユーザは、キーボードからデスクトップを利用し、操作することができます。</para>

<section id="keynav-1">
<title>キーボード・ナビゲーションの紹介</title>
<para>この章は、キーボードからデスクトップ操作を有効にするキーボード・ショートカットの要点を記載しています。</para>
<para>この章に書かれたキーボード・ショートカットのいくつかはカスタマイズができます。次のテキストはカスタマイズができるショートカットを示しています。キーボード・ショートカットをのカスタマイズ方法についての情報は<xref linkend="keynav-36"/>を見てください。</para>

<section id="keynav-2">
<title>キーボード・ショートカットの要点</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>要点</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>キャレット・ナビゲーション・モード</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>以下の表はデスクトップを操作するために使うことができるキーボード・ショートカットの要点を並べています。特定の要素や制御の操作で利用できるキーボード・ショートカットがこの章の適した項に記載されています。</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Tab</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>次の要素や制御にフォーカスを与えます</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>操作方向を逆転し、前の要素または制御にフォーカスを与えます。通常、<keycap>Shift</keycap>キー操作方向を逆転します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Give focus to the next element or control if the <keycap>Tab</keycap> key has a specific purpose in a control. For example, if you press <keycap>Tab</keycap> in a text box, the system inserts a tab space.
</para>
<para>前の要素や制御にフォーカスを与えるなら、<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo>を押してください。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>要素や制御内で操作します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>フォーカスを持った要素や制御を有効化します。例えば、現在の制御がボタンなら、この動作はマウスでボタンをクリックすることと同様です。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Esc</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>ウインドウやメニューや引き出しを閉じます</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para>
<keycap>F7</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>キャレット・ナビゲーションモードに切り替えます。キャレットナビゲーションモードはキーボードを使ってテキストを選択することを可能にします。キャレットナビゲーションモードに関する多く情報は、<xref linkend="keynav-52"/>を見てください。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-3">
<title>グローバル・キーボード・ショートカット</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>グローバル</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>以下の表は、GNOME Desktopの一部のいくつかから使うことができるキーボード・ショートカットを並べています</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F1</keycap>
</keycombo>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para><guimenu>メイン・アプリケーション・メニュー</guimenu>を開きます。</para>
<para>このキーボード・ショートカットをカスタマイズできます</para>
<note>
<para>
For Solaris systems, this key is <keycap>Ctrl-Esc</keycap> (as with Microsoft Windows).
</para>
</note>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap>
</keycombo>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Open the <guilabel>Run Application</guilabel> dialog.
</para>
<para>このキーボード・ショートカットをカスタマイズできます</para>
<note>
<para>
For Solaris systems, this key is <keycap>Meta-R</keycap> (as with Microsoft Windows). A meta- or super-key is an OS-logo shift key.
</para>
</note>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Print Screen</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>スクリーンショットアプリケーションを開始し、全画面のスクリーンショットを写します。</para>
<para>このキーボード・ショートカットをカスタマイズできます</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Print Screen</keycap></keycombo>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>スクリーンショットアプリケーションを開始し、現在フォーカスが当たっているウィンドウのスクリーンショットを写します。</para>
<para>このキーボード・ショートカットをカスタマイズできます</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>F1</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>もし、フォーカスが当たっている要素がアプリケーションのウィンドウかダイアログなら、このキーボード・ショートカットはアプリケーションのヘルプを開きます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F1</keycap>
</keycombo>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>もし、フォーカスが当たっている要素がパネルかアプリケーションのウィンドウなら、このキーボード・ショートカットはウィンドウまたはパネルオブジェクトのツールチップのON・OFF表示を切り替えます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Open a popup menu for the element that has focus (if a popup menu exists for that element).
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>
</section>

<section id="keynav-4">
<title>デスクトップ背景の操作</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>デスクトップ背景のため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>デスクトップ背景は、パネルやウインドウのような、アイテムやアプリケーションのインタフェースが無いGNOME Desktopの一部です。以下の表はデスクトップ背景やデスクトップ背景のオブジェクトを操作するために利用することができるキーボード・ショートカットの一覧です。デスクトップ背景のオブジェクトとは、ファイルやアプリケーションを開くために利用することができるデスクトップ背景上のアイコンです。</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>D</keycap></keycombo>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>すべてのウィンドウを一時的に隠し、デスクトップ背景にフォーカスを与えます。</para>
<para>ウィンドウを元に戻すため、<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>D</keycap></keycombo>を再度押してください。</para>
<para>このキーボード・ショートカットをカスタマイズできます</para>
<note>
<para>
For Solaris systems, this key is <keycap>Meta-D</keycap> (as with Microsoft Windows). A meta- or super-key is an OS-logo shift key.
</para>
</note>

</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Display a popup window with icons that represent the desktop background and the panels. Press and hold <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo> and continue to press <keycap>Tab</keycap> to switch the focus between the desktop background and the panels. 
</para>
<para>このキーボード・ショートカットをカスタマイズできます</para>
</entry>
</row>
<!--<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Tab</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
When the desktop background or a desktop background 
object has focus, give focus to the next desktop 
background object in alphabetical order.
</para>
</entry>
</row>-->
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Give focus to a neighboring desktop background object (if the desktop has focus).
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
A sequence of characters that matches the first <replaceable>n</replaceable> 
characters of a desktop background object name.
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
If the desktop background has focus, give focus to the desktop background object whose name starts with the specified sequence of characters.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>F2</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>フォーカスを持っているデスクトップ背景のオブジェクトの名前を変えます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>フォーカスを持っているデスクトップ背景のオブジェクトのポップアップメニューを開きます</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para><guimenu>デスクトップ背景</guimenu>メニューを開きます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-5">
<title>パネルの操作</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>パネルのために</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>パネルは特別なプログラムやアプリケーション、パネルアプリケーションを実行することができるエリアです。多くの一般的なパネルは、デスクトップの下端の全幅を伸ばすパネルです。</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Give focus to a panel. This keyboard shortcut displays a popup window with icons that represent the desktop background, panels, and drawers. Press and hold 
<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo> and continue to press <keycap>Tab</keycap> to switch the focus between the desktop background, panels, and drawers. If you're especially dexterous, you can add <keycap>Shift</keycap> to go in reverse.
</para>
<para>このキーボード・ショートカットをカスタマイズできます</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Tab</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>パネル上の次のオブジェクトにフォーカスを与えます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>F10</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Open the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu when the Menu Panel has focus. Continue to press <keycap>F10</keycap> to switch focus between the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> menu and the window list. This key behavior may alter slightly depending on context and specific user setup.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Activate a panel object; for example, open a menu or start a launcher (icon shortcut).
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>パネルオブジェクトのポップアップメニューを開きます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>パネルのポップアップメニューを開きます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>

<section id="keynav-6">
<title>Moving Panel Objects</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>パネルオブジェクトを移動するには</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>フォーカスが当たっているパネルオブジェクトを異なる位置にあるパネルやドロワーに移動する事ができ、次のパネルにオブジェクトを移動する事ができます。パネルオブジェクトを移動するには、以下の方法を実施します:</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>オブジェクトにフォーカスを与えるため、<keycap>Tab</keycap>を押してください。</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>パネルオブジェクトのポップアップメニューを開くため、<keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo>押してください。</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the arrow keys to select the <guimenuitem>
Move</guimenuitem> menu item.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the keyboard shortcuts that are listed in the following table to perform the move operation:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Move the object left/right on a horizontal panel, or up/down on a vertical panel.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycap>Shift</keycap> + 矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Move the object with focus, swapping positions with any other objects encountered.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap> + 矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Move the object, swapping positions with any other objects that you encounter in the move.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Tab</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>次のパネルにオブジェクトを移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>移動操作を完了します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
The following examples demonstrate the effect of different move operations on the objects in a panel:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="50*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="50*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>イラスト</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>説明</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/move_object_before.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
Portion of a panel with three objects  displayed in the following order from left to right: <application>Geyes</application> icon, <application>Volume Control</application> icon, and <application>Help</application> icon.
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Show a panel with three panel objects before a move operation takes place.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/move_object_arrows.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
Portion of a panel with three objects displayed in the following order from left to right: <application>Geyes</application> icon, <application>Volume Control</application> icon, and <application>Help</application> icon. 
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Shows the effect of using the arrow keys to move the <application>Geyes</application> panel application on the panel. You can use the arrow keys to move the panel application left or right until you meet the next panel 
object.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/move_object_push.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
Portion of a panel with three objects displayed in the following order from left to right: <application>Geyes</application> icon, <application>Volume Control</application> icon, and <application>Help</application> icon.
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Shows the effect of using <keycap>Shift</keycap> + arrow keys to move the <application>Geyes</application> panel application on the panel. You can use the 
<keycap>Shift</keycap> + arrow keys to push the <application>Volume Control</application>
and <application>Help</application> panel objects ahead of the object that you are moving.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/move_object_jump.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
Portion of a panel with three objects displayed in the following order from left to right: <application>Volume Control</application> icon, <application>Help</application> icon, and <application>Geyes</application> icon.
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Shows the effect of using <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> + arrow keys to move the <application>Geyes</application> panel 
application on the panel. You can use the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> + arrow keys to swap positions with the <application>Volume Control</application> and <application>Help</application> panel objects as you meet the objects.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<note>
<para>
Panel applications that are <guilabel>Locked</guilabel> cannot be moved. To unlock a panel application, use the <guimenu>panel object</guimenu> menu and deselect the <guimenuitem>Lock to Panel</guimenuitem> option.
</para>
</note>
</section>

<section id="keynav-7">
<title>Navigating Drawers</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>ドロワーのために</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>ドロワーは、パネルの折り畳むことができる拡張です。以下の表の一覧はドロワーの中や外で操作することができるキーボード・ショートカットです。ドロワーを開いたとき、パネルを操作するいくつかの方法でドロワーの中身を操作できます。パネルの操作方法の情報は<xref linkend="keynav-5"/>を見てください。</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>フォーカスが当たっているドロワーを開いたり閉じたりします</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>フォーカスが当たっているドロワーの中を操作します</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Esc</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>パネル上のドロワーオブジェクトへフォーカスを与えたり、ドロワーを閉じたりします</para>
</entry>
</row>
<!--<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Esc
</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Gives focus to the drawer object on the panel and leaves 
the drawer open.
</para>
</entry>
</row>-->
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-8">
<title>Navigating Panel Menus</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>パネル上のメニューのため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate menus on panels:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>フォーカスが当たっているメニューを開きます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>メニューを操作します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>メニューアイテムを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Open the popup menu associated with a menu item (if one exists).
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Esc</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>メニューを閉じます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-9">
<title>Navigating Panel Applications</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>パネルアプリケーションをのため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>パネルアプリケーションはパネルに備わっている小さなアプリケーションです。すべてのパネルアプリケーションをそうさしたり、キーボードからパネルアプリケーションのポップアップメニューを開くことができます。しかし、パネルアプリケーションがフォーカスを与えることができる操作に含まれない場合、パネルアプリケーションの操作を行うことはできません。以下の表はパネルアプリケーションを操作するために使うことができるキーボード・ショートカットの一覧です。</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>適切であれば、フォーカスを持つパネルアプリケーション操作をアクティブにすることができます。すべてのパネルアプリケーションがアクティブできる操作を持っていません。パネルアプリケーションがアクティブすることができる操作を含んでいないなら、<keycap>スペースキー</keycap>は何もしません。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>パネルアプリケーション上の制御を操作</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>パネルアプリケーションのポップアップメニューを開いてください。メニューを操作するには、メニューを操作するため一般的なキーボード・ショートカットを使ってください。メニューの操作方法についての情報は<xref linkend="keynav-24"/>を見てください。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>
</section>

<section id="keynav-10">
<title>Navigating Workspaces</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>ワークスペースのため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
A workspace is a discrete area in which you
can work. You can have many workspaces on your desktop and you can switch from one workspace to another. Each workspace can 
contain different windows and processes. The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate workspaces:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo> + 矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>次または前のワークスペースにフォーカスを与えます。このキーボード・ショートカットはワークスペースを表すアイコンを伴うポップアップウィンドウを表示します。<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo>を押したまま矢印キーを押すと、互いのワークスペースにフォーカスを切り替えます。</para>
<para>このキーボード・ショートカットをカスタマイズできます</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap></keycombo> + 矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>前後のワークスペースにフォーカスを持っているウィンドウを移動します。</para>
<para>このキーボード・ショートカットをカスタマイズできます</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-11">
<title>ウィンドウの操作</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>ウィンドウのために</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>以下の項はウィンドウ操作するために利用することができるキーボード・ショートカットを記述しています。ウィンドウはアプリケーションを表示したスクリーン上の長方形のフレームです。</para>
<note>
<para>ウィンドウ操作に関連したキーボード・ショートカットのすべてはカスタマイズすることができます。これ以上の情報は<xref linkend="keynav-10"/>を見てください。</para>
</note>

<section id="keynav-12">
<title>Giving Focus to Windows</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>ウィンドウにフォーカスを与えるには</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
Before you can use or modify a window, you must give focus to the window. The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to give focus to a window:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Display a popup window with icons that represent each window. Press and hold <keycap>Alt</keycap> and continue to press <keycap>Tab</keycap> to move through the windows until you reach the window you want to have focus.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Esc</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Raise each window in turn until you reach the window you want.
</para>
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F6</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Cycle between windows belonging to the current application (eg, a multiple document interface application like <application>Text Editor</application>).
</para>
</entry>
</row>


</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-13">
<title>Controlling Windows</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>ウィンドウをコントロールするには</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
When a window has focus, you can perform various actions on the window. The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts that
you can use to control the window that has focus:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>スペースバー</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Open the <guimenu>Window</guimenu> menu.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F4</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>ウィンドウを閉じます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<emphasis>Solaris:</emphasis>
<keycap>Open</keycap>
</para>
<para><emphasis>Linux:</emphasis><keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F9</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>ウィンドウを最小化します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>ウィンドウを最大化します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F5</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Restore a maximized window to its original size.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-14">
<title>Moving Windows</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>ウィンドウを移動するには</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
When a window has focus, you can move the window around the screen. The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to move a window:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F7</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>移動操作を始めます。マウスポインターは十字に変わります。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>矢印キーの向きにウィンドウを10ピクセル移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap> + 矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>矢印キーの向きにウィンドウを1ピクセル移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycap>Shift</keycap> + 矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Move the window in the direction of the arrow key and align it with the edge of the nearest window, panel or screen edge.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Complete the move operation, leaving the window in the current position.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Esc</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Cancel the move operation, restoring the window to its original position.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-15">
<title>Resizing Windows</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>ウィンドウのサイズを変更するには</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
When a window has focus, you can increase or
decrease the size of the window. The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts
that you can use to resize the window that has focus:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>F8</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>サイズ変更の操作を始めます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Resize the window in the direction of the arrow key.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Complete the resize operation, leaving the window at the current size.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Esc</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Cancel the resize operation, restoring the window to its original size.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-16">
<title>Navigating Paned Windows</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>ウィンドウ・ペインのため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
A paned window is a window that is split into
two or more panes. <application>Help Browser</application> is an example of an application that uses paned windows. 
</para>
<para>
The following table describes the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate paned/split windows:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>F6</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>次の枠にフォーカスを与えます。システムは最後に枠内にフォーカスを持ったコントロールにフォーカスを与えます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>F8</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>ウィンドウのリサイズ・ハンドルの最初にフォーカスを与えます。リサイズ・ハンドルは枠とサイズ変更が可能な枠の間に表示されます。<keycap>F8</keycap>を押して、次のリサイズ・ハンドルに再度フォーカスを与えてください。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<para>
When the resize handle has focus, you can use the keyboard shortcuts that are listed in the following table to modify the paned window:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>少量のリサイズ・ハンドルを移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap> + 矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>大量のリサイズ・ハンドルを移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Home</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Contract the pane to the minimum size allowed. 
</para>
<para>
For vertical panes, reduces the size of the pane to the left of the resize handle to the minimum size allowed.  
</para>
<para>
For horizontal panes, reduces the size of the pane above the resize handle to the minimum size allowed.  
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>End</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Expand the pane to the maximum size allowed. 
</para>
<para>
For vertical panes, increases the size of the pane to the left of the resize handle to the maximum size allowed.  
</para>
<para>
For horizontal panes, increases the size of the pane above the resize handle to the maximum size allowed.  
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Set the position of the resize handle and return focus to the last control that had focus.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Esc</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Reset the position of the resize handle to the original position and return focus to the last control that had focus.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>
</section>

<section id="keynav-17">
<title>アプリケーションの操作</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>アプリケーションのため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
An application is any program, utility, or other software package that you run on your desktop. Applications contain standard user interface components:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>ウィンドウ</term>
<listitem>
<para>ウインドウはアプリケーションを表示するスクリーン上にある長方形のフレームです。ウインドウを操作歩応報についての情報は<xref linkend="keynav-11"/>を見てください。</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>ダイアログ</term>
<listitem>
<para>
A dialog is a popup window which displays 
information or accepts input from the user. See <xref linkend="keynav-19"/> for information about how to navigate dialogs.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>コントロール要素</term>
<listitem>
<para>
A control is any user-interactive screen element. Examples of controls include buttons, check boxes, menus, and text boxes. See <xref linkend="keynav-23"/> for detailed information about how to navigate the different types of controls that are available.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>
This section of the manual describes the essential keyboard shortcuts that you can use in applications and dialogs. 
</para>

<section id="keynav-18">
<title>アプリケーション操作のためのキーボード・ショートカットの要素</title>
<anchor id="keynav-22"/>
<para>
Since there are so many applications that you can use in the GNOME Desktop, this manual does not describe all the custom keyboard shortcuts that you can use with each individual application. However, the basic keyboard shortcuts are common to many applications.
</para>
<para>
Access keys are another way to quickly navigate applications with the keyboard. An access key is identified by an underlined letter on a menu or control. In some cases, you must press <keycap>Alt</keycap> in combination with the access key to perform an action.
</para>
<para>
The following table lists the essential keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate applications:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>F10</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>アプリケーションのメニューバー上にある最初のメニューを開きます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycap>Alt</keycap> + アクセスキー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>アクセスキーに関連付けられたメニューを開きます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>アクセスキー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>アクセスキーに関連付けられたメニューアイテムを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycap>左矢印キー</keycap>と<keycap>右矢印キー</keycap></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>メニューバー上のメニュー間のフォーカスを切り替えます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycap>上矢印キー</keycap>と<keycap>下矢印キー</keycap></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>メニュー内でフォーカスを移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Esc</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Close the open menu and give focus to the control that had focus before the menubar.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>O</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>ファイル選択ダイアログを開きます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>S</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>保存ダイアログを開きます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>L</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>
Open a Location dialog, enabling you to type
the name of a file that you want to open or save.
</para>
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>P</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>
Open a Print dialog, if available.
</para>
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>C</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>
Copy highlighted text to the global, application-spanning clipboard.
</para>
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>X</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>
Cut highlighted text to the global, application-spanning clipboard.
</para>
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>V</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>
Paste text from the global, application-spanning clipboard to the current cursor position.
</para>
</entry>
</row>

</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-19">
<title>ダイアログ操作のためのキーボード・ショートカット要素</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>ダイアログのため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The following table lists the essential keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate dialogs:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>アクセスキー</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>コントロール要素の選択または有効化</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Tab</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>次のコントロール要素にフォーカスを与えます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Page Up</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Move to the next page/tabbed section of the dialog.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Page Down</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Move to the previous page/tabbed section of the dialog.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Esc</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Cancel/dismiss the dialog. Some application-specific dialogs may retain dialog settings, but this practice is discouraged. These dialogs usually have a single <guilabel>Close</guilabel> button, with no <guilabel>Ok/Accept</guilabel> buttons.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Return</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Perform the default action for the dialog. The default action will usually apply any changes and close the dialog. A default button will have a bold outline and a selected button will have a slightly bolder outline than the default button.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>
</section>

<section id="keynav-20">
<title>ファイルマネージャの操作</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>ファイルマネージャのため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
By default, the file manager operates in 
<guilabel>Spatial</guilabel> mode. This mode uses separate windows for each folder. Conversely, <guilabel>Browser</guilabel> mode will reuse the same window for each folder.
</para>
<note>
<para>
For more information about different modes for the file manager, see <ulink url="ghelp:user-guide?nautilus-presentation">
the user guide</ulink>.
</para>
</note>

<section id="keynav-spatial">
<title>Navigating Folders</title>
<para>
The following table describes the keyboard shortcuts that enable you to navigate folders in the file manager:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>矢印キーの向きにある前後のファイルやフォルダを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap> + 矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Give focus to the next or previous file or folder but do not select the item. This allows multiple, non-contiguous blocks of files to be selected.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>フォーカスが当たっているファイルやフォルダを開きます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap> + <keycap>スペースバー</keycap></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>フォーカスをもつ現在のアイテムを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>ファイル名の最初の<replaceable>n</replaceable>文字目にマッチする一連の文字</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>特定した一連の文字で開始するファイルやフォルダを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Home</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>現在のフォルダ内の最初のファイルやフォルダを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>End</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>現在のフォルダ内の最後のファイルやフォルダを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Backspace</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>現在のフォルダの親フォルダを開きます。</para>
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Shift-F10</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Open a file or folder popup menu.
</para>
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Ctrl-F10</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Open the enclosing folder's popup menu (equivalent to right-clicking on the view pane background).
</para>
</entry>
</row>

</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-navigational">
<title>Navigating Browser Window Components</title>
<anchor id="keynav-21"/>
<para>
When operating in <guilabel>Browser</guilabel> mode, the file manager window 
contains several components, with keyboard shortcuts defined to navigate each component: 
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>F6</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>表示ペインをサイドペイン間のフォーカスを切り替えます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>F10</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>サイドペインのポップアップメニューを開きます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>
</section>

<section id="keynav-52">
<title>Caret Navigation Mode</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キャレット・ナビゲーション・モード</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The following table describes how to use caret navigation mode (eg, in supporting applications like <application>Yelp</application>, <application>Evolution</application>, <application>Epiphany</application>, or <application>Firefox</application>). Caret navigation is a mode of operation in an application which enables you to use the keyboard to navigate and select text.
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para>
<keycap>F7</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>
Switch to caret navigation mode [Yelp-only]. 
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para>左矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>一文字左に移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para>右矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>一文字右に移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para>上矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>一行上に移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para>下矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>一行下に移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap> + 左矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>前の単語の先頭に移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap> + 右矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>次の単語の最後に移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para>
<keycap>Page Up</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>内容を1ページ上にスクロールします。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para>
<keycap>Page Down</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>内容を1ページ下にスクロールします。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para>
<keycap>Home</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>現在行の先頭に移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para>
<keycap>End</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>現在行の最後に移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para><keycap>Shift</keycap> + 矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>
Move from the current position to the destination position, selecting all text between the two positions.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para>
<keycap>Tab</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>次のフォーカスを当てることができるコントロール要素にフォーカスを移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>前のフォーカスを当てることができるコントロール要素にフォーカスを移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para>
<keycap>Enter</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>
Activate a button, link or other control.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-23">
<title>基本的なエレメントやコントロール要素を操作するには</title>
<para>以下の項は、キーボードから基本的なユーザインタフェース・エレメントやコントロール要素を利用または操作する方法を記載しています。</para>

<section id="keynav-24">
<title>Navigating Menus</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>メニューのため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate menus:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para><keycap>上矢印キー</keycap>と<keycap>下矢印キー</keycap></para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>メニュー上にある前後のメニューアイテムにフォーカスを与えます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>右矢印キー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>フォーカスを持っているメニューアイテムがサブメニューである場合、サブメニューを開きサブメニュー上にある最初のメニューアイテムへフォーカスを与えます。</para>
<para>フォーカスを持っているメニューアイテムがサブメニューでない場合、メニューバー上の次のメニューを開きます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>左矢印キー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>フォーカスを持っているメニューアイテムがサブメニューである場合、サブメニューに戻りフォーカスを切り替えます。</para>
<para>フォーカスを持っているメニューアイテムがサブメニューでない場合、メニューバー上の前のメニューを開きます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Return</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>フォーカスが当たっているメニューアイテムを選択し、開いたメニューを閉じます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>アクセスキー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Select the menu item that is associated with the access key and close the menu.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Select the focused menu item and close the menu except when the menu item is a check box or radio button.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Esc</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Close the menu.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-25">
<title>Navigating Buttons</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>ボタンのため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>ボタンは動作を開始するために利用するコントロール要素です。ほとんどのボタンは長方形であり、テキストラベルを持っています。</para>
<figure id="keynav-FIG-39">
<title>ボタンのサンプル</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/button.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>ボタンを閉じます。</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</figure>
<para>
The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate buttons:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>フォーカスを持っているボタンを有効化します。これは、ボタンでクリックすることと同じ意味を持ちます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Return</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>フォーカスを持っているボタンを有効化し、もしボタンがフォーカスを持っていなくても、ダイアログの既定動作とを実行します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>
<section id="keynav-26">

<title>Navigating Radio Buttons</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>ラジオボタンのため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>ラジオボタンはそれぞれの相互排他選択肢の一つを選ぶために利用するコントロール要素です。</para>
<figure id="keynav-FIG-40">
<title>ラジオボタンのサンプル</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/radio_button.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>2つのラジオボタンサンプル</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</figure>
<para>
The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate a set of radio buttons:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>前後のラジオボタンを選択し、グループ内にある他のラジオボタンを選択から外します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-27">
<title>Navigating Check Boxes</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>チェックボックスのために</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>チェックボックスは選択の有無をオプションとするコントロール要素です。</para>
<figure id="keynav-FIG-41">
<title>チェックボックスのサンプル</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/check_box.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>チェックボックスのサンプル</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</figure>
<para>
The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate a check box:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>チェックボックスを選択または選択から外します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-28">
<title>Navigating Text Boxes</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>テキストボックスのために</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>テキストボックスは、テキストを入力するコントロール要素です。</para>
<figure id="keynav-FIG-42">
<title>1行テキストボックスのサンプル</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/text_box.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>1行の入力を持つテキストボックスのサンプル</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</figure>
<para>
The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate a single line text box:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>左矢印キー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>1文字左にカーソルの位置を合わせます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>右矢印キー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>1文字右にカーソルの位置を合わせます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>左矢印キー</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Position the cursor at the start of the current word. Press and hold <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> and continue to press <keycap>left arrow</keycap> to position the cursor at the start of the previous word.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>右矢印キー</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Position the cursor at the end of the current word. Press and hold <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> and continue to press <keycap>right arrow</keycap> to position the cursor at the end of the next word.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Home</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>行頭にカーソルの位置を合わせます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>End</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>行末にカーソルの位置を合わせます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>左矢印キー</keycap></keycombo>または<keycap>右矢印キー</keycap></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>カーソルの左または右の1文字を選択します</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>left arrow
</keycap></keycombo> or <keycap>right arrow
</keycap></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>カーソルの左または右の1単語を選択します</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>Home</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>カーソルから左のテキストをすべて選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>End</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>カーソルから右のテキストをすべて選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>A</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>テキストボックス内のすべてのテキストを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<para>
In addition to the keyboard shortcuts listed in the previous table, use the keyboard shortcuts in the following table to navigate multi-line text boxes:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Page Up</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>カーソルの位置を現在見ている場所の先頭に位置します。以前見ていた場所の上端にカーソルを位置させるには<keycap>Page Up</keycap>を再度押してください。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Page Down</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>カーソルの位置を現在見ている場所の末端に位置します。以前見ていた場所の末端にカーソルを位置させるには<keycap>Page Down</keycap>を再度押してください。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>上矢印キー</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Position the cursor at the start of the current paragraph. Press and hold <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> and continue to press the <keycap>up arrow</keycap> key to position the cursor at the start of the previous 
paragraph.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>下矢印キー</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Position the cursor at the end of the current paragraph. Press and hold <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> and continue to press the <keycap>down arrow</keycap> key to position the cursor at the end of the next 
paragraph.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Page Up</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>カーソルの見えている幅を左に位置付けます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Page Down</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>カーソルの見えている幅を右に位置付けます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Home</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>テキストボックスの最初にカーソルを移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>End</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>テキストボックスの最後にカーソルを移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>ダイアログ上の次のコントロール要素にフォーカスを与えます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>Page Up</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Select the text to the start of the current view. Press and hold <keycap>Shift</keycap> and continue to press <keycap>Page Up</keycap> to extend the selection to the start of the previous view.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>Page Down</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Select the text to the end of the current view. Press and hold <keycap>Shift</keycap> and continue to press <keycap>Page Down</keycap> to extend the selection to the end of the next view.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>Home</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>その行の先頭までテキストを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>End</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>その行の行末までテキストを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>上矢印キー</keycap>
</keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>その段落の先頭からテキストを選択し、前の段落の先頭まで選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>下矢印キー</keycap>
</keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>その段落の終端からテキストを選択し、次の段落の終端まで選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Home</keycap>
</keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>テキストボックスの最初までテキストを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>End</keycap>
</keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>テキストボックスの最後までテキストを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-29">
<title>Navigating Spin Boxes</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>スピンボックスのため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>スピンボックスは数値の入力や可能な値のすべての一覧から値を選択できるコントロール要素です。</para>
<figure id="keynav-FIG-43">
<title>スピンボックスのサンプル</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/spin_box.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>スピンボックスのサンプル。テキストボックスと上下の矢印を含んでいます。</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</figure>
<para>
The keyboard shortcuts that you use to navigate the text box area of a spin box are listed in <xref linkend="keynav-28"/>. The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate the up and down arrows in the spin box:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para><keycap>上矢印キー</keycap>または<keycap>下矢印キー</keycap></para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>少さい単位でスピンボックスの値を増やしたり減らしたりします。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycap>Page Up</keycap>または<keycap>Page Down</keycap></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>大きな単位でスピンボックスの値を増やしたり減らしたりします。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-30">
<title>Navigating Drop-Down Lists</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>ドロップダウンリストのため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>ドロップダウンリストはいくつかの利用可能なアイテムの一つを選択するために利用するコントロール要素です。ドロップダウンリストは利用可能なアイテムを表示するために利用するボタンを含みます。</para>
<figure id="keynav-FIG-44">
<title>ドロップダウンリストのサンプル。</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/dropdown_list_box.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>ドロップダウンリストのサンプル。</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</figure>
<para>
The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate a drop-down list:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>このキーは以下の機能の一つとして動作します:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>もし、ドロップダウンリストが開いていない場合、このキーはドロップダウンリストを開きます。</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>もし、ドロップダウンリストが開いている場合、このキーは現在の選択を受け入れてリストを閉じます。</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>上矢印キー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>前のリストのアイテムを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>下矢印キー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>次のリストのアイテムを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Esc</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>選択を変更せずリストを閉じます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-31">
<title>Navigating Drop-Down Combination Boxes</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>ドロップダウンコンビネーションボックスのため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>ドロップダウンコンビネーションボックスはドロップダウンリストが付属したテキストボックスです。</para>
<figure id="keynav-FIG-45">
<title>ドロップダウンコンビネーションボックスのサンプル</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/dropdown_combination_box.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>ドロップダウンコンビネーションボックスのサンプル。テキストボックスとクリックするとドロップダウンリストが表示される矢印ボタンが含まれます。</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</figure>
<para>
When the text box has focus, use the keyboard shortcuts that are listed in <xref linkend="keynav-28"/> to navigate the text box area. When the text box has focus, 
you can also use the keyboard shortcuts in the following table to navigate the drop-down list area:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>上矢印キー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>リストが表示されていないドロップダウンリストから前のアイテムを選択します</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>下矢印キー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>リストが表示されていないドロップダウンリストから次のアイテムを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>下矢印キー</keycap></keycombo>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>ドロップダウンリストを開きます</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<para>
When the drop-down list has focus, you can use the keyboard shortcuts that are listed in the following table to navigate the drop-down list:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>上矢印キー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>前のリストのアイテムを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>下矢印キー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>次のリストのアイテムを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Home</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Select the first item in the list.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>End</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Select the last item in the list.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Page Up</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>現在のリストビューの先頭にあるアイテムを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Page Down</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>現在のリストビューの最後にあるアイテムを選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>現在の選択を受け入れ、ドロップダウンリストを閉じます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Page Up</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>もし必須であれば、リストの左側へスクロールします。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Page Down</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>もし必須であれば、リストの右側へスクロールします。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-32">
<title>Navigating Sliders</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>スライダーのため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>スライダーは数値の連続的な範囲がある値を設定するために使うコントロール要素です。</para>
<figure id="keynav-FIG-46">
<title>スライダーのサンプル</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/slider.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>スライダーのサンプル。左または右に移動することができるスライダーコントロール要素を表示します</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</figure>
<para>
The following table describes the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate a slider:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para><keycap>left arrow</keycap> or <keycap>up arrow
</keycap></para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>最小単位でスライダーを左または上に移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycap>右矢印キー</keycap>または<keycap>下矢印キー</keycap></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>最小単位でスライダーを右または下に移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Page Up</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Move the slider left or up by a large amount.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Page Down</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Move the slider right or down by a large amount.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Home</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>最大値でスライダーを移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>End</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>最小値でスライダーを移動します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-33">
<title>Navigating Tabbed Sections</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>タブセクションのため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<figure id="keynav-FIG-47">
<title>タブセクションをもつダイアログのサンプル</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/tabbed_section.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
Editing profile dialog from the GNOME <application>Terminal</application> application; contains six tabbed sections.
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</figure>
<para>
Windows and dialogs are sometimes divided into logical sections that are displayed one section at a time on the window or dialog. The overall control is referred to as a notebook or tabbed panel. The divisions are called panels, pages, or tabs, and are sometimes collectively referred to as a tabstrip or notebook header. Each individual tab is identified by a text label.
</para>
<para>
The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate the tabbed sections of a window or dialog when a tabstrip has focus:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>左矢印キー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>前のタブ化されたセクションにフォーカスを与えます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>右矢印キー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>次のタブ化されたセクションにフォーカスを与えます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycap>Tab</keycap> or<keycombo>
<keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>down arrow
</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Give focus to the first control in the active section.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<para>
The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate a 
window or dialog when a control within a section has focus:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Page Up</keycap></keycombo>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Give focus to the previous section. 
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Page Down</keycap></keycombo>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Give focus to the next section.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Give focus to the next control outside the sections.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-34">
<title>Navigating Lists</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>リストのため</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate multi-column lists when a column header has focus:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para><keycap>left arrow</keycap>または<keycap>right arrow</keycap></para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>前または次のコラムヘッダーにフォーカスを与えます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>スペースバー</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>ヘッダーを有効化します。この動作は通常コラムヘッダによってソートします。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Tab</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>リストの内容にフォーカスを与えます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
<para>
The following table lists the keyboard shortcuts that you can use to navigate lists when the list area has focus:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>前後の列または行を選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Page Up</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Select the top row of the list contents that are currently in view. Press <keycap>Page Up</keycap> again to select the top row of the previous view.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Page Down</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Select the bottom row of the list contents that are currently in view. Press <keycap>Page Down</keycap> again to select the bottom row of the next view.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Home</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>リスト内の最初の列を選択します</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>End</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>リスト内の最後の列を選択します</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycap>Shift</keycap> + 矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>複数行の選択をサポートしているリストのため、現在の選択に前後の行または列を追加します。</para>
<para>単数行の選択のみ許可しているリストのため、前後の行または列を選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>Page Up</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>現在の選択とビューの先頭列の間にあるすべての列を選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>Page Down</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>現在の選択とビューの終端列の間にあるすべての列を選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>Home</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>現在の選択とリストの最初の列の間にあるすべての列を選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>End</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>現在の選択とリストの最後の列の間にあるすべての列を選択します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycap>Ctrl</keycap> + 矢印キー</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Give focus to the next row or column without extending the selection. Further items can be selected by pressing <keycap>spacebar</keycap>.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Page Up</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Give focus to the top row in the view without extending the selection.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Page Down</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Give focus to the bottom row in the view without extending the selection.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Home</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Give focus to the first row in the list without extending the selection.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>End</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Give focus to the last row in the list without extending the selection.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Return</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Activate the item(s).
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>A</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Select all rows (for lists that support multi-line selections).
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap>
<keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>該当する場合、コラムヘッダーにフォーカスを与えます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>

<section id="keynav-35">
<title>Navigating Trees</title>
<para>ツリーは伸ばしたり折り畳んだりすることができるセクションを含んだユーザインタフェースのコントロール要素です。ツリーは一般的に階層構造で表されます。</para>
<figure id="keynav-FIG-48">
<title>ツリー構造のサンプル</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/tree.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
Categories tree from the <application>gedit</application> preferences dialog; contains three subcategories.
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</figure>
<para>
To navigate trees, you can use the same keyboard shortcuts that are listed in 
<xref linkend="keynav-34"/>. In addition, the following table lists the keyboard shortcuts you can use for the tree items:
</para>
<informaltable frame="topbot">
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="33*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="67*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>キー</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>機能</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>+</keycap> (plus) or <keycombo><keycap>shift</keycap><keycap>right</keycap></keycombo>
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>フォーカスされたアイテムを拡張します。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para><keycap>-</keycap> (minus) or <keycombo><keycap>shift</keycap><keycap>left</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>フォーカスされたアイテムを折り畳みます。</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<keycap>Backspace</keycap>
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>前のアイテムを選択します</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<para><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F</keycap></keycombo></para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1">
<para>
Display a search dialog, allowing you to type the name of the tree item that you want to find. Not all trees support searching.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</informaltable>
</section>
</section>

<section id="keynav-36">
<title>キーボード・ショートカットのカスタマイズ</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>キーボード・ショートカット</primary>
<secondary>カスタマイズ</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
Use the <application>Keyboard Shortcuts</application> preference tool to display the default keyboard shortcuts that you use to navigate the GNOME Desktop. You can customize the default keyboard shortcuts to meet your requirements. You can also create hot keys (keyboard shortcuts which start applications).
</para>
<para>
To start the <application>Keyboard Shortcuts
</application> preference tool, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences
</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Keyboard Shortcuts
</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The <guilabel>
Desktop shortcuts</guilabel> table lists the keyboard shortcuts that are associated with each action.
</para>

<!--commenting out old irrelevant Solaris-only method...
<section id="keynav-49">
<title>Customizing Keyboard Shortcuts on Solaris Systems</title>
<para>
To customize a keyboard shortcut on a Solaris system, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the action for which you want to customize the keyboard shortcut. The row is highlighted.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the keyboard shortcut in the <guilabel>Shortcut</guilabel> column. The text <quote>Type a new accelerator, or press Backspace to clear</quote> is displayed in the Shortcut column. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Press the keys that you want to associate with the action. The new keyboard shortcut is displayed in the <guilabel>Shortcut</guilabel> column.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
To disable a keyboard shortcut, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the action for which you want to disable the keyboard shortcut. The row is highlighted.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the keyboard shortcut in the <guilabel>Shortcut</guilabel> column. The text <quote>Type a new accelerator, or press Backspace to clear</quote> is displayed in the Shortcut column. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Press the <keycap>backspace</keycap>. The keyboard shortcut is disabled.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
-->

<section id="keynav-50">
<title>Assigning and Clearing Keyboard Shortcuts
</title>
<para>
To assign a keyboard shortcut, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>カスタマイズしたいキーボード・ショートカットの操作をクリックしてください。行が強調され、<quote>新しいアセクラレータ...</quote>のテキストがショートカットの行に表示されます。</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>動作と関連付けたいキーを押します。新しいキーボード・ショートカットは<guilabel>ショートカット</guilabel>の行に表示されます。</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>キーボード・ショートカットを無効化するには、以下の方法を実施してください:</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>無効化したいキーボード・ショートカットの操作をクリックしてください。行が強調され、<quote>新しいアセクラレータ...</quote>のテキストがショートカットの行に表示されます。</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Press the <keycap>backspace</keycap>. The keyboard shortcut is disabled.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
</section>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter id="low-vision">
<title>Low Vision or Blindness</title>
<para>
From low vision to blindness, the range of visual limitations is broad. Symptoms of low vision include dimness, haziness, extreme far-/near-sightedness, color blindness, and tunnel vision, among others. People with these disabilities are concerned with being able to see text or images on a computer screen and being able to perform tasks that 
require eye-hand coordination, such as moving a computer mouse. Text size and color can make a big difference in legibility for people with low vision.
</para>
<para>
The technologies that can assist those with low vision or blindness are:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Desktop Appearance Enhancement</emphasis> - users can configure the desktop to be easy to read; for example, by increasing text size and using high-contrast themes.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Screen Magnifier</emphasis> - this is like a magnifying glass. People using them 
are able to control what area of the computer screen they want enlarged, and can move the magnifier to view different areas of the screen. They are also known as screen enlargers or large print programs.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Screen Reader</emphasis> - this makes on-screen information available as 
synthesized speech and/or a refreshable braille display. They generally only translate text-based information. Graphics and other non-textual objects can be 
translated if there is alternative text 
describing the item. They are also known as 
blind access utilities or screen reviewers.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>


<section id="themes-0">
<title>Desktop Appearance Enhancement</title>
<para>
This chapter describes the methods you can use to change the appearance of the GNOME Desktop in order to enhance the accessibility of the desktop for users with visual 
impairments.
</para>

<section id="themes-1">
<title>Customization Options</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>customizing the desktop appearance</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
There are several ways to customize the appearance of the GNOME Desktop to suit your 
specific needs:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>Themes</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Themes are the most effective way to change the appearance of the desktop in a consistent manner. See <xref linkend="themes-2"/> for more information about themes and how to use them to achieve the type of desktop environment that you require.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Desktop and Application-Specific Configuration Settings
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
You can customize different components of the desktop to achieve the display settings that you require. You can configure the desktop and applications in addition to using themes or as an alternative to themes. See <xref linkend="themes-7"/> for more information.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>
The following table summarizes the changes that you can make to the GNOME Desktop and where you can make the changes. This guide does not provide detailed instructions about how to customize the desktop. For detailed instructions about how to use the customization tools that the desktop provides, refer to the Help for each tool or to the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide?prefs">User Guide</ulink>.
</para>
<table frame="topbot" id="themes-TBL-1">
<title>Quick Reference to Customizing the Appearance of the Desktop
</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="50%"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="50%"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>To change the...</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Use...
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Overall appearance of the desktop using high-contrast colors, low-contrast colors, or large print.
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>The <guilabel>Theme</guilabel> section of the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Appearance of the desktop background only.
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
The <guilabel>Desktop Background</guilabel> section of the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool; also the file manager <guilabel>Backgrounds and Emblems</guilabel> menu item.
</para>
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Appearance of the mouse pointer.
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
The <guilabel>Theme</guilabel> section of the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool; use the <guilabel>Pointers</guilabel> tab of the <guilabel>Customize</guilabel> option.
</para>
</entry>
</row>

<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Font displayed on the desktop background and
in all desktop applications.
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
The <guilabel>Font</guilabel> section of the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Default font settings of the <application>Text Editor</application>,  <application>Terminal</application> or <application>Help</application> application.
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Normally these applications use the default 
application font that is specified in the <guilabel>Font</guilabel> section of the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool, but these font settings can also be overridden in the <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> dialog for the application.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>

<section id="themes-2">
<title>Using Themes to Customize the Desktop</title>
<para>
This section describes how to use themes to customize the appearance of the GNOME Desktop.
</para>

<section id="themes-3">
<title>Introduction to Themes</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>themes</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
A theme is a group of coordinated settings that specifies how a desktop component or a group of desktop components appears. You can use themes to modify and control the appearance of the desktop in a consistent manner. When you apply a theme, the system modifies many desktop components simultaneously to achieve the desired effect. For example, if you apply a theme that increases the font size across the desktop, the theme also modifies the size of panels and icons on the desktop for optimum compatibility with the font size. Some themes have suggested font settings that may optionally be auto-set; in addition, most colors within a theme can be customized.
</para>
<para>
A theme contains settings that affect different parts of the desktop: 
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>コントロール要素</term>
<listitem>
<para>
The controls setting for a theme determines the visual appearance of all windows, applications, panels, and panel applications. The controls setting also determines the visual appearance of the GNOME-compliant interface items that appear on windows, applications, panels, and panel applications such as menus, icons, and buttons. Some of the control options that are available in the desktop are designed for special accessibility needs.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Window Border</term>
<listitem>
<para>
The window frame setting determines the appearance of the border around windows only.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Icon</term>
<listitem>
<para>
The icon setting determines the appearance of icons on panels and on the desktop background.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>

<section id="themes-4">
<title>Choosing Themes</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>themes</primary>
<secondary>desktop</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>To choose a theme, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Appearance
</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The themes
are listed under the <guilabel>Theme</guilabel> tab.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on a theme in the list box to choose a new theme. The system automatically applies the theme to the desktop, and may also prompt whether to apply a suggested font for the theme. 
</para>
<para>
There are several themes available that suit different accessibility needs, as described in the following table:
</para>
<table frame="topbot" id="themes-TBL-2">
<title>Themes Designed for Accessibility Requirements
</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="50*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="50*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>Theme Name</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>説明</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>High Contrast</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Provides dark text on a light background using high-contrast colors.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>High Contrast Inverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Provides light text on a dark background using high-contrast colors.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>Large Print</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
This theme suggests an increased font size of 18pt. The background and foreground colors are the same as those specified by the <guilabel>Default</guilabel> desktop theme. To apply the suggested font, click on the <guibutton>Apply Font</guibutton> button.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>High Contrast Large Print</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
This theme suggests an increased font size of 18pt using dark text on a light background. To apply the suggested font, click on the <guibutton>Apply Font</guibutton> button.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>High Contrast Large Print Inverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
This theme suggests an increased font size of 18pt using light text on a dark background. To apply the suggested font, click on the <guibutton>Apply Font</guibutton> button.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
In some GNOME distributions there are also prebuilt low-contrast/low-contrast-large-print themes to complement the high-contrast theme set.
</para>
<para>
To view the controls, window frame, and icon settings that are associated with a theme, select a theme in the <guilabel>Appearance </guilabel> preference tool, then click on the <guibutton>Theme</guibutton> tab. The <guilabel>Customize</guilabel> option contains a tabbed section for each setting category. Each tabbed section lists the options that are available and the current setting for the theme is highlighted. 
</para>
</section>

<section id="themes-20">
<title>Modifying the Controls Setting for a Theme</title>
<para>
To modify the controls setting that is associated with a theme, perform the following steps: 
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Within the <guilabel>Theme</guilabel> tab, select the theme that you want to modify.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guibutton>Customize</guibutton> button. The <guilabel>Customize Theme</guilabel> dialog is displayed.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guilabel>Controls</guilabel> tab to display the controls options that are available.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the controls option that you want to associate with the current theme from the list box, then click <guibutton>Close</guibutton>. The following table lists the controls options that are suitable for accessibility needs: 
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<table frame="topbot">
<title>Controls Options Designed for Accessibility Requirements
</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="50*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="50*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>Control Option</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>説明</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrast</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Provides dark text on a light background using high-contrast colors.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastInverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Provides light text on a dark background using high-contrast colors.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>LargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Increases the size of controls to accommodate larger fonts. To increase the font size, you must use the <application>Font</application> preference tool. The background and foreground colors are the same as those 
specified by the <guilabel>Default</guilabel> desktop theme.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastLargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Provides dark text on a light background using high-contrast colors. Increases the size of controls to accommodate larger fonts. To increase the font size, you must use the <application>Font</application> preference tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastLargePrintInverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Provides light text on a dark background using high-contrast colors. Increases the size of controls to accommodate larger fonts. To increase the font size, you must use the <application>Font</application> preference tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>

<section id="themes-5">
<title>Modifying the Window Border Setting for a Theme
</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>themes</primary>
<secondary>window border</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
To modify the window border setting that is associated with a theme, perform the following steps: 
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
In the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool, choose the <guilabel>Theme</guilabel> tab and the theme you want to modify. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guibutton>Customize</guibutton> button. The <guilabel>Customize Theme</guilabel> dialog is displayed.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guilabel>Window Border</guilabel> tab to display the window frame options that are available. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the window frame option that you want to associate with the current theme from the list box, then click <guibutton>Close</guibutton>. The <guilabel>Atlanta</guilabel> option is designed for accessibility. 
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section id="themes-19">
<title>Modifying the Icon Setting for a Theme</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>themes</primary>
<secondary>icon</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
To modify the icon setting that is associated with a theme, perform the following steps: 
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
In the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool, choose the <guilabel>Theme</guilabel> tab and select the theme that you want to modify. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guibutton>Customize</guibutton> button. The <guilabel>Customize Theme</guilabel> dialog is displayed.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guilabel>Icons</guilabel> tab to display the icon options that are available. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the icon option that you want to associate with the theme from the list box, then click <guibutton>Close</guibutton>. The following table lists the icon options that are suitable for accessibility needs:
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<table frame="topbot">
<title>Icon Options Designed for Accessibility Requirements
</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="50*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="50*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>Icon Option</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>説明</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrast</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Provides dark-on-light icons using high-contrast colors.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastInverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Provides light-on-dark icons using high-contrast colors.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<!--<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>LargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
The background and foreground colors are the same as 
those specified by the <guilabel>Default</guilabel> 
desktop theme. To increase the font size, you must use 
the <application>Font</application> Preference tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastLargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Provides dark text on a light background using 
high-contrast colors. To increase the font size, you 
must use the <application>Font</application> Preference 
tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>HighContrastLargePrintInverse</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Provides light text on a dark background using 
high-contrast colors. To increase the font size, you 
must use the <application>Font</application> Preference 
tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>
<guilabel>LowContrastLargePrint</guilabel> 
</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Uses low-contrast colors for the background and 
foreground text. To increase the font size, you must use
the <application>Font</application> Preference tool.
</para>
</entry>
</row>-->
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>

<section id="themes-6">
<title>Creating Your Own Themes</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>themes</primary>
<secondary>creating own</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
For information about how to create your own themes, see the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:system-admin-guide?themes-0">
System Administration Guide</ulink>. 
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="themes-7">
<title>Customizing Specific Components of the Desktop
</title>
<para>
This section describes how to customize specific components of the GNOME Desktop individually.
</para>

<section id="themes-8">
<title>Customizing the Desktop Background</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>customizing desktop appearance</primary>
<secondary>desktop background</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The themes do not affect the desktop background. To set the desktop background, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu>
<guimenuitem>Appearance</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and select a background from the <guilabel>Background</guilabel> tab. If no background is chosen, the first entry listed here may be used.
</para>
</section>

<section id="themes-9">
<title>Customizing Desktop Background Objects</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>customizing desktop appearance</primary>
<secondary>desktop background objects</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The size of the icons that are displayed on the desktop background is controlled by the <application>File Management</application> preference tool. To change the size of the icons, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
From the <application>File Manager</application> window, choose the <menuchoice><guimenu>Edit</guimenu>
<guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu></menuchoice> menu item.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the <guilabel>Views</guilabel> tabbed section.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
In the <guilabel>Icon View Defaults</guilabel> group, select the zoom level that you require in the <guilabel>Default Zoom Level</guilabel> drop-down list.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section id="themes-10">
<title>Customizing Fonts</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>customizing desktop appearance</primary>
<secondary>fonts</secondary>
</indexterm>
<anchor id="themes-13"/>
<anchor id="themes-14"/>
<para>
This section describes how to customize
the font settings for the desktop and frequently-used applications.
</para>
<para>
If you have difficulty with the default font type and font size that is used on the desktop and desktop background, you can customize the font settings to suit your needs. 
</para>
<para>
You can specify individual font settings for the following desktop components and applications: 
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Entire desktop (excluding the desktop background)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Desktop background only</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Terminal</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Text Editor</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Help</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Web Browser</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<section id="themes-11">
<title>Customizing Desktop Fonts</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>customizing desktop appearance</primary>
<secondary>desktop fonts</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The <application>Appearance</application> preference tool allows you to specify the default fonts for the desktop.
</para>
<para>
To start the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu>
<guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Appearance</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The <guilabel>
Fonts</guilabel> tab contains the following options: 
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<guilabel>Application Font</guilabel> 
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on this button to select a default font to use for the text that is displayed on the desktop, including the text displayed on the windows and dialogs associated with GNOME-compliant applications and panel applications.
</para>
<note>
<para>
If you use a predefined theme and you click on the <guibutton>Apply Font</guibutton> button, the font that is associated with the theme overrides the font from the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool.
</para>
</note>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<guilabel>Document Font</guilabel> 
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on this button to select a font to use for displaying documents.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<guilabel>Desktop Font</guilabel> 
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on this button to select a font to use for the text that is displayed on the desktop background only.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><guilabel>Window Title Font</guilabel> </term>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on this button to select a font to use for the text that is displayed in the titlebar area of windows.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><guilabel>Fixed Width Font</guilabel> </term>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on this button to select a font to use for editing documents.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term><guilabel>Font Rendering</guilabel> </term>
<listitem>
<para>
To specify how to render fonts on the desktop, select one of the following options:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<guilabel>Monochrome</guilabel> 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<guilabel>Best Shapes</guilabel> 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<guilabel>Best Contrast</guilabel> 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<guilabel>Subpixel Smoothing</guilabel> 
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<note>
<para>
If you use large fonts, you may need to change the size of panes in some applications, such as the file manager and Help browser. 
</para>
</note>
<para>
For more information about the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool and fonts, see the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide?prefs-font">
User Guide</ulink>. 
</para>
</section>

<section id="themes-cust">
<title>Customizing Application Fonts</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>custom desktop appearance</primary>
<secondary>set choose individual font</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
By default, GNOME applications use the default font specified in the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool. Some applications allow this default font to be customized. These applications are:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide#yelp">
Help Browser</ulink> 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gedit? gedit-prefs-fontsandcolors">
Text Editor</ulink> </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gnome-terminal# gnome-terminal-prefs-general">
Terminal</ulink> 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<ulink type="help" url="ghelp:epiphany# ephy-customize">Web Browser</ulink> 
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section id="themes-15">
<title>Meeting Specific Accessibility Needs</title>
<para>
The following sections summarize the steps you need to take to improve the accessibility of the desktop in a particular area. 
</para>

<section id="themes-16">
<title>Achieving a High- or Low-Contrast Desktop</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>high contrast desktop</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>low contrast desktop</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
To achieve a high- or low-contrast desktop, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool to select the high-contrast or low-contrast desktop theme that you require from the <guilabel>Theme</guilabel> tab.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the <guilabel>Background</guilabel> tab to customize your desktop background as follows:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Set the <guilabel>Desktop Wallpaper</guilabel> to <guilabel>No Wallpaper</guilabel>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Set the <guilabel>Desktop Colors</guilabel> to <guilabel>Solid Color</guilabel>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select a background color that suits your needs.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
In the <application>Terminal</application> application, ensure that the <guilabel>Use colors from system theme</guilabel> option is selected in the <guilabel>Colors</guilabel> tabbed section of the <guilabel>Editing
Profile</guilabel> dialog.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
In the <application>gedit</application> (Text Editor) application, ensure that the <guilabel>Use default theme colors</guilabel> option is selected in the <guilabel>Fonts &amp; Colors</guilabel> tabbed section of the 
<guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> dialog.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section id="themes-17">
<title>Achieving a Large Print Desktop</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>large print desktop</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
To achieve a large-print desktop, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the <application>Appearance</application> preference tool to select the <guilabel>Large Print</guilabel> theme.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guibutton>Apply Font</guibutton> button to increase the size of the font that is used on the desktop and on window frames.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the <guilabel>Desktop Font</guilabel> option in the <guilabel>Font</guilabel> tab to increase the font that is displayed on desktop background objects.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Increase the font size that is used to display the contents of the <application>Terminal</application> application window. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
If the <guilabel>Use default theme font</guilabel> option is selected in the <application>gedit</application> (Text Editor) <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> dialog, <application>gedit</application> uses the font size that is specified in the large-print theme that you selected. However, if the <guilabel>Use default theme font
</guilabel> option is not selected, increase the font size that is used to display the contents of the <application>gedit</application> text editor window. See the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gedit?gedit-prefs-fontsandcolors">gedit manual</ulink> for more information.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
If you use applications that use panes, such as the file manager and help browser, you may need to change the size of panes to accommodate the large print. See the online help for the appropriate application for more information.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section id="ats-2">
<title>Orca: Screen Reader and Magnifier</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>Screen Reader and Magnifier</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>Orca</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The <application>Orca</application> Screen Reader and Magnifier application enables users with limited or no vision to use the GNOME Desktop and associated applications. <application>Orca</application> provides the following functionality: 
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Screen Reader
</para>
<para>
The screen reader enables non-visual access to standard applications in the GNOME Desktop by using speech and braille output.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Magnifier
</para>
<para>
The magnifier provides automated focus tracking and full-screen magnification to aid low-vision users.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
The following sections provide information about <application>Orca</application> and how to use it.
</para>

<section>
<title>Introduction to Orca</title>
<section>
<title>What is Orca?</title>
<para>
Orca is a flexible, extensible, and powerful assistive technology for people with visual impairments. Using various combinations of speech synthesis, braille and magnification, Orca helps provide access to applications
and toolkits that support the AT-SPI (e.g., the GNOME Desktop). <application>Orca</application> is also free open source software.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Why the name Orca?</title>
<para>
One of the first DOS screen readers was Flipper, made by Omnichron Corporation in Berkeley, CA. It was named Flipper in part because the blind wife of the programmer 
envisioned computers as being programmed by flipping switches (an accurate image of a bygone era). Then came another DOS screen reader, this one from Henter-Joyce in 
Florida - "Jobs Access With Speech" (or JAWS). And so on....
</para>
<para>
Although no obvious connection exists between blindness and creatures from the sea, there is certainly a naming tradition for screen-reader software. Hence <application>Orca</application>, which is a lot tougher-sounding than Nemo, Ariel, Willy, or Mr. Limpet.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>What's the schedule?</title>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> is part of the GNOME platform and <application>Orca</application>'s releases are coupled with the releases of the GNOME platform.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>How do I request a new feature?</title>
<para>
<ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/buglist.cgi?query=product:orca+">Bugs</ulink> and feature/enhancement requests (RFEs) 
should be reported to the <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org">GNOME Bug Tracking System
</ulink>. Patches are always welcome, and instructions for creating patches can be found in the <ulink url="http://developer.gnome.org/tools/svn.html">
GNOME Introduction to Subversion (SVN)
</ulink>.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Where is the discussion list?</title>
<para>
You can get in touch with developers and other users by <ulink url="mailto:orca-list@gnome.org">sending an e-mail</ulink> to the <ulink url="http://mail.gnome.org/mailman/listinfo/orca-list">Orca mailing list</ulink> 
(<ulink url="http://mail.gnome.org/archives/orca-list">Archives</ulink>).
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Is braille supported?</title>
<para>
Yes! Braille is supported via BrlTTY and it is tightly integrated with Orca. BrlTTY offers support for nearly every refreshable braille display known to man.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Is contracted braille supported?</title>
<para>
Yes, <application>Orca</application> fully supports contracted braille output.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>What voices are available?</title>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> provides interfaces to both <userinput>gnome-speech</userinput> and <userinput>emacspeak</userinput> speech services. As such, the available voices for <application>Orca</application> are only restricted by the speech engines supported by the available speech services. For free speech engines, you typically have a choice of the eSpeak, Festival, and FreeTTS speech engines. For commercial engines, you have a choice of 
additional engines such as Fonix DECtalk, Loquendo, Eloquence, Cepstral and IBMTTS, with others on the way. Periodically check the <userinput>gnome-speech</userinput> package for more progress in this area.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>What languages are supported?</title>
<para>
The <ulink url="http://l10n.gnome.org/teams">
GNOME translation teams</ulink> are composed of many passionate volunteers from around the world. These teams do a great job and keep an up-to-date status report. See the <ulink url="http://l10n.gnome.org/module/orca">
Orca translation status page</ulink> for the large number of languages into which <application>Orca</application> has been translated.
</para>
<para> 
Note: support for a language also depends on 
the speech synthesis engine also supporting the same language.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>How well does magnification work?</title>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> currently uses the <userinput>gnome-mag</userinput> 
magnification service. <userinput>gnome-mag</userinput> has incorporated support for smoother full-screen magnification, which 
relies upon newer extensions in the X Window System server. These extensions do not always function well on all platforms, so smooth full-screen magnification may not always work.
</para>
</section>

</section>

<section id="enable-orca">
<title>Enabling Orca</title>
<para>
For a text-only guided setup, open a Run dialog with <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo> or <keycombo><keycap>Meta</keycap><keycap>R</keycap></keycombo> and use the command <userinput>orca --text-setup</userinput> <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>
<para>
The first time <application>Orca</application> is launched you will be asked a few questions:
</para>
<para>
First you will be presented with a list of languages to choose from; there are currently about 45 languages supported. Most of this list will scroll off the screen, so you may have to use the terminal's scrollbar to view earlier parts of the list. Type in the number of your language choice (e.g., 7 for American English) and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.  You do not need to wait for the entire list to be spoken, and Orca attempts to make your default language the first choice (choice 1).
</para>
<para>
You are next asked to set <guilabel>Echo By Word</guilabel>. This option instructs <application>Orca</application> to speak words as you finish typing them. Type <keycap>y</keycap> or <keycap>n</keycap> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>
<para>
The next item is <guilabel>Key Echo</guilabel>. This option will speak all keys as they are pressed. Type <keycap>y</keycap> or <keycap>n</keycap> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>
<para>
Now select your desired keyboard layout; generally, you will want to choose the layout that matches your keyboard type - 1 for Desktop or 2 for Laptop. This choice will determine what key will act as the <application>Orca</application> modifier key. The Desktop layout uses <keycap>Insert</keycap> while the Laptop layout uses <keycap>Caps Lock</keycap>. A system, host, shift or modifier key is one which is used in conjunction with other keys, enabling keyboard access to most program functions.
</para>
<para>
Next, specify if you require braille output. This functionality assumes a BrlTTY-compatible device is available. Type <keycap>y</keycap> or <keycap>n</keycap> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.  Note that you can usually just enter <keycap>y</keycap> here; Orca will recover gracefully and function even if it cannot find BrlTTY.
</para>
<para>
Lastly, indicate whether you want an on-screen braille output monitor. This is mostly for developers who need to verify BrlTTY output, but may also be useful in other situations, such as visually diagnosing or verifying braille output. Type <keycap>y</keycap> or <keycap>n</keycap> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>
<para>
That's it! <application>Orca</application> is now ready for use. If accessibility was not yet enabled, <application>Orca</application> does so now and asks you to logout and back in for the services to start. Type <keycap>y</keycap> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap> to restart your login session.
</para>
<para>
After completing the first-time <application>Orca</application> settings, use <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo> or <keycombo><keycap>Meta</keycap><keycap>R</keycap></keycombo> to bring up the Run dialog, type in <literal>orca</literal> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>. Accessibility functions should now be active.  Orca's Configuration GUI (<xref linkend="configuration-gui"/>) also has an option to let you indicate that Orca should be started automatically when you log in.
</para>
<para>
If you plan to use the Magnifier portion of <application>Orca</application> in full screen mode, nonfirm the <application>Xserver</application> "Composite" extension is enabled: use <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo> or <keycombo><keycap>Meta</keycap><keycap>R</keycap></keycombo> to bring up the Run dialog, type in <literal>xdpyinfo</literal> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.  Look for the string "Composite" in the output.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Using Orca</title>
<section>
<title>Initial Setup</title>
<para>
When you run <application>Orca</application> for the first time, it will automatically enter setup mode. If you want to run setup 
at some later point, you can pass the
<userinput>--setup</userinput> option to <application>Orca</application> the next 
time you run it. Furthermore, while <application>Orca</application> is running, 
you can press <keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo> to bring up <application>Orca</application>'s Configuration GUI (<xref linkend="configuration-gui"/>). Finally, <application>Orca</application> provides a text setup utility that you can start by passing the 
<userinput>--text-setup</userinput> option to <application>Orca</application>. All of these options will create a <userinput>~/.orca/user-settings.py</userinput> file that holds your preferences and will also enable the accessibility infrastructure. You need to log out and log back in for the new settings to take effect.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>How do I run Orca?</title>
<para>
Run <application>Orca</application> by typing <userinput>orca</userinput> in a terminal session window. You can do so from a virtual 
console window if you do not yet have access to the GUI. With the GUI installed you can also press <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo> or <keycombo><keycap>Meta</keycap>
<keycap>R</keycap></keycombo> to bring up the Run dialog and then type <userinput>orca</userinput> as the command (followed by any optional parameters).  Then, press <keycap>Enter</keycap>. <application>Orca</application> will automatically enter text setup mode if you run it from a virtual console window or your GUI environment is not yet set up for accessibility.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Quitting Orca</title>
<para>
To quit <application>Orca</application>, press <keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap>
<keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo> (or <keycombo><keycap>CapsLock</keycap>
<keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo> in laptop layout mode). A confirmation dialog will appear. Select <guilabel>Yes</guilabel> to quit. If the system seems unresponsive, you can try a few things:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Run <userinput>orca --quit</userinput> from a terminal window, such as a virtual console; press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F1</keycap>
</keycombo> (on most Linux platforms) to get to a virtual console, enter your commands, and then use <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>F7</keycap></keycombo> to get back to the desktop. This will kill the <application>Orca</application> process and reclaim system resources. You can then 
rerun <application>Orca</application> using the previously outlined methods.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Backspace</keycap>
</keycombo> to end your login session and get back to the graphical login prompt (not implemented in all Linux distributions).
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</section>

<section id="configuration-gui">
<title>Orca Configuration GUI</title>
<para>
The <application>Orca</application> Configuration GUI allows you to customize the behavior and features of <application>Orca</application>, such as speech, braille, and magnification. For example, you can select which speech synthesis engine you want to use, whether braille is enabled or not, and which magnification preferences you want. You can select which general keyboard layout you want (desktop or laptop) and you can also examine and modify the existing keyboard layout with fine-grained control. To bring up the <application>Orca</application> Configuration GUI, press <keycombo><keycap>Orca_Modifier</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo>, where <keycap>Orca_Modifier</keycap> is <keycap>Insert</keycap> when you use the Desktop Keyboard Layout (<xref linkend="orca-desktop-keys"/>) and <keycap>CapsLock</keycap> when you use the Laptop Keyboard Layout (<xref linkend="orca-laptop-keys"/>). If you want to change settings for a single application, press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Orca_Modifier</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo> while the application has focus.
</para>
<para>
The <application>Orca</application> Configuration GUI is a dialog containing several tabbed pages, each of which is described in the following sections.
</para>

<section>
<title>General Page</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/General_Tab.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
<application>Orca</application> GUI Configuration - General Page
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
<para>
The <guilabel>General</guilabel> page allows you to customize general aspects of <application>Orca</application>. These include the following:
</para>

<section>
<title>Keyboard Layout</title>
<para>
The keyboard layout section allows you to specify if you will be working on a laptop (small) or desktop (large, with a numeric keypad) keyboard. You select which layout you want by selecting one of the following options:
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Desktop</emphasis> - if selected, the Desktop Keyboard Layout (<xref linkend="orca-desktop-keys"/>) will be used.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Laptop</emphasis> - if selected, the Laptop Keyboard Layout (<xref linkend="orca-laptop-keys"/>) will be used.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Show Orca main window</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/MainWindow.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
<application>Orca</application> GUI Configuration - Main window
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
<para>
The <application>Orca</application> main window provides you with a graphical way to display the <application>Orca</application> Configuration GUI (also accessible with <keycombo><keycap>Orca_Modifier</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo>, where Orca_Modifier is <keycap>Insert</keycap> when you use the Desktop Keyboard Layout (<xref linkend="orca-desktop-keys"/>) and <keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap> when you use the Laptop Keyboard Layout (<xref linkend="orca-laptop-keys"/>)). The main window also provides a <guibutton>Quit</guibutton> option, also available with <keycombo><keycap>Orca_Modifier</keycap><keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo>). Many users do not like the <application>Orca</application> main window because it shows up in the window manager's tab order when you press <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo> to switch windows. By deselecting the "Show Orca main window" button, you can tell <application>Orca</application> to not show the <application>Orca</application> main window.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Quit Orca without Confirmation</title>
<para>
Normally, when you press <keycombo><keycap>Orca_Modifier</keycap><keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo> to quit <application>Orca</application> or press the <guibutton>Quit</guibutton> button in the <application>Orca</application> main window, <application>Orca</application> will pop up a confirmation dialog asking you if you want to quit. Unchecking this option prevents the confirmation window from appearing.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Disable gksu keyboard grab</title>
<para>
When running commands from the launch menu, many distributions use an application known as <application>gksu</application> to authorize the user to run these commands; <application>gksu</application> is the GUI that asks you for your password. When it runs, <application>gksu</application> enables what is known as a "keyboard grab," which is a feature to prevent keyboard actions from going to any other application on the desktop, including <application>Orca</application>.  The result of a keyboard grab is that <application>Orca</application> will not receive any keyboard events, preventing <application>Orca</application> from functioning normally.
</para>
<para>
By selecting the "Disable gksu keyboard grab" button, you will turn off the keyboard grab behavior, allowing <application>Orca</application> to function normally with system administration applications.
</para>
<note>
<para>
The keyboard grab is a security attempt by <application>gksu</application> to prevent nefarious applications from "sniffing" the keyboard and grabbing secret information.  Please be advised that disabling the gksu keyboard grab feature can expose you to such nefarious behavior. If you do not feel comfortable with this, you can always use the root account for system administration purposes. To do so, you need to enable the root account for login, and then logout and log back in as root whenever you want to perform a system administration command.
</para>
</note>
</section>

<section>
<title>Present tooltips</title>
<para>
When checked, this option will tell <application>Orca</application> to present information about tooltips when they appear as the result of mouse hovering. Specific actions to force tooltips to appear, such as pressing <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F1</keycap></keycombo> when an object has focus, will always result in tooltips being presented, regardless of this setting.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Speak object under mouse</title>
<para>
When checked, this option will tell <application>Orca</application> to present information about the object under the mouse when you move it around the screen. Note that this can cause <application>Firefox</application> and <application>Thunderbird</application> versions 2.x and earlier to crash; this is not a problem with <application>Firefox</application> and <application>Thunderbird</application> versions 3.x and later.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Start Orca when you login</title>
<para>
When checked, this option will tell the system to automatically launch <application>Orca</application> when you log in.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Speech Page</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/Speech_Tab.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
<application>Orca</application> GUI Configuration - Speech Page
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
<para>
The speech page allows you to customize how <application>Orca</application> uses speech synthesis.
</para>

<section>
<title>Enable speech</title>
<para>
The first control of note on the speech page is the "enable speech" check box. This check box toggles whether or not <application>Orca</application> will make use of a speech synthesizer. This option, along with the ability to enable braille and enable magnifier support, allow <application>Orca</application> to be tailored to meet the needs of a wide variety of users.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Speech System and Speech Synthesizer</title>
<para>
The next two controls deal with selecting the speech system and synthesizer. <application>Orca</application> provides support for a growing number of speech systems. At the time of this writing, these include GNOME-speech, Emacspeak, and an experimental backend for Speech Dispatcher.  Depending upon how your machine is configured, you may have all or none of these options.  Typically, you will have just GNOME-speech.
</para>
<para>
First, determine which speech system you would like to use - GNOME-speech works best at this time. After making your selection, tab to the speech synthesizer combo box and choose from the list of available synthesizers.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Voice Settings</title>
<para>
If your synthesizer supports it, <application>Orca</application> can utilize multiple voices in order to identify special cases within an application, such as hyperlinks or upper case text. The voice settings and person combo boxes can be adjusted to customize these settings to your liking. For example, assume you were using Fonix DECtalk and wanted the Betty voice to denote upper case. To accomplish this, you could do the following:
</para>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>
Tab to the voice settings combo box, and down arrow until the upper case voice is selected.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Tab to the person combo box, and down arrow to choose the Betty voice.
</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<para>
The next three sliders in the tab order allow adjustment of the synthesizer's rate, pitch and volume, respectively.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Punctuation Level</title>
<para>
The punctuation level radio button group is used to adjust the amount of punctuation spoken by the synthesizer. The available levels are None, Some, Most and All.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Verbosity</title>
<para>
The verbosity setting determines the amount of information that will be spoken in certain situations. For example, if it is set to verbose, the synthesizer will speak shortcut keys for items in pull down menus. When it is set to brief, these shortcut keys are not announced.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Table Row Speech</title>
<para>
The table row speech option determines the way in which <application>Orca</application> will read items within tables. The available settings are "speak current row" or "speak current cell". The ability to adjust this behavior can be useful in many situations.  For example, consider the process of browsing email messages in <application>Evolution</application>. In this instance it may be preferable to set table speech to "speak current row" so that while arrowing through the list of messages all relevant info, such as the sender, subject, and whether the message has attachments, is read automatically. While the current row setting is active, it is still possible to read individual cells by using the left and right arrows.
</para>
<note>
<para>
You can quickly toggle this behavior by pressing <keycombo><keycap>Orca_Modifier</keycap><keycap>F11</keycap></keycombo>.
</para>
</note>
</section>

<section>
<title>Speak Progress Bar Updates</title>
<para>
If this setting is enabled, <application>Orca</application> will periodically announce the status of progress bars. How often the announcement is made is determined by the value chosen in the <guilabel>Update Interval</guilabel> spin button. Note that this spin button is only available if the "Speak progress bar updates" checkbox has been checked.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Speak Indentation and Justification</title>
<para>
When working with code or editing other documents it is often desirable to be aware of justification and indentation. Selecting the "Speak indentation and justification" check box will cause <application>Orca</application> to provide this information.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Speak Blank Lines</title>
<para>
Some users desire to hear "blank" when navigating to a blank line in a document.  Other users do not. If the "speak blank lines" check box is selected, <application>Orca</application> will speak blank lines.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Speak tutorial messages</title>
<para>
When moving from component to component in an interface, this option will provide spoken tutorial messages for how to work with the component.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Say All By</title>
<para>
This combo box allows you to specify whether the "say all" functionality of <application>Orca</application> speaks by sentence or line.  See the Desktop Keyboard Layout (<xref linkend="orca-desktop-keys"/>) and Laptop Keyboard Layout (<xref linkend="orca-laptop-keys"/>) for how to invoke the "say all" functionality).
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Braille Page</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/Braille_Tab.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
<application>Orca</application> GUI Configuration - Braille Page
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
<para>
The braille page allows you to customize various aspects about the use of braille.
</para>
<note>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> does not automatically start BrlTTY for you; typically you need to do this yourself, usually at boot time.
</para>
</note>

<section>
<title>Enable Braille Support</title>
<para>
The first control on the braille page is the "Enable braille support" check box. This check box toggles whether or not <application>Orca</application> will make use of a braille display. This option, along with the ability to enable braille and enable magnifier support, allow <application>Orca</application> to be tailored to meet the needs of a wide variety of users. By default, this check box is enabled. If BrlTTY is not running, <application>Orca</application> will recover gracefully and will not communicate with the braille display. If you configure BrlTTY later on, you need to restart <application>Orca</application> in order for it to use braille.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Enable Braille Monitor</title>
<para>
<application>Orca</application>'s braille monitor provides an on-screen representation of what takes place on the braille display. This feature is mostly for demonstration purposes, but is also useful for <application>Orca</application> developers who do not have access to a braille display.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Abbreviated Role Names</title>
<para>
The "Abbreviated role names" check box determines the manner in which role names are displayed and can be used to help conserve real estate on the braille display. The "Abbreviated role names" option can be better understood if we consider the following example. Let us assume that a slider had focus, and that the abbreviated role names box was not checked. In this case, the word "slider" would be shown on the display, to reflect the fact that the current control was indeed a slider. If the abbreviated role names box were checked, the word "slider" would be abbreviated to "sldr".
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Disable end of line symbol</title>
<para>
When checked, this feature tells <application>Orca</application> to not present the "$l" string at the end of a line.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Contracted Braille</title>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> supports contracted braille via the liblouis project.  Refer to <ulink url="http://live.gnome.org/Orca/Braille#Braille">the Orca WIKI</ulink>, where you can find additional information about setting up liblouis with <application>Orca</application>.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Verbosity</title>
<para>
The verbosity radio button group determines the amount of information that will be brailled in certain situations. For example, if it is set to verbose, keyboard shortcut and role name information is displayed. This information is not displayed in brief mode.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Selection Indicator</title>
<para>
When you select text, <application>Orca</application> will "underline" that text on your braille display with Dots 7 and 8. If you would prefer, you can change the indicator to only be Dot 7, only be Dot 8, or not be present at all.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Hyperlink Indicator</title>
<para>
When you encounter a hyperlink, <application>Orca</application> will "underline" that text on your braille display with Dots 7 and 8. If you would prefer, you can change the indicator to only be Dot 7, only be Dot 8, or not be present at all.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Key Echo Page</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/KeyEcho_Tab.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
<application>Orca</application> GUI Configuration - Key Echo Page
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
<para>
The key echo page allows you to specify the behavior of <application>Orca</application> when pressing keys on the page and whether words are spoken as you complete them.
</para>

<section>
<title>Enable Key Echo</title>
<para>
The first control on the key echo page is the "Enable key echo" check box. When this box is selected, six additional check boxes become available. These are: "Enable alphanumeric and punctuation keys", "Enable modifier keys", "Enable locking keys", "Enable function keys", "Enable action keys", and "Enable navigation keys".
</para>
<para>
The alphanumeric and function key groups are relatively self explanatory.
</para>
<para>
Modifier keys are those such as <keycap>Shift</keycap>, <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, and <keycap>Alt</keycap>.
</para>
<para>
Locking keys include <keycap>Caps Lock</keycap>, <keycap>Scroll Lock</keycap> and <keycap>Num Lock</keycap>.
</para>
<para>
The action keys group consists of keys that perform some logical action, such as <keycap>Backspace</keycap>, <keycap>Return</keycap> and <keycap>Tab</keycap>.
</para>
<para>
The navigation keys group include the four arrow keys as well as any key combination in which the Orca Modifier key is being held down. The latter is designed to prevent <application>Orca</application> from echoing flat review commands.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Enable Echo by Word</title>
<para>
The next toggle on the key echo page is the "Enable echo by word" check box, used to echo the word you just typed. The "Echo by word" control is always available, regardless of whether any of the key echo options are checked.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Enable Echo by Sentence</title>
<para>
The last toggle on the key echo page is the "Enable echo by sentence" check box, used to echo the sentence you just typed. The echo by sentence control is always available, regardless of whether any of the key echo options are checked.
</para>
<para>
In summary, the key echo scheme can offer a great deal of flexibility. For example, one user might choose to enable all key echo options, while another might prefer to use word echo, but only have locking keys announced.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Magnifier Page</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/Magnifier_Tab.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
<application>Orca</application> GUI Configuration - Magnifier Page
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
<para>
The magnifier page allows you to enable/disable magnification and specify how magnification is performed.
</para>

<section>
<title>Enable Magnifier</title>
<para>
The first control on the magnifier page is the "Enable magnifier" check box. This check box toggles whether or not <application>Orca</application> will provide magnification. This option, along with the ability to enable speech and enable braille support, allow <application>Orca</application> to be tailored to meet the needs of a wide variety of users.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Zoomer Settings</title>
<para>
Two zoomer GUI controls determine magnification characteristics:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
"Scale factor", which sets magnification power from 1.0x to 16.0x (fractional values are supported).
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
"Position", which sets the location and size of the magnifier window: "Full Screen", "Left Half", "Right Half", "Top Half", "Bottom Half", and "Custom". The default position is "Full Screen". Choosing "Custom" causes four spin buttons to become available: "Top", "Left", "Right", and "Bottom".  These spin buttons allow you to define the location of each edge of the zoom window.  Units are in pixels.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section>
<title>Border Settings</title>
<note>
<para>
These options are not available in "Full Screen" mode.
</para>
</note>

<section>
<title>Enable border</title>
<para>
This option determines if a window border is visible for the magnifier.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Border size</title>
<para>
This value determines the size of the border in pixels. 
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Cursor Settings</title>
<para>
These controls can be used to customize the size and color of the magnifier's cursor.
</para>

<section>
<title>Enable cursor</title>
<para>
If this check box is enabled then a cursor is visible and the size and color options become available.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Custom size</title>
<para>
Enable this check box if you would like to make the mouse pointer larger than it normally is. The cursor size can be changed from the default value of 32 pixels.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Custom color</title>
<para>
If the cursor is enabled, a custom color can also be applied.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Cross-hair Settings</title>
<para>
This set of controls can be used to customize the magnifier's optional area-targeting cursor.
</para>

<section>
<title>Enable cross-hair</title>
<para>
If checked, you can additionally configure the clipping behavior, size and color of the cross-hair.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Enable cross-hair clip</title>
<para>
If enabled, the cross-hair will be "clipped" (removed) in the area immediately surrounding the mouse pointer.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Cross-hair size</title>
<para>
This control sets the thickness of the cross-hair in pixels.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Cross-hair color</title>
<para>
This control allows a custom color to be used for the cross-hair.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Color Settings</title>
<para>
This allows you to do some rough color adjustments of the magnified region.
</para>

<section>
<title>Invert colors</title>
<para>
Creates a reverse or negative-image effect.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Brightness</title>
<para>
Ranges from -1 to 1 (-1 is black/no brightness; 1 is white/total brightness; 0 is "normal"/unchanged).
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Contrast</title>
<para>
Ranges from -1 to 1 (-1 is grey/no contrast; 1 is maximum contrast; 0 is "normal"/unchanged).
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Tracking and Alignment Settings</title>
<para>
These options control the tracking of the mouse cursor.
</para>

<section>
<title>Mouse pointer</title>
<para>
Choose from the following options:
</para>

<section>
<title>Centered</title>
<para>
Keeps the mouse pointer at the center of the screen whenever possible. This is the default.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Proportional</title>
<para>
Positions the mouse pointer in the zoom window relative to its actual, unmagnified position.  For instance, if the mouse pointer is 25% away from the left edge of the desktop, <application>Orca</application> positions the magnified mouse pointer 25% from the left edge of the zoom window.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Push</title>
<para>
Moves the zoomer window the least amount necessary to keep the mouse pointer on the screen.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>None</title>
<para>
Moving the mouse pointer has no impact on what the zoomer window displays.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Pointer follows zoomer</title>
<para>
This option is enabled by default. If the mouse pointer is not on the screen when you initially move the mouse, it will be moved into the zoomer so that you can continue to see what you were working on. If your preferred mouse tracking mode is centered, the pointer will be moved to the center; otherwise it will be moved to the item with focus.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Control and menu item</title>
<para>
These options control additional behavior of the magnifier.
</para>

<section>
<title>Centered</title>
<para>
When navigating via keyboard, keep the focused dialog box control or menu item at the center of the screen whenever possible.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Push</title>
<para>
When navigating via keyboard, move the zoomer window the least amount necessary to display the focused dialog box control or menu item.  This is the default.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>None</title>
<para>
Using the keyboard to navigate among dialog box controls and menu items will have no impact on what the zoomer window displays.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Pointer follows focus</title>
<para>
If this option is enabled, the mouse pointer will follow you as you arrow through menu items and move among controls in dialog boxes. This option is disabled by default.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Text cursor</title>
<para>
These options control how the text cursor behaves.
</para>

<section>
<title>Centered</title>
<para>
As the text cursor moves, keep it at the center of the screen whenever possible.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Push</title>
<para>
As the text cursor moves, move the zoomer window the least amount necessary to display it. This is the default.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>None</title>
<para>
Moving the text cursor will have no impact on what the zoomer window displays.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Edge margin</title>
<para>
The edge margin is how close the caret should be allowed to get to the edge of the screen before it's time to "push" the zoomer window. The margin can range from 0 to 50%, with 50% being the equivalent of choosing centering.  The default value is 0.
</para>
<note>
<para>
This option is only available if "Push" is your text cursor tracking mode.
</para>
</note>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Advanced Settings</title>
<para>
If you press the Advanced Settings button located near the bottom of the Magnifier page, the following dialog will appear:
</para>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/Magnifier_Advanced.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
<application>Orca</application> GUI Configuration - Magnifier - Advanced Settings
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>

<section>
<title>Smoothing</title>
<para>
Bilinear or none.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Brightness</title>
<para>
Red, Green, Blue: Individual controls for choosing customized brightness levels.  Choosing different brightness levels for each color allows you to create the color scheme that works best for you.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Contrast</title>
<para>
Red, Green, Blue: Individual controls for choosing customized contrast levels. While not as significant as changes to brightness, choosing different contrast levels for each color helps you to create the color scheme that works best for you.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Color Filtering</title>
<para>
Allows you to pick one of the colorblind filters available through libcolorblind.
</para>
<note>
<para>
In order to take advantage of this feature you will need to install libcolorblind and then rebuild gnome-mag.
</para>
</note>
</section>

<section>
<title>Multi-Monitor Settings - Source Display</title>
<para>
X Window System DISPLAY of what should be magnified. Written in the form ":0.x" where x is the number of the screen whose contents should be magnified.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Multi-Monitor Settings - Target Display</title>
<para>
X Window System DISPLAY of where to put the zoomer window. Written in the form ":0.y" where y is the number of the screen where the zoomer window should appear.
</para>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section id="orca-keybindings-page">
<title>Key Bindings Page</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/KeyBindings_Tab.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
<application>Orca</application> GUI Configuration - Key Bindings Page
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
<para>
The key bindings page allows you to examine and modify the key bindings for <application>Orca</application>.
</para>

<section>
<title>Orca Modifier Key(s)</title>
<para>
The first control on the key bindings page allows you to examine which key (or keys) acts as the "<application>Orca</application> modifier." The <application>Orca</application> modifier is the key that you press and hold in conjunction with other keys to give commands to <application>Orca</application>. For  desktop keyboards, the Orca modifier defaults to <keycap>Insert</keycap>. For laptop keyboards, the <application>Orca</application> modifier defaults to the <keycap>Caps Lock</keycap> key.  See the Desktop Keyboard Layout (<xref linkend="orca-desktop-keys"/>) and Laptop Keyboard Layout (<xref linkend="orca-laptop-keys"/>) sections for the default values.
</para>
<note>
<para>
You cannot modify the <application>Orca</application> modifier key(s) using the Configuration GUI at this time.
</para>
</note>
</section>

<section>
<title>Key Bindings Table</title>
<para>
The key bindings table provides a list of <application>Orca</application> operations and the keys that are bound to them.
</para>
<para>
The "Function" column header is a description of the <application>Orca</application> operation to be performed.
</para>
<para>
The "Key Binding" header is the primary way to invoke the function from the keyboard. Note that the function description may include the word "Orca". This indicates that the <application>Orca</application> modifier key should be held down along with the other keys.
</para>
<para>
The "Alternate" header provides an alternate mechanism for invoking the function from the keyboard.
</para>
<para>
To modify either the "Key Binding" or the "Alternate" bindings, arrow to the cell and press <keycap>Return</keycap>. Then, press a key combination and press <keycap>Return</keycap> to confirm the new combination. When you do so, the new keystroke will be saved and the check box in the last column (the "Modified" column) will indicate that the key binding has been modified.
</para>
<para>
To undo a modified keybinding, merely arrow to the modified column, uncheck the checkbox, and press the "Apply" button <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>A</keycap></keycombo>.
</para>
<para>
Beneath the list of <application>Orca</application> keybindings, you will find a group of "unbound" commands:
</para>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/KeyBindings_Tab_Unbound.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
<application>Orca</application> GUI Configuration - Key Bindings Page showing the 'unbound' group of commands
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
<para>
These are commands which we feel will be very useful for some users, but not needed by most users. Rather than "use up" a keystroke for such commands, we have left them unassigned.  You can assign a keystroke to any of these unbound commands by following the procedure outlined above. In addition, you can unbind any bound command in a similar fashion: press <keycap>Return</keycap> to edit the keybinding, and when prompted for the new keybinding, press <keycap>Delete</keycap> or <keycap>Backspace</keycap>. You will be told that the key binding has been removed. Press <keycap>Return</keycap> to confirm.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Pronunciation Page</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/Pronunciation_Tab.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
<application>Orca</application> GUI Configuration - Pronunciation Page
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
<para>
Sometimes your speech synthesizer just doesn't say the right thing for a given string. You might prefer to hear "laughing out loud" rather than "LOL." Or there may be a name or a technical term which the synthesizer mispronounces. The pronunciation page is where you can add, edit, and delete <application>Orca</application>'s pronunciation dictionary entries. Because the pronunciation page is also part of the application-specific settings dialog that's started when you give a particular application focus and type <keycombo><keycap>Orca_Modifier</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo>, you can customize your entries on an as-needed basis for each application you use.
</para>

<section>
<title>Add a new dictionary entry</title>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>
Press the <guibutton>New Entry</guibutton> button (<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>N</keycap></keycombo>).
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Type the text of the new entry and press <keycap>Return</keycap> to finish editing the actual string.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Move to the Replacement String column and press <keycap>Return</keycap> to begin editing.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Type the text that you would like to have spoken instead and press <keycap>Return</keycap> to finish editing the replacement string.
</para>
</step>
</procedure>  
</section>

<section>
<title>Edit an existing dictionary entry</title>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>
Move to the cell you wish to edit and press <keycap>Return</keycap> to begin editing.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Make your changes and then press <keycap>Return</keycap> to finish editing.
</para>
</step>
</procedure>  
</section>

<section>
<title>Delete an existing dictionary entry</title>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>
Move to the entry you wish to delete.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Press the Delete button or <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>D</keycap></keycombo>.
</para>
</step>
</procedure>  
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Text Attributes Page</title>
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/TextAttributes_Tab.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>
<application>Orca</application> GUI Configuration - Text Attributes Page
</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> will speak known text attribute information about an object when you press <keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>F</keycap></keycombo> (desktop layout) or <keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>F</keycap></keycombo> (laptop layout). Because the number of text attributes is large, and not everyone cares about every attribute, the "Text Attributes" tab of the configuration
GUI allows you to customize which text attributes <application>Orca</application> will present.
</para>
<para>
On this tab is a text attribute list, where each row consists of four columns:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
The name of the text attribute.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
A checkbox which the user can set to indicate whether this text attribute should be spoken or not.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
A checkbox which the user can set to indicate whether this text attribute should be "underlined" on the braille display.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
An editable "Present unless" string value. By default, not all text attributes will have this set. If present, what it means (assuming the user wants this text attribute presented) is that the value of the attribute will only be presented if it is <emphasis>not</emphasis> this value.
</para>
<para>
For example, by default the "underline" text attribute has a value of "none." If the user has this attribute checked and the user types
<keycombo><keycap>Orca_Modifier</keycap><keycap>F</keycap></keycombo> and the text in question is not underlined, then this
attribute is not spoken. If you always want this attribute to be spoken irrespective of whether the text is underlined, then the
attribute should be checked and the "Present unless" value cleared.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
There is also a <guibutton>Reset</guibutton> button (<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>R</keycap></keycombo>) which will set the list values back to their initial state when the dialog was first displayed.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
When you initially display the text attribute pane, all your checked attributes are put at the top of the list. They are given in the order that they will be spoken and brailled.
</para>
<para>
If you decide to check others or adjust the order, there are four buttons to help you do this:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<guibutton>Move to top</guibutton> (<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>T</keycap></keycombo>) - moves the selected attribute to the top of the list.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<guibutton>Move up one</guibutton> (<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>U</keycap></keycombo>) - moves the selected attribute up one row.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<guibutton>Move down one</guibutton> (<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>D</keycap></keycombo>) - moves the selected attribute down one row.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<guibutton>Move to bottom</guibutton> (<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>B</keycap></keycombo>) - moves the selected attribute to the bottom of the list.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
Beneath these push buttons is the Braille Indicator group of radio buttons. Here you can select the cell or cells to be used to indicate text which has at least one of the specified attributes. Your choices are:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
None (the default)
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Dot 7
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Dot 8
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Dots 7 and 8
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
Text attributes can also be set on an individual application basis. The text attribute pane is also part of the application-specific settings dialog that's started when you give a particular application focus and type <keycombo><keycap>Orca_Modifier</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo>.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Orca Keyboard Commands</title>
<para>
You can get a complete list of available keyboard commands by visiting the <guilabel>Key Bindings</guilabel> page of the <application>Orca</application> Configuration GUI (<xref linkend="orca-keybindings-page"/>). To bring up the <application>Orca</application> Configuration GUI, press <keycombo><keycap>Orca_Modifier</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo>, where <userinput>Orca_Modifier</userinput> is the <keycap>Insert</keycap> key for the <link linkend="orca-desktop-keys">desktop layout</link> and the <keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap> key for the <link linkend="orca-laptop-keys">laptop layout</link>. Note that you can also enter <application>Orca</application>'s "learn mode" while running <application>Orca</application> by pressing <keycombo><keycap>Orca_Modifier</keycap><keycap>H</keycap></keycombo>. When in learn mode, <application>Orca</application> will intercept all keyboard and braille input events and tell you what the effect would be.  To exit learn mode, press the <keycap>Escape</keycap> key.
</para>
<note>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> provides additional commands for some applications, such as <application>Firefox</application>.  To get the list of additional commands for an application, press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Orca_Modifier</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo> when that application has focus. This will bring up the <application>Orca</application> Configuration GUI in the "application-specific" state, and the additional commands will appear in the <guilabel>Key Bindings</guilabel> page.
</para>
<para>
The GNOME Desktop itself also has <ulink url="http://library.gnome.org/users/user-guide/stable/shortcuts-global.html.en">built in keyboard commands</ulink> to control the desktop and its applications.
</para>
<para>
WARNING: the MouseKeys functionality of AccessX can interfere with the <application>Orca</application> modifier key (see <ulink url="http://bugzilla.gnome.org/show_bug.cgi?id=548169">bug 548169</ulink>), resulting in odd behavior. In particular, MouseKeys uses the <keycap>KP_Insert</keycap> key to emulate a mouse button press. When enabled, MouseKeys can conflict with <keycap>KP_Insert</keycap> as the <application>Orca</application> modifier, resulting in what appears to be a stuck <application>Orca</application> modifier key.  As an alternative, you can use the <link linkend="orca-laptop-keys">laptop key bindings</link>, which avoids the keypad for <application>Orca</application> commands. If you accidentally enabled MouseKeys, you can disable it via the <application>gnome-keyboard-properties</application> application.
</para>
</note>

<section id="orca-desktop-keys">
<title>Desktop Layout</title>
<para>
Following is a list of common <application>Orca</application> keyboard commands for desktop keyboards arranged by category:
</para>

<section>
<title>Flat review commands</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycap>Numpad-7</keycap> - move the flat review cursor to the previous line and read it.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycap>Numpad-8</keycap> - read the current line.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycap>Numpad-9</keycap> - move the flat review cursor to the next line and read it.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycap>Numpad-4</keycap> - move the flat review cursor to the previous word and read it.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycap>Numpad-5</keycap> - read the current word.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycap>Numpad-6</keycap> - move the flat review cursor to the next word and read it.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycap>Numpad-1</keycap> - move the flat review cursor to the previous character and read it.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycap>Numpad-2</keycap> - read the current character.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycap>Numpad-3</keycap> - move the flat review cursor to the next character and read it.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycap>Numpad-slash</keycap> - perform a left mouse click at the location of the flat review cursor.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycap>Numpad-star</keycap> - perform a right mouse click at the location of the flat review cursor.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycap>Numpad-minus</keycap> - toggle between flat review and focus tracking mode.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<note>
<para>
The above commands apply when working with objects as well as when working with text.  For example, if the flat review cursor were positioned on a menu bar, pressing the "read current line" command would speak the names of all visible menus. Similarly, pressing the "read next word" command would speak the object to the right of the flat review cursor on the same line, or move flat review to the next line if no more objects were found.
</para>
</note>
</section>

<section>
<title>Bookmark commands</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>[1-6]</keycap></keycombo> - assign a bookmark to a numbered slot. If a bookmark already exists in the slot it will be replaced with the new one. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>[1-6]</keycap></keycombo> - go to the position pointed to by the bookmark bound to this numbered slot.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>[1-6]</keycap></keycombo> -  "Where am I" information for this bookmark relative to the current pointer location.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>B</keycap></keycombo> and <keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>B</keycap></keycombo> - move between the given bookmarks for the given application or page. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>B</keycap></keycombo> - save the defined bookmarks for the current application or page.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section>
<title>Miscellaneous functions</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Numpad</keycap><keycap>Plus</keycap></keycombo> - "say all" command; reads from the current position of the caret to the end of the document. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Numpad</keycap><keycap>Enter</keycap></keycombo> - "Where am I" command; speaks information such as the title of the current application window, as well as the name of the control that currently has focus. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>H</keycap></keycombo> - enter into <application>Orca</application>'s "learn mode"; press <keycap>Escape</keycap> to exit. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>F</keycap></keycombo> - speak font and attribute information for the current character. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo> - Launch the <application>Orca</application> Configuration dialog. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo> - reload user settings and reinitialize services as necessary. Also launches the <application>Orca</application> Configuration dialog for the current application.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>S</keycap></keycombo> - toggle speech on and off.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>F11</keycap></keycombo> - toggle the reading of tables, either by single cell or whole row.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo> - quit <application>Orca</application>.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section>
<title>Commands for debugging</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Home</keycap></keycombo> - report information on the currently active script. 
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<note>
<para>
In order for the next three commands to be of use, <application>Orca</application> needs to be started from a virtual console or via gnome-terminal. Output is sent to the console only (i.e., it is not sent to speech or braille).
</para>
</note>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>End</keycap></keycombo> - print a debug listing of all known applications to the console where <application>Orca</application> is running. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Page_Up</keycap></keycombo> - print debug information about the ancestry of the object with focus. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Page_Down</keycap></keycombo> - print debug information about the hierarchy of the application with focus. 
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</section>

<section id="orca-laptop-keys">
<title>Laptop Layout</title>
<para>
Following is a list of common <application>Orca</application> keyboard commands for laptop keyboards arranged by category:
</para>

<section>
<title>Flat review commands</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>U</keycap></keycombo> - move the flat review cursor to the previous line and read it.
Double-click to move flat review to the top of the current window.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>I</keycap></keycombo> - read the current line.
Double-click to read the current line along with formatting and capitalization details.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>O</keycap></keycombo> - move the flat review cursor to the next line and read it. Double- click to move flat review to the bottom of the current window.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>J</keycap></keycombo> - move the flat review cursor to the previous word and read it.
Double-click to move flat review to the word above the current word.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>K</keycap></keycombo> - read the current word.
Double-click to spell the word. Triple-click  to hear the word spelled phonetically.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>L</keycap></keycombo> - move the flat review cursor to the next word and read it. Double- click to move flat review to the word below the current word.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>M</keycap></keycombo> - move the flat review cursor to the previous character and read it.
Double-click to move flat review to the end of the current line.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>Comma</keycap></keycombo> - read the current character. Double-click to pronounce the character phonetically if it is a letter.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>Period</keycap></keycombo> - move the flat review cursor to the next character and read it.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>7</keycap></keycombo> - perform a left mouse click at the location of the flat review cursor.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>8</keycap></keycombo> - perform a right mouse click at the location of the flat review cursor.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>8</keycap></keycombo> - perform a right mouse click at the location of the flat review cursor.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>p</keycap></keycombo> - toggle between flat review and focus tracking mode.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<note>
<para>
The above commands apply when working with objects as well as when working with text.  For example, if the flat review cursor were positioned on a menu bar, pressing the "read current line" command would speak the names of all visible menus. Similarly, pressing the "read next word" command would speak the object to the right of the flat review cursor on the same line, or move flat review to the next line if no more objects were found.
</para>
</note>
</section>

<section>
<title>Bookmark commands</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>[1-6]</keycap></keycombo> - add a bookmark to the numbered slot. If a bookmark already exists for the slot it will be replaced with the new one.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>[1-6]</keycap></keycombo> - go to the position pointed to by the bookmark bound to this numbered slot.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>[1-6]</keycap></keycombo> - "Where am I" information for this bookmark relative to the current pointer location.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>B</keycap></keycombo>and <keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>B</keycap></keycombo> - move between the given bookmarks for the given application or page.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>B</keycap></keycombo> - save the defined bookmarks for the current application or page.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section>
<title>Miscellaneous functions</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>Semicolon</keycap></keycombo> - "Say all" command; reads from the current position of the caret to the end of the document.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>Enter</keycap></keycombo> - "Where am I" command; speaks information such as the title of the current application window, as well as the name of the control that currently has focus.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>H</keycap></keycombo> - enter learn mode (press <keycap>Escape</keycap> to exit).
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>F</keycap></keycombo> - speak font and attribute information for the current character.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo> - launch the <application>Orca</application> Configuration dialog.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo> - reload user settings and reinitialize services as necessary; also  launches the <application>Orca</application> Configuration dialog for the current application.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>S</keycap></keycombo> - toggle speech on and off.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>F11</keycap></keycombo> - toggle the reading of tables, either by single cell or whole row.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>Q</keycap></keycombo> - quit <application>Orca</application>.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section>
<title>Commands for debugging</title>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Home</keycap></keycombo> - report information on the currently active script.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<note>
<para>
In order for the next three commands to be of use, <application>Orca</application> needs to be started from a virtual console or via <application>gnome-terminal</application>. Output is sent to the console only (i.e., 
it is not sent to speech or braille).
</para>
</note>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>End</keycap></keycombo> - prints a debug listing of all known applications to the console where <application>Orca</application> is running.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Page_Up</keycap></keycombo> - prints debug information about the ancestry of the object with focus.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<keycombo><keycap>Caps_Lock</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Page_Down</keycap></keycombo> - prints debug information about the object hierarchy of the application with focus.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</section>

</section>
<section>
<title>Application-Specific Information</title>
<section>
<title>Accessible Applications</title>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> is designed to work with applications and toolkits that support the Assistive Technology Service Provider Interface (AT-SPI). This includes the GNOME Desktop and its bundled applications: OpenOffice, Firefox, and the Java platform. Some applications work better than others, however, and the <application>Orca</application> community continually works to provide superior access to more and more applications.
</para>
</section>

<!--
<section>
<title>Using Adobe's Acrobat Reader</title>
<para>
We are currently working on a script for Adobe's Acrobat Reader, and the initial version has been contributed to <application>Orca</application> v2.17.5. Note that there is still work to do, and we are very encouraged by Adobe's commitment to accessibility.
</para>

<section>
<title>Installation</title>
<para>
If you get Adobe Acrobat Reader directly from the <ulink url='http://www.adobe.com/products/acrobat/readstep2.html'>Adobe site</ulink>, you may find that the software will not launch. If launched from the Applications menu, it may appear that nothing has happened, or if launched from a terminal window you may receive a long series of syntax error messages. Should this occur, you will need to edit your /usr/bin/acroread file as described in this <ulink url='http://ubuntuforums.org/showthread.php?t=233514'>Ubuntu forum thread</ulink>.
</para>
<para>
If you instead choose to install Acrobat Reader from your distribution's packages, be sure to install both <application>acroread</application> and <application>acroread-plugins</application>. Without the plugins package, you will not have the access to the "Reading" category in the <menuchoice>
<guimenuitem>Edit-</guimenuitem>
<guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
</menuchoice> dialog.
</para>
<para>
Note: If you use Ubuntu and cannot locate the
<application>acroread</application> package, you will likely need to edit your /etc/apt/sources.list to include the 'multiverse' repository. Then run <userinput>apt-get update</userinput>. Having done so, you should then be able to install both <application>acroread</application> and <application>acroread-plugins</application>.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Enabling Accessibility and Caret Navigation</title>
<para>
Once you've installed Reader, you need to enable accessibility:
</para>
<orderedlist numeration='arabic'>
<listitem>
<para>
In the "Accessibility" tab of the 
<menuchoice>
<guimenuitem>Edit-</guimenuitem>
<guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
</menuchoice> dialog, make sure 
<guilabel>Always display the keyboard selection cursor</guilabel> (<keycombo>
<keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>D</keycap>
</keycombo>) is checked.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
In the "Reading" tab of the 
<menuchoice>
<guimenuitem>Edit-</guimenuitem>
<guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
</menuchoice> dialog, make sure
<guilabel>Enable Document Accessibility
</guilabel> ((<keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>E</keycap></keycombo>) is checked.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section>
<title>Working with Untagged Documents</title>
<para>
When you open an untagged document, you will be presented with a dialog box asking you to specify the reading order and the reading mode options. The default reading order is 
<guilabel>Infer reading order from document
</guilabel>. This setting works well for most documents.
</para>
<para>
The default reading mode will vary depending on the length of the document; for short documents, the default is <guilabel>Read the entire document</guilabel>; for long documents the default is <guilabel>Read currently visible pages only</guilabel>. <application>Orca</application> tends to work better when <guilabel>Read the entire document</guilabel> is selected.
</para>
<para>
If you find that a document seems to be missing parts of the text, try changing the reading options. To do so, get into the Document menu and select <guilabel>Change Accessibility Reading Options...</guilabel> or use the shortcut <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>5</keycap></keycombo>.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Page Layout</title>
<para>
The best page layout for reading a document with <application>Orca</application> is <guilabel>Single Page</guilabel>. When <guilabel>Continuous</guilabel> is chosen, moving focus to text as the page is scrolling 
can cause that text not to be read. You can change the page layout to <guilabel>Single Page</guilabel> by getting into the View menu and selecting the Page Layout submenu.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Navigating Tables</title>
<para>
As far as we know there isn't currently a whole lot of keyboard support for tables in
<application>Acrobat Reader</application>. We hope Adobe will remedy this soon.
</para>
<para>
Basically, there are the arrow keys. Their behavior is to move you first within the cell with focus, then to the next cell with data in it. Note that currently, Up and Down Arrow do not seem to move you vertically among cells - at least that has been the experience 
with the tables we have tried. Instead, Up and Down seem to move you horizontally until you run out of cells on the current row.
</para>
</section>
</section>
-->

<section>
<title>Making Application-Specific Settings</title>
<para>
To customize the settings for a particular application, you will first need to run that application. Make sure the application has focus, then press <keycombo><keycap>Orca_Modifier</keycap>
<keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Space</keycap>
</keycombo> (by default, this will be 
<keycombo><keycap>Insert</keycap><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Space</keycap></keycombo> for the Desktop keyboard layout).
</para>
<para>
This brings up a tabbed dialog window very similar to the <application>Orca</application> configuration dialog, but with the following differences:
</para>
<orderedlist numeration="arabic">
<listitem>
<para>
There is no initial General pane.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
The Speech System and Speech Synthesizer combo
boxes on the Speech pane will be grayed out (made inactive).
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Any existing application-specific key bindings will appear at the top of the list on the Key Bindings pane.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
There may be a new application-specific settings pane at the end of the set of tabbed panes. Note that pressing the End key from the tab list will get you directly to the right-most tab.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
Adjust your application-specific settings in the same way you set your general <application>Orca</application> preferences.
For example, you may have Key Echo disabled generally in <application>Orca</application> but would like to specifically have it enabled for the <application>gcalctool</application> (GNOME Calculator) application. Here's where you could easily set that.
</para>
<para>
When you have your application settings customized the way you want, press the <guilabel>OK</guilabel> button. These settings will be written to your 
<userinput>~/.orca/app-settings</userinput> directory in a file called 
<userinput>&lt;APPNAME&gt;.py</userinput>, where <userinput>&lt;APPNAME&gt;</userinput> is the name of the application.
</para>
<para>
These files are automatically written by <application>Orca</application>. The contents of the file will be overwritten each time you change your application settings for that
application.
</para>
<para>
If you want to have some extra application-specific settings or code that you don't want to lose, then you should put it in a file called <userinput>~/.orca/app-settings/&lt;APPNAME&gt;-customizations.py</userinput>. This file will be automatically read when the settings for the 
<userinput>&lt;APPNAME&gt;</userinput> application are loaded.
</para>
<para>
Note that this is an advanced feature that we don't expect many people to use. It's just there if you really want it.
</para>
<para>
There is currently one known bug (some people would call it a feature) that we are trying to track down and fix:
</para>
<note>
<para>
If you adjust one or more application-specific key bindings, the new values will not take effect until you've pressed the <guilabel>OK</guilabel> button. The work-around is to either restart <application>Orca</application>, or Alt-Tab 
away to some other application and then Alt-Tab back to the one that you've just changed the key bindings for.
</para>
</note>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Braille</title>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> uses 
<ulink url="http://mielke.cc/brltty/">BrlTTY</ulink> for braille support. On Linux systems, BrlTTY is used to access the text mode console content. On a typical braille-enabled installation of Linux, BrlTTY is already running and providing access to the text consoles. When Orca starts, it connects to BrlTTY. If you switch from a text console to your X Windows session, your braille display will automatically follow and display the content that Orca is presenting to you.
</para>
<para>
<application>Orca</application> attempts to work with various releases of BrlTTY. It works well with BrlTTY v3.7.2, and we've also been working with the BrlTTY team to get it going for BrlTTY v3.8. The remainder of this document provides information related to using <application>Orca</application> with <application>BrlTTY</application> 3.8.
</para>

<para>
Below are descriptions of the necessary tasks to install/setup BrlTTY in Ubuntu and Solaris. For both, you need to first obtain 
<ulink url="http://mielke.cc/brltty/releases/ brltty-3.8.tar.gz">brltty-3.8.tar.gz</ulink> from the BrlTTY site.
</para>

<section>
<title>BrlTTY 3.8 on Ubuntu</title>
<para>
First, configure your build environment to build BrlTTY. Much of this setup is done for you automatically in the Ubuntu distribution with products such as G++ already present. In addition, <emphasis>you must</emphasis> 
also install tcl, Pyrex, and the Python developer environment. To do this, execute the following commands as <userinput>root</userinput>:
</para>
<para/>
<screen>
<![CDATA[apt-get build-dep brltty
apt-get install tcl8.4 python-pyrex python-dev
]]>
</screen>
<para>
Then, when you build BrlTTY, avoid configuring the package with --prefix=/usr. Use the standard procedure instead, executing the following commands as <userinput>root</userinput>:
</para>
<para/>
<screen>
<![CDATA[gunzip -c brltty-3.8.tar.gz | tar xvf -
cd brltty-3.8
./autogen
./configure
make
make install
]]>
</screen>
<para>
Run BrlTTY as <userinput>root</userinput>:
</para>
<para/>
<screen>
<![CDATA[/bin/brltty -bauto -d/dev/ttyUSB0
]]>
</screen>
<para>
If you want, you can remove the existing 
<userinput>/sbin/brltty</userinput> and replace it with the <userinput>/bin/brltty</userinput>, either by copying the <userinput>/bin/brltty</userinput> to <userinput>/sbin/brltty</userinput> or just by making a 
symbolic link. Do so at your own risk.
</para>
<para/>
</section>
</section>

<section>
<title>Troubleshooting</title>
<section>
<title>My desktop has stopped responding. What do I do?
</title>
<para>
Press <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo> or <keycombo><keycap>Meta</keycap><keycap>R</keycap></keycombo> to open the Run dialog and restart <application>Orca</application> by running a new instance: type <userinput>orca</userinput> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>. This will force any existing <application>Orca</application> processes to exit and will then restart <application>Orca</application>. This 
sometimes has the effect of unhanging the desktop (which is usually due to an ill-behaved application).
</para>
<para>
If you cannot get to a terminal window, try 
pressing <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap>
<keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Backspace</keycap>
</keycombo>: shut down the X Window System server. This should return you to the login screen.
</para>
</section>
</section>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter id="ats-1">
<title>Mobility Impairments</title>
<para>
Mobility impairments can be caused by arthritis, stroke, cerebral palsy, Parkinson's disease, multiple sclerosis, and loss of limbs or digits, among others. Poor muscle control or weakness can make using standard keyboards and mouse devices difficult. For instance, some people are unable to type two keys simultaneously, while others tend to hit multiple keys or to bounce keys when pressing or releasing them. People who are able to use only one hand likewise have difficulties with some keyboard and mouse tasks. 
</para>
<para>
The technologies which can assist those with mobility impairments are:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis>On-Screen Keyboard</emphasis> 
 - lets users select keys using a pointing method such as pointing devices, switches, or Morse-code input systems.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Mouse and Keyboard Enhancements
</emphasis> - helpful for users who have trouble typing and controlling a mouse or a keyboard.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<section id="gok">
<title>GNOME On-Screen Keyboard (gok)</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>On-Screen Keyboard</primary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>GOK</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The <application>On-Screen Keyboard</application> application displays virtual keyboards on your desktop. You can use the standard mouse pointer or alternative pointing device to operate the virtual keyboards. <application>On-Screen Keyboard</application> displays the following types of keyboards:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Composer Keyboards enable you to compose text. To type alphanumeric characters, you select the characters on the composer keyboard.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Dynamic Keyboards reflect the applications 
that are currently running on the desktop. For example, <application>On-Screen Keyboard</application> generates dynamic keyboards that contain keys to represent the applications that are running on your desktop or the menus that are contained in an application. 
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>多くの利用可能なアクセシビリティツールを利用する前に、支援技術サービスを有効にしなければいけません。</para>
<procedure>
<step>
<para><menuchoice><guimenuitem>システム</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>設定</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>支援技術</guimenuitem></menuchoice>を選択してください。</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Select <guilabel>Enable assistive technologies
</guilabel> and then press <guibutton>Close and Log Out</guibutton>.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>再度ログインすると、支援技術サービスは自動的に開始します</para>
</step>
</procedure>

<!--
<para>
For more information about the 
<application>On-Screen Keyboard</application> application, see the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:gok"> Help for <application>On-Screen Keyboard</application></ulink>.
</para>
<-->
</section>

<section id="ats-5">
<title>Maximizing Application Windows for On-Screen Keyboard Users
</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>maximizing Terminal On-Screen Keyboard</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
If you are an <application>On-Screen Keyboard
</application> user, you cannot use any application in Full-Screen mode because the application window obscures the <application>On-Screen Keyboard</application> display.
</para>
<para>
To resize the window for use with the 
<application>On-Screen Keyboard</application> 
application, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Do not enable the Full-Screen mode in the application.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Give focus to the application window.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Press <keycap>F10</keycap> to maximize the application.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section id="dtconfig-0">
<title>Mouse and Keyboard Enhancements</title>
<para>
This section describes how to configure the mouse and keyboard to make these devices accessible to more users.
</para>

<section id="dtconfig-1">
<title>Configuring the Mouse</title>
<para>
Use the <guilabel>Mouse</guilabel> preference tool to configure the mouse to suit your needs. To open the <guilabel>Mouse</guilabel> preference tool, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Mouse
</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The <guilabel>
Mouse Preferences</guilabel> dialog is displayed.
</para>

<section id="dtconfig-2">
<title>Configuring Mouse Behavior</title>
<para>
The following sections describe how to modify the behavior of the mouse to suit your needs. 
</para>

<section id="dtconfig-3">
<title>Configuring the Mouse for Left-Handed Use</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>mouse</primary>
<secondary>left hand</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
To configure the mouse for left-handed use, click on the <guilabel>Buttons</guilabel> tab in the <guilabel>Mouse Preferences</guilabel> dialog, then select the <guilabel>Left-handed mouse</guilabel> option. When you select
this option, the system swaps the functions of the left mouse button and the right mouse button immediately.
</para>
</section>

<section id="dtconfig-4">
<title>Configuring Double-Click Behavior</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>mouse</primary>
<secondary>double-click behavior</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
If you have difficulty double-clicking, you can increase the period of time that the system allows to elapse between the first click and the second click of a double-click. For example, if the double-click timeout
setting is 0.4 seconds, you must perform the second click of a double-click within 0.4 seconds of the first click. If the second click occurs more than 0.4 seconds after the first click, the system interprets the two clicks as two single clicks. 
</para>
<para>
To configure the double-click timeout setting, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guilabel>Buttons</guilabel> tab in the <guilabel>Mouse Preferences</guilabel> dialog.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the <guilabel>Timeout</guilabel> slider to specify the timeout in seconds that the system allows between the two clicks of a double-click. Moving the slider to the right will increase the timeout interval in 0.1 
second intervals. In the same manner, moving the slider to the left will decrease the timeout in 0.1 second intervals.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Double-click on the light bulb to the right of the slider to test the setting. If you perform the two clicks of the double-click within the timeout specified, the light bulb lights up fully to display a yellow glow around the bulb. If you do not double-click 
within the timeout specified, the light bulb does not light fully. You should increase the timeout setting and try again. When the light bulb lights, the timeout setting is suitable for your needs. 
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section id="dtconfig-20">
<title>Changing Mouse Pointer Size</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>mouse</primary>
<secondary>pointer size</secondary>
</indexterm>
<indexterm>
<primary>pointer</primary>
<secondary>size</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
To change the size of the mouse pointer that is displayed on the desktop, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guilabel>Pointers</guilabel> tab in the <guilabel>Mouse Preferences</guilabel> dialog. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
This will display a list of pointer themes and sizes available.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
By default, GNOME does not include mouse pointer themes. Information about installing and using pointer themes can be found in the <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide?goscustdesk-54">User Guide</ulink>.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<note>
<para>
On some platforms you must log out and log in again for this setting to take effect.
</para>
</note>
</section>

<section id="dtconfig-6">
<title>Locating the Mouse Pointer</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>mouse</primary>
<secondary>locating pointer</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
If you have difficulty locating the mouse pointer on the screen, you can enable an option to highlight the pointer when you press the <keycap>Control</keycap> 
key. To enable this option, click on the <guilabel>Pointers</guilabel> tab in the <guilabel>Mouse Preferences</guilabel> dialog, then select the <guilabel>Highlight the pointer when you press Ctrl</guilabel>
option. When you press <keycap>Control</keycap>, the system displays an animation around the pointer to highlight the pointer. 
</para>
<note>
<para>
On some platforms, you must log out and log in again before this setting takes effect.
</para>
</note>
</section>

<section id="dtconfig-5">
<title>Configuring Mouse Speed and Sensitivity</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>mouse</primary>
<secondary>speed and sensitivity</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
To configure the speed and sensitivity of the mouse, perform the following steps: 
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guilabel>Motion</guilabel> tab in the <guilabel>Mouse Preferences</guilabel> dialog. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Configure the following options:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>Acceleration</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the slider to specify the speed at which the mouse pointer moves around the screen when you move the mouse.
</para>
<para>
If you select a low setting, the mouse pointer moves at a speed similar to the speed at which you are physically moving the mouse. This means that you need to physically move the mouse larger distances to cover the screen
area. If you select a high setting, the mouse pointer moves at a faster speed than the speed at which you physically move the mouse. This means that you need to physically move the mouse small distances to cover the screen area.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Sensitivity</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the slider to specify how responsive the mouse pointer is to movements of the mouse. Moving the slider to the right will increase the sensitivity and moving it to the left will decrease the sensitivity.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Threshold</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the slider to specify the distance that you must move an item before the system interprets the move action as a drag-and-drop action.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
</section>

<section id="dtconfig-7">
<title>Configuring the Cursor</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>cursor</primary>
<secondary>stop blinking</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The following section describes how to modify the display characteristics of the cursor. 
</para>

<section id="dtconfig-9">
<title>Stopping the Cursor from Blinking</title>
<para>
To stop the cursor from blinking in text boxes and other areas, perform the following steps: 
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu>
<guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Keyboard</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to start the 
<application>Keyboard</application> preference tool.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
In the <guilabel>Keyboard</guilabel> tabbed section, deselect the <guilabel>Cursor blinks in text boxes and fields</guilabel> option.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
</section>

<section id="dtconfig-10">
<title>Keyboard Mouse Emulation</title>
<para>
If you have difficulty using a mouse, you can use the keyboard to emulate the mouse functions. See <xref linkend="dtconfig-14"/> of this guide for more information.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="dtconfig-14">
<title>Configuring an Accessible Keyboard</title>
<para>
Use the <application>Keyboard</application> preference tool to configure the keyboard accessibility options. To open the <application>Keyboard</application> 
preference tool, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System
</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu>
<guimenuitem>Keyboard</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Accessibility options can be enabled by selecting the <guilabel>Accessibility</guilabel> tab.
</para>
<para>
The <guilabel>Accessibility</guilabel> tabbed section allows the following options:
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>"Allow to turn accessibility features on and off from the keyboard" (Alt-A)</emphasis> - this determines if keyboard accessibility functions can be turned on or off with a key command.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Simulate simultaneous keypresses (Alt-S)</emphasis> - allows multiple shift (or other) keys to be entered individually but processed as a single combination keystroke. This keyboard accessibility technique is known as "sticky keys."
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Disable sticky keys if two keys are pressed together (Alt-B)</emphasis> - automatically exit the sticky keys mode if any key combination is entered normally (eq, at the same time instead of entered individually).
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Only accept long keypresses (Alt-O)</emphasis> - in this mode, keys must be pressed for a given length of time before they are accepted as input. This accessibility technique is also known as "slow keys." This portion of the <guilabel>Accessibility</guilabel> tabbed section also supplies a Delay slider (Alt-D) to indicate the press-down delay before the key is accepted as input.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Ignore fast duplicate keypresses (Alt-I)</emphasis> - in this mode, successive entry of the same key will only have a single instance of that key accepted as input. This accessibility technique is also known as "bounce keys." This portion of the <guilabel>Accessibility</guilabel> tabbed section also supplies a Delay slider (Alt-E) to indicate the press-down delay before successive keys are ignored.
</para>
</section>

<section id="dtconfig-mousekeys">
<title>Configuring a Keyboard-Based Mouse</title>
<para>
Use the <application>Keyboard</application> preference tool to configure the keyboard to simulate a mouse. To open the <application>Keyboard</application> 
preference tool, choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System
</guimenu><guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu>
<guimenuitem>Keyboard</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. The Mouse Keys options can be enabled by selecting the <guilabel>Mouse Keys</guilabel> tab.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>"Allow to control the pointer using the keyboard" (Alt-A)</emphasis> - this determines if the keyboard can be used to control the mouse pointer.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Acceleration (Alt-C)</emphasis> - determines how quickly mouse motion will accelerate when keyboard directional keys are 
pressed.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Speed (Alt-S)</emphasis> - determines how quickly the mouse pointer will move when keyboard directional keys are pressed.
</para>
<para>
<emphasis>Delay (Alt-D)</emphasis> - determines how much (or if) keypresses may be dampened or ignored when keyboard directional keys are pressed.
</para>
</section>

<section id="mousetweaks">
<title>MouseTweaks</title>
<para>
<application>MouseTweaks</application> is a collection of accessibility enhancements for pointing devices. The <userinput>mousetweaks</userinput> package provides the functions offered by the <guilabel>Accessibility</guilabel> tab of the <guilabel>Mouse</guilabel> preference tool. It also contains two panel applets related to the mouse accessibility. More particularly:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
It allows users to perform a secondary click by doing a click-and-hold of the primary mouse button.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
It offers a way to perform the various clicks without using any hardware button. In this context, the <application>Dwell Click</application> panel applet can be used to choose what click type to perform.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
It provides the <application>Pointer Capture</application> panel applet. This applet creates an area on the panel into which the pointer can be captured until the user releases it with a predefined button and modifier combination.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
Most mouse-related accessibility options can be found by using <menuchoice><guimenuitem>System</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Mouse</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and selecting the <guilabel>Accessibility</guilabel> tab. Two additional panel applets can optionally be added to the GNOME menu bar / system panel as well; see the sections below. The full manual can be viewed by selecting the <guilabel>Help</guilabel> item from the contextual menu of the <application>Dwell Click</application> applet.
</para>

<!--
<para>
yelp mousetweaks(1) - <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:user-guide?mousetweaks">full manual</ulink>
</para>
-->

<section>
<title>Simulated Secondary Click</title>
<para>
A secondary or right-click can be issued by using the primary button and keeping it held down for a specified delay.
</para> 
</section>

<section>
<title>Dwell Click</title>
<para>
A click can be issued by having the mouse pointer dwell in a given spot for a specified delay. In this mode, the click-type is determined by the <guilabel>ClickType</guilabel> window, <application>Dwell Click</application> applet, or by the direction in which the user moves the mouse after the dwell time has elapsed. The click-type can be single, double, drag or right.
</para>
<para>
The <application>Dwell Click</application> panel applet can be installed by right-clicking the GNOME Desktop menu bar / system panel, selecting <guilabel>Add to Panel</guilabel>, choosing <application>Dwell Click</application> and clicking the <guilabel>Add</guilabel> button.
</para>
</section>

<section>
<title>Pointer Capture</title>
<para>
The mouse pointer can be locked into an area of the screen so the pointing device is free for other tasks. For example, this capability allows a powerchair user to control both the powerchair and the mouse pointer with a single powerchair joystick.
</para>
<para>
The <application>Pointer Capture</application> panel applet creates such an area on the panel, into which the user can lock the pointer until released in a determined way.
</para>

<para>
The <application>Pointer Capture</application> panel applet can be installed by right-clicking the GNOME Desktop menu bar / system panel, selecting <guilabel>Add to Panel</guilabel>, choosing <application>Pointer Capture</application> and clicking the <guilabel>Add</guilabel> button.
</para>
<para>
Preferences may be set by choosing <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> in the context menu of the <application>Pointer Capture</application> applet:
</para>
<para>
In the <guilabel>Capture Pointer</guilabel> section, the user can specify under what circumstances the pointer gets captured when it moves into the capture area. For example, if the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> modifier key is checked, the pointer gets captured when it is over the capture area and the user presses the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> modifier key. If no modifier is checked and the mouse button is set to 0, the pointer only has to move into the capture area to get locked. It is also possible to specify a combination of modifiers and mouse button.
</para>
<para>
In the <guilabel>Release Pointer</guilabel> section, the user can specify what modifier or mouse button releases the pointer. It is also possible to specify a combination of modifiers and mouse button.
</para>
<para>
In the <guilabel>Size of Capture Area</guilabel> section, the user can specify the width of the capture area on the GNOME panel.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="enable-dasher">
<title>Dasher</title>
<para>
Dasher is an information-efficient text-entry interface, driven by natural continuous pointing gestures. Dasher is a competitive text-entry system wherever a full-size keyboard cannot be used - for example on a palmtop or wearable computer, or when operating any computer one-handed (by joystick, touchscreen or mouse) or zero-handed (eg, by head-mouse or eye-tracker).
</para>
<procedure>
<step>
<para>
Choose <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Accessories</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Terminal</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Enter: <userinput>sudo apt-get install dasher
</userinput>
</para>
</step>
<step>
<para>
Enter: <userinput>dasher</userinput>
</para>
</step>
</procedure>
<para>
Dasher may also be installed from the <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Add/Remove</guimenuitem></menuchoice> dialog. In either case, it may later be launched in these ways:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Press <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap>
<keycap>F2</keycap></keycombo> or <keycombo><keycap>Meta</keycap>
<keycap>R</keycap></keycombo> for the <emphasis>Run</emphasis> dialog, type <userinput>dasher</userinput> and press <keycap>Enter</keycap>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Choose <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Accessories</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Terminal</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and execute <userinput>dasher</userinput>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Press <keycap>Alt-F1</keycap> and select <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Applications</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Universal Access</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Dasher</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<!--
<listitem>
<para>
Using the numeric keypad to emulate mouse actions. See <xref linkend="dtconfig-14"/>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Specifying the duration for which you must press and hold a key before the system accepts the keypress. See <xref linkend="dtconfig-15"/>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Ignoring rapid, repeated keypresses of the same key. See <xref linkend="dtconfig-16"/>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Accepting key combinations in sequence rather than simultaneously. See <xref linkend="dtconfig-17"/>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Emitting an audible notification when a user activates or deactivates a toggle key. See <xref linkend="dtconfig-18"/>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Ignoring long keypresses of the same key and control the repeat rate of a keypress. See <xref linkend="dtconfig-19"/>.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<section id="dtconfig-13">
<title>Activating Keyboard Accessibility Options</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>keyboard accessibility options</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
To activate the keyboard accessibility options, perform the following steps: 
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Choose <menuchoice><guimenu>System</guimenu>
<guisubmenu>Preferences</guisubmenu><guimenuitem>Keyboard</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and select 
<guilabel>Accessibility</guilabel>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the <guilabel>Enable keyboard accessibility features</guilabel> option.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Click on the <guilabel>Basic</guilabel> tab.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the <guilabel>Beep when features turned on or off from keyboard</guilabel> option to receive an audible notification each time a keyboard accessibility option changes; to toggle these settings, use the 
following keyboard shortcuts:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Press and hold <keycap>Shift</keycap> for eight seconds to enable or disable the Slow Keys feature. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Press <keycap>Shift</keycap> five times to enable or disable the Sticky Keys feature.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
To automatically disable the keyboard accessibility options if the options are not used for a specified number of seconds, select the <guilabel>Disable if unused for X seconds</guilabel> option. Use the slider 
to specify the number of seconds of keyboard idle time required before the system disables the keyboard accessibility options. 
</para>
<para>
This option is intended for computers that are shared by a number of different users, some of whom require the keyboard accessibility options. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Changes made will be instantly applied.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section id="dtconfig-14">
<title>Enabling Mouse Emulation</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>mouse keys</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The mouse keys feature enables you to use the numeric keypad on the keyboard to emulate mouse actions. This feature benefits users who have difficulty using a mouse or other pointing device. To enable and configure the mouse keys feature, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
In the <application>Keyboard Accessibility Preferences (AccessX)</application> dialog, select the <guilabel>Mouse Keys</guilabel> tab.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the <guilabel>Enable Mouse Keys</guilabel> option.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Configure the following options to determine the behavior of the mouse pointer when you control the pointer from the numeric keypad:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<guilabel>Maximum Pointer Speed</guilabel>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Use this spin box to specify the maximum speed in pixels per second at which the pointer moves around the screen.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<guilabel>Elapsed Time before Maximum Mouse Speed
</guilabel>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Use this spin box to specify the duration in 
milliseconds before the pointer accelerates to the maximum pointer speed. 
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<guilabel>Delay between Keypress and Pointer Movement
</guilabel>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Use this spin box to specify the interval
in milliseconds between a keypress and the time when the pointer starts to move. 
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
When you enable mouse keys, the keys on the numeric keypad have the following functions:
</para>
<table frame="topbot" id="dtconfig-TBL-1">
<title>Numeric Keypad to Mouse Function Mapping</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="52.78*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="47.22*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry>
<para>Numeric Keypad Keys</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Function</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
1, 2, 3, 4, 6, 7, 8, 9
</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Move the mouse pointer around the screen
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>5</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Mouse button click
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>0</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Mouse button toggle
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>/</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>
Primary mouse button
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>*</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Secondary mouse button
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>-</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>
Tertiary mouse button
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>
The Toggle Mouse Button key enables the currently selected mouse button until the <guilabel>Mouse button click</guilabel> key is pressed. This allows you to perform drag and drop operations.
</para>
<para>
The <guilabel>Mouse button click</guilabel> emulates the currently selected mouse button. Pressing <keycap>/</keycap>, <keycap>*</keycap> or <keycap>-</keycap> will change the behaviour of this. The currently selected mouse button can be seen in the <application>Keyboard Accessibility Status
</application> panel application, discussed in <xref linkend="dtconfig-21"/>.
</para>
<note>
<para>
The <guilabel>Primary mouse button</guilabel> is the left mouse button for right-handed people. The <guilabel>Secondary mouse button</guilabel> is the right mouse button and the <guilabel>Tertiary mouse button</guilabel> is the middle mouse button.
</para>
</note>
<para>
Some Solaris systems also use the function keys to emulate the mouse buttons. The 
function-key-to-mouse-button mappings are described in the following table:
</para>
<table frame="topbot" id="dtconfig-TBL-2">
<title>F-Key to Mouse Action Mapping on Solaris Systems</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="52.78*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="47.22*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry>
<para>Function Key</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Function</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>F2</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Mouse button 1</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>F3</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>Mouse button 2</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>F4</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>Mouse button 3</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>

<section id="dtconfig-15">
<title>Enabling Slow Keys</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>slow keys</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The slow keys feature enables you to customize how the keyboard handles user input in the following ways:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Specify the duration for which you must press and hold a key before the system accepts the keypress. This aspect of the feature benefits users who frequently press keys that they do not intend to press. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Enable audible indications of keyboard input and acceptance. This aspect of the feature benefits users who cannot see the result of a keypress.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
To enable and configure the slow keys feature, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
From the <application>Keyboard Accessibility 
Preferences (AccessX)</application> dialog, select the <guilabel>Filters</guilabel> tab.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the <guilabel>Enable Slow Keys</guilabel> option.
</para>
<tip>
<para>
To select or deselect the Slow Keys feature from the keyboard, press and hold <keycap>Shift</keycap> for eight seconds. This will present a dialog confirming 
that you want Slow Keys enabled. The <keycap>Shift</keycap> keyboard shortcut automatically selects all of the Slow Keys options. If you selected the <guilabel>Beep when features turned on or off from the
keyboard</guilabel> option in the <guilabel>Basic</guilabel> tab, after four seconds the system beeps three times to indicate that the system is about to 
select or deselect the feature.
</para>
</tip>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the <guilabel>Only accept keys held for</guilabel> slider or spin box to specify the duration, in milliseconds, for which you must press and hold a key before the system accepts the keypress. Use the <guilabel>Type to test settings</guilabel> text box to 
test the Slow Keys setting and modify the setting as required. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
To enable audible indications of keyboard input and acceptance, select the following options:
</para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<guilabel>Beep when key is pressed</guilabel>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Select this option to hear a beep when you press a key.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<guilabel>Beep when key is accepted</guilabel>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Select this option to hear a beep when the system accepts a keypress. 
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<guilabel>Beep when key is rejected</guilabel>
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Select this option to hear a beep when the system rejects a keypress. The system rejects a keypress if you do not press and hold the key for the duration that is specified in the <guilabel>Only accept keys held for</guilabel> spin box.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section id="dtconfig-16">
<title>Enabling Bounce Keys</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>bounce keys</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The bounce keys feature enables you to customize the keyboard to ignore rapid, repeated keypresses of the same key. For example, users with impaired motor skills 
might press the same key several times when they intend to press the key once. This feature enables you to customize the keyboard to ignore repeated keypresses. 
</para>
<para>
To enable and configure the Bounce Keys feature, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
From the <application>Keyboard Accessibility Preferences (AccessX)</application> dialog, select the <guilabel>Filters</guilabel> tab.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the <guilabel>Enable Bounce Keys</guilabel> option. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the <guilabel>Ignore duplicate keypresses within</guilabel> slider or spin box to specify the duration in milliseconds (ms) after the first keypress for which the system ignores repeated keypresses of the same key. For example, if you select a duration of 500 ms, the system ignores all repeated keypresses of the same key that occur within half a second of the first keypress.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the <guilabel>Beep if key is rejected</guilabel> option to hear an audible indication when the system ignores a key.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<note>
<para>
If you want to enable the Bounce Keys feature, ensure that the <guilabel>Enable Slow Keys</guilabel> option is deselected. The Slow Keys feature requires you to press a key for a specified duration before the 
system accepts the keypress as a valid keypress. If you cannot press the key for the duration that is specified by the Slow Keys setting, deselect the <guilabel>Enable Slow Keys</guilabel> option to enable the system 
to accept your input.
</para>
</note>
</section>

<section id="dtconfig-17">
<title>Enabling Sticky Keys</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>sticky keys</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The sticky keys feature enables you to press  
key combinations in sequence rather than simultaneously. This feature is designed for users who are unable to press two or more keys at the same time. 
</para>
<para>
To enable and configure the Sticky Keys feature, perform the following steps:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
From the <application>Keyboard Accessibility 
Preferences (AccessX)</application> select the <guilabel>Basic</guilabel> tab.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the <guilabel>Enable Sticky Keys</guilabel> option.
</para>
<tip>
<para>
To enable the Sticky Keys feature from the keyboard, press <keycap>Shift</keycap> five times. This will present a dialog confirming that you with to enable Sticky Keys. The <keycap>Shift</keycap> keyboard shortcut automatically selects all of the Sticky Keys 
options. If you selected the <guilabel>Beep when features turned on or off from the keyboard</guilabel> option, the system beeps to indicate that the system is about to select or deselect the feature. When active, pressing <keycap>Shift</keycap> five times 
in a row will present a dialog asking if you want to disable Sticky Keys.
</para>
</tip>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the <guilabel>Beep when modifier is pressed</guilabel> option to receive an audible indication each time you press a modifier key such as <keycap>Ctrl</keycap>, <keycap>Alt</keycap>, or <keycap>Shift</keycap>. This option is useful to remind you whether a modifier key is active or inactive. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Selecting the <guilabel>Disable if two keys pressed together</guilabel> option will present a dialog with the option to disable Sticky Keys if two keys are pressed at the same time.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
You can use the Sticky Keys feature in Latch or Lock mode. The following table describes how to choose a mode and the difference between the two modes:
</para>
<table frame="topbot" id="dtconfig-TBL-3">
<title>Sticky Keys Latch or Lock Mode</title>
<tgroup cols="3" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="52.78*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="47.22*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec2" colwidth="47.22*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry valign="top">
<para>To use the Sticky Keys feature in...</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Press the modifier key...</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec2" valign="top">
<para>The modifier key remains active
until...</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Latch mode</para>
</entry>
<entry valign="top">
<para>Once.</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec2" valign="top">
<para>
You press a non-modifier key.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0" valign="top">
<para>Lock mode</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="top">
<para>Twice in quick succession.</para>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec2" valign="top">
<para>
You press the modifier key again.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
<para>
Example 1: If you want to press <keycombo><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>F1</keycap></keycombo>, do the following:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Press <keycap>Alt</keycap> to latch the modifier key. The <keycap>Alt</keycap> key remains active.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Press <keycap>F1</keycap>. The key combination is now complete. After you press <keycap>F1</keycap>, the <keycap>Alt</keycap> modifier key is no longer active.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
Example 2: If you want to press <keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>Alt</keycap><keycap>Tab</keycap></keycombo>, do the following:
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
Press <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> twice to lock the modifier key. The <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key remains active.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Press <keycap>Alt</keycap>. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Press <keycap>Tab</keycap>. The key combination is now complete. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
To unlock the modifier key, press <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> again.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>

<section id="dtconfig-18">
<title>Enabling Audible Toggle Key Notifications</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>toggle keys</primary>
<secondary>enabling audio notifications</secondary>
</indexterm>
<para>
A toggle key is any key on the keyboard that
can switch between two states. The <keycap>Num Lock</keycap>, <keycap>Caps Lock</keycap>, and <keycap>Scroll Lock</keycap> keys are toggle keys. Most toggle keys have an associated light emitting diode (LED) on the keyboard that lights when the toggle key 
is active. To assist users with visual impairments, you can customize the keyboard to emit an audible notification when a user presses a toggle key. For example, when you press <keycap>Num Lock</keycap>, you can determine whether the key is toggled or not 
by the sound emitted. 
</para>
<para>
To enable accessible toggle keys, perform the following steps: 
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
From the <application>Keyboard Accessibility 
Preferences (AccesX)</application> select the 
<guilabel>Filters</guilabel> tab.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the <guilabel>Enable Toggle Keys</guilabel> option.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
<para>
When you activate the <keycap>Num Lock</keycap>, <keycap>Caps Lock</keycap>, or <keycap>Scroll Lock</keycap> keys, the system beeps once. When you deactivate a toggle key, the system beeps twice.
</para>
</section>

<section id="dtconfig-19">
<title>Enabling Repeat Keys</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>repeat keys</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The Repeat Keys feature enables you to repeat a keystroke multiple times without pressing
the key more than once. This feature is designed for users who cannot release keys quickly; for example, users who operate a mouth stick. When you enable repeat keys, you can specify the duration for which you 
must press a key before the key starts to repeat.
</para>
<para>
To enable and configure the Repeat Keys feature, perform the following steps: 
</para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
From the <application>Keyboard Accessibility 
Preferences (AccessX)</application> select the <guilabel>Basic</guilabel> tab.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Select the <guilabel>Enable Repeat Keys</guilabel> option.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the <guilabel>Delay</guilabel> slider or spin box to specify the duration for which you must press a key before the keyboard interprets the action as a repeat key. If you have difficulty releasing keys, select a long time delay. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Use the <guilabel>Speed</guilabel> slider or spin box to specify the speed at which the keyboard repeats the keypress as input.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</section>
</section>

<section id="dtconfig-21">
<title>Using the Keyboard Accessibility Status Panel Application</title>
<indexterm>
<primary>Keyboard Accessibility Status panel application</primary>
</indexterm>
<para>
The <application>Keyboard Accessibility Status
</application> panel application shows you the status of the keyboard accessibility features. This panel application displays icons to indicate which keyboard accessibility features are enabled in the 
<application>Keyboard Accessibility</application> preference tool.
</para>
<para>
To add the <application>Keyboard Accessibility Status</application> panel application to a panel, right-click on the panel, then choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Add to Panel</guimenu></menuchoice> and select <guimenuitem>Keyboard Accessibility Status</guimenuitem>.
</para>
<para>
The following table describes the icons that the panel application displays and the status that each icon represents:
</para>
<table frame="topbot" id="dtconfig-TBL-25">
<title>Keyboard Accessibility Status Icons</title>
<tgroup cols="2" colsep="0" rowsep="0">
<colspec colname="colspec0" colwidth="21.97*"/>
<colspec colname="colspec1" colwidth="78.03*"/>
<thead>
<row rowsep="1">
<entry>
<para>Icon</para>
</entry>
<entry>
<para>Keyboard Accessibility Status</para>
</entry>
</row>
</thead>
<tbody>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/accessx.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Keyboard Accessibility Features enabled icon</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</entry>
<entry valign="middle">
<para>Keyboard accessibility is available 
but none of the individual features are enabled.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/bouncekeys.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Bounce Keys enabled icon</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</entry>
<entry valign="middle">
<para>
The Bounce Keys feature is enabled.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/mousekeys.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Mouse Keys enabled icon</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</entry>
<entry valign="middle">
<para>
The Mouse Keys feature is enabled. The dot in the mouse button shows which button is currently associated with the <guilabel>Mouse button click</guilabel> key.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/slowkeys.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Slow Keys enabled icon</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</entry>
<entry valign="middle">
<para>The Slow Keys feature is enabled.</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/stickyaltlatch.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Alt key latched icon</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</entry>
<entry valign="middle">
<para>
The Sticky Keys feature is enabled and the 
<keycap>Alt</keycap> key is latched.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry valign="top">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/stickyaltlock.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Alt key locked icon</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</entry>
<entry valign="middle">
<para>
The Sticky Keys feature is enabled and the 
<keycap>Alt</keycap> key is locked.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/stickyctrllatch.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Ctrl key latched icon</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="middle">
<para>
The Sticky Keys feature is enabled and the 
<keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key is latched.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/stickyctrllock.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Ctrl key locked icon</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="middle">
<para>
The Sticky Keys feature is enabled and the 
<keycap>Ctrl</keycap> key is locked.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/stickyshiftlatch.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Shift key latched icon</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="middle">
<para>
The Sticky Keys feature is enabled and the 
<keycap>Shift</keycap> key is latched.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/stickyshiftlock.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Shift key locked icon</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="middle">
<para>
The Sticky Keys feature is enabled and the 
<keycap>Shift</keycap> key is locked.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/stickywindowlatch.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Super/Windows key latched icon</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="middle">
<para>
The Sticky Keys feature is enabled and the 
<keycap>Super</keycap>/<keycap>Windows</keycap> key is latched.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
<row>
<entry colname="colspec0">
<screenshot>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="figures/stickywindowlock.png" format="PNG"/>
</imageobject>
<textobject>
<phrase>Super/Windows key locked icon</phrase>
</textobject>
</mediaobject>
</screenshot>
</entry>
<entry colname="colspec1" valign="middle">
<para>
The Sticky Keys feature is enabled and the 
<keycap>Super</keycap>/<keycap>Windows</keycap> key is locked.
</para>
</entry>
</row>
</tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
</section>
-->
</section>
</chapter>


<!--
&sysadmin;
-->

<!-- If generating PDFs and if you want an index,
     then uncomment <index/> line below -->
<!-- <index/> -->

</book>
