<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "en">
<!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
]>
	<article id="games" status="review">
	<articleinfo>
		<title>Games</title>
    	&legalnotice;
	</articleinfo>
			<para>Explore Ubuntu's Games menu by pressing &games;.</para>
			<para>Ubuntu comes with 16 games by default, including <application>Aisleriot Solitaire</application>, <application>Gnometris</application> and <application>Mines</application>. There are many more games which can be installed optionally. This section is intended to give a summary of some of the games which are available for you to install and play.</para>
		
		<sect1 id="games-ubuntu-popular" status="review">
			<title>Popular Games</title>
			<para>A list of some of the most popular games available in Ubuntu.</para>
			
			<sect2 id="games-popular-neverball" xreflabel="Neverball" status="review">
				<title>Neverball</title>
				<para>
				<application>Neverball</application>, part puzzle and part
				action game, is a test of skill. The object of the game is to roll the ball
				through an obstacle course before time runs out by tilting the floor.
				</para>
				<para>
				Included with the <application>Neverball</application> package is
				the game <application>Neverputt</application>.
				<application>Neverputt</application> is a hot-seat multiplayer miniature golf
				game based on <application>Neverball</application>. Installing <application>Neverputt</application> by itself is not currently possible.
				</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para><ulink url="apt:neverball">Install the <application>neverball</application> package</ulink> from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Click &neverball; to play <application>Neverball</application>.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Click &neverputt; to start the <application>Neverputt</application> game.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="games-popular-scorched" xreflabel="Scorched3D" status="review">
					<title>Scorched3D</title>
					<para><application>Scorched3D</application> is a 3D remake of <emphasis>Scorched Earth</emphasis>, an artillery duel game.</para>
					<para>You must have your video card's hardware-accelerated 3D drivers installed in order to play Scorched3D</para>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para><ulink url="apt:scorched3d">Install the <application>scorched3d</application> package</ulink> from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository.</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>To start
								<application>Scorched3D</application>,
								choose &scorched3d;.
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="games-popular-chromium" xreflabel="Chromium" status="review">
				<title>Chromium</title>
				<para>
				<application>Chromium</application> is a fast paced,
				arcade-style, top-scrolling space shooter. As a captain of the Chromium B.S.U., 
				the objective is to deliver supplies to the troops on the front
				line. The ship has a small fleet of robotic fighters which you control from the
				relative safety of the Chromium vessel. More information about the game can be
				found on the <ulink url="http://www.reptilelabour.com/software/chromium/">Chromium website</ulink>.
				</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>Install the <application>chromium</application> package from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository (see <ulink type="help" url="ghelp:add-applications">Add Applications</ulink>).</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Press &chromium; to play <application>Chromium</application>.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="games-popular-frozenbubble" xreflabel="Frozen Bubble" status="review">
				<title>Frozen Bubble</title>
				<para>
				<application>Frozen Bubble</application> is a clone of the
				popular <emphasis>Puzzle Bobble</emphasis> game. The object of the game is to
				shoot bubbles into groups of the same color to cause them to pop. Features
				include 100 single-player levels, a two-player mode, as well as music and striking
				graphics. More information about the game can be found on the <ulink url="http://www.frozen-bubble.org/">Frozen Bubble website</ulink>.
				</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para><ulink url="apt:frozen-bubble">Install the <application>frozen-bubble</application> package</ulink> from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Press &frozen-bubble;.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="games-popular-supertux" xreflabel="SuperTux" status="review">
				<title>SuperTux</title>
				<para>
				<application>SuperTux</application> is a classic 2D jump and
				run sidescroller game in a style similar to the original <emphasis><trademark>Super Mario
				Bros.</trademark></emphasis> games. Features include 9 enemies, 26 playable levels,
				software and OpenGL rendering modes, configurable joystick and keyboard input,
				new music and completely redone graphics. More information about the game can be
				found on the <ulink url="http://supertux.berlios.de/">SuperTux website</ulink>.
				</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para><ulink url="apt:supertux">Install the <application>supertux</application> package</ulink> from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Press &supertux; to start the <application>SuperTux</application> game.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="games-popular-planetpenguinracer" xreflabel="Planet Penguin Racer" status="review">
				<title>PlanetPenguin Racer</title>
				<para>
				<application>PlanetPenguin Racer</application> is a fork created
				from the last GPL-licenced version of <emphasis>Tux Racer</emphasis>. In
				addition to the levels from the original game, <application>PlanetPenguin
				Racer</application> also includes additional levels which have been developed by
				the community. The object of the game is to slide down the mountain, collecting
				fish as you go, and trying to reach the finish line in the shortest amount of time.
				</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para><ulink url="apt:planetpenguin-racer">Install the <application>planetpenguin-racer</application> package</ulink> from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Press &ppracer; to play the game.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="games-popular-tremulous" xreflabel="Tremulous" status="review">
				<title>Tremulous</title>
				<para>
				<application>Tremulous</application> is a free, open source game
				that blends a team based First Person Shooter (FPS) with elements of a Real Time
				Strategy (RTS) game. Players can choose from two unique races, aliens and
				humans. The objective is to eliminate the opposing team by not only killing the
				opposing players but also removing their ability to respawn by destroying the
				spawn structures. More information about the game can be found on the <ulink url="http://tremulous.net/">Tremulous website</ulink>.
				</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para><ulink url="apt:tremulous">Install the <application>tremulous</application> package</ulink> from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Press &tremulous; to play <application>Tremulous</application>.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect2>

			<sect2 id="games-popular-nexuiz" xreflabel="Nexuiz" status="review">
				<title>Nexuiz</title>
				<para>
				<application>Nexuiz</application> is a 3D deathmatch game based
				on the Darkplaces engine, which is an advanced
				<emphasis>Quake 1</emphasis> engine built on OpenGL technology. It includes 17
				maps, 15 player models, advanced UI, and an available master server allowing you
				to play people from all over the world. More information about the game can be
				found on the <ulink url="http://www.alientrap.org/nexuiz/index.php">Nexuiz website</ulink>.
				</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para><ulink url="apt:nexuiz">Install the <application>nexuiz</application> package</ulink> from the <quote>Universe</quote> repository.</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>Press &nexuiz; to start <application>Nexuiz</application>.</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="games-ubuntu-arcade" status="review">
			<title>Arcade Games</title>
			
			<para>Arcade games are usually simple, fun games. A large collection of arcade games is available with Ubuntu; listed below are just a few of them.</para>
			
			<sect2 id="ubuntu-arcade-classic" status="review">
				<title>Classic arcade games</title>
				<itemizedlist>

					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KBounce</application> is a game
					where the object is to catch several moving balls in a rectangular game field by
					building walls. More balls are added with each level that you complete successfully; 
					how many can you catch?
					</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KFouleggs</application> clones
					the well-known <emphasis>PuyoPuyo</emphasis> game from Japan, and contains
					modifications of the well-known Tetris game principle.
					</para>
					</listitem>
				
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>Kolf</application> is a
					miniature golf game played with an overhead view, with a short bar representing
					the golf club and direction of the intended shot. It features various courses, a
					course editor, water hazards, slopes, sand traps, and black holes.
					</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KSirtet</application> is a
					<emphasis>Tetris</emphasis> clone which allows multiplayer duels as well as
					duels against the computer player.
					</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KSmiletris</application> is yet
					another clone of <emphasis>Tetris</emphasis>, which is easy to learn and play.
					</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>Robots</application> is a game
					where the object is to avoid a hoard of robots who are trying to catch you. With
					every step you make, the robots get closer to getting you and you must do whatever 
					you can to avoid them.
					</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="ubuntu-arcade-maze" status="review">
				<title>Maze games</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KGoldrunner</application> is a
					game of action and puzzle solving. Run through the maze, dodge your enemies, 
					collect all of the gold, and climb up to the next level.
					</para>
					</listitem>
					
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KSnakerace</application> is a
					fast action game where you control a snake which has to eat the food that appears on the map.
					The more you eat, the larger your snake grows. The goal is to eat as much as possible without
					colliding with another snake or the wall, however this becomes more and more 
					difficult the more you eat.
					</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KTron</application> is based on 
					the popular computer game for two players as well as the famous movie. It is
					a fast paced game in which both players have to move and avoid colliding with
					any walls, the opponent, or the paths that you or your opponent have created.
					</para>
					</listitem>
				
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>Nibbles</application> is a game 
					where the user controls a snake, moving it around the board and eating diamonds
					while avoiding the walls. <application>Nibbles</application> also features
					network multiplayer, and up to four worms can be controlled by the computer.
					</para>
					</listitem>
					
				</itemizedlist>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="ubuntu-arcade-space" status="review">
				<title>Space games</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KAsteroids</application> is a
					fast arcade shooting game where you command a spaceship trying to survive the passage
					through an asteroid field. Destroy asteroids by shooting them until they split into smaller and smaller 
					parts.
					</para>
					</listitem>
					
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KSpaceDuel</application> is a 
					space game for two players, however one player can be controlled by the
					computer. Each player controls a satellite that flies around the Sun, all the 
					while trying not to collide with anything and trying to shoot at the other space
					ship.
					</para>
					</listitem>
					
				</itemizedlist>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="games-ubuntu-card" status="review">
			<title>Card, Puzzle and Board Games</title>
			<para>Card and puzzle games are very popular, and Ubuntu has a large collection of such games for you to choose from. A list of some of the more popular games available is given below.</para>
			
			<sect2 id="ubuntu-card-card" status="review">
				<title>Card games</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>Aisleriot</application>, also
					known as <emphasis>Solitaire</emphasis> or <emphasis>Patience</emphasis>, is a
					collection of single-player card games which are easy to learn and fun to play.
					</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>Blackjack</application> is a 
					multiple deck, casino-rules blackjack game. The object is to hold cards having a
					higher count than those of the dealer, without going over 21. Face card plus an
					Ace equals 21, Blackjack!
					</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>Freecell</application> is 
					another <emphasis>Solitaire</emphasis> game which is very popular on the
					<trademark>Windows</trademark> platform.
					</para>
					</listitem>
					
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KPatience</application> is a
					collection of various patience games known worldwide. Games include
					<emphasis>Klondike</emphasis>, <emphasis>Freecell</emphasis>,
					<emphasis>Yukon</emphasis>, <emphasis>forty and Eight</emphasis> and many more.
					</para>
					</listitem>
					
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KPoker</application> follows the
					rules of the original <emphasis>Poker</emphasis> game. The game provides a
					computer player and various card decks.
					</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>Lieutnant Skat</application> is
					a two player card game which follows the rules of the German game,
					<emphasis>(Offiziers)-Skat</emphasis>. The game includes various card decks and a
					computer opponent can play for any of the players.
					</para>
					</listitem>
					
				</itemizedlist>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="ubuntu-card-board" status="review">
				<title>Board games</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>Atlantik</application> is an
					open-source game client for the <trademark>Monopoly</trademark>-like board games
					played on the monopd network.
					</para>
					</listitem>
					
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>Chess</application> (or <application>glChess</application>) is a 
					chess game where you can play against the computer or against other players. 
					Chess detects and uses known third-party chess engines for computer players, 
					and can show the chess board in 2D or 3D.
					</para>
					</listitem>
					
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KBackgammon</application>
					follows the rules of the popular boardgame, and supports multiplayer games 
					and games against computer engines such as GNU bg, as well as other online games.
					</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KBlackbox</application> is a
					logical game of hide-and-seek, inspired by <emphasis>emacs blackbox</emphasis> 
					and played on a grid of boxes.
					</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>Kenolaba</application> is a two-player tactical 
					game which follows the rules of <emphasis>Abalone</emphasis>, where
					players try to shove their opponents' pieces from the game board.
					</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KMahjongg</application> is a
					clone of the well known tile-based patience game of the same name. Your goal is
					to empty the board by matching pieces with the same pattern.
					</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KReversi</application> is a two
					player game in which players gain the majority of pieces on the board by
					tactically placing their pieces in order to turn over their opponent's pieces.
					</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KWin4</application>, or
					<emphasis>Four wins</emphasis>, is a two player game which follows the rules of
					the famous <trademark>Connect Four</trademark> game. Align four pieces of the 
					same color to win!
					</para>
					</listitem>
					
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>Mahjongg</application> is a
					single-player version of the classic tile game. The objective is to select pairs
					of similar tiles.
					</para>
					</listitem>
					
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>Shishen-Sho</application> is similar to <emphasis>Mahjongg</emphasis>, 
					and is played by removing all tiles from	the field, two at a time, by matching tiles of the same type.
					</para>
					</listitem>
					
				</itemizedlist>
			</sect2>
			
			<sect2 id="ubuntu-card-puzzle" status="review">
				<title>Puzzle games</title>
				<itemizedlist>
					
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>Anagramarama</application> is a
					fast-paced word game in which you must make as many words as possible from 
					a series of jumbled letters. If you find the longest word possible, you can move on 
					to the next level.
					</para>
					</listitem>
					
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>Atomix</application> is a
					puzzle game where you must join up a series of atoms to make certain molecules. 
					However, the atoms can only be moved in certain ways, making complex molecules 
					a challenge to construct. No knowledge of chemistry is required.
					</para>
					</listitem>
					
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>KAtomic</application> is a thinking game similar to <application>Atomix</application>, 
					where you have to form chemical molecules out of atoms. This is 
					done by moving each atom in a labyrinth until you have formed a complete molecule.
					</para>
					</listitem>
					
					<listitem>
					<para>
					<application>Sudoku</application> is a
					popular number puzzle game. Use logic to complete a grid of 
					numbers so that each row, column and large square contains the numbers one 
					to nine.
					</para>
					</listitem>
					
				</itemizedlist>
			</sect2>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="games-ubuntu-kids" status="review">
			<title>Kids&apos; Games</title>
			<para>As well as games for adults, Ubuntu also caters for children by providing a selection of games intended to be both interesting and educational 				for younger age groups. A small list of available games is given below.</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				
				<listitem>
				<para>
				<application>GCompris</application> is a collection of educational games and activities 
				intended for young children. A large number of language, arithmetic and reading exercises 
				are included, along with plenty of fun activities such as an animation and drawing program.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				
				<listitem>
				<para>
				<application>KTuberling</application>, or the
				<emphasis>Potato Game</emphasis>, is intended for young children. However, some
				adults may find it appeasing too! The object is to create your very own 
				potato-like guy from a selection of eyes, mouths, moustaches, and other parts of
				the face. Other items can also be attached.
				</para>
				</listitem>
				
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect1>
		
		<sect1 id="games-ubuntu-strategy-sim" status="review">
			<title>Strategy and Simulation Games</title>
			<para>Strategy games require you to use careful tactics to plan the next move; simulation games let you explore and manage realistic models of such things as cities and vehicles. Strategy and simulation games can be quite addictive and many people happily spend hours playing their game of choice! A small selection of strategy and simulation games available with Ubuntu is given below.</para>
			<itemizedlist>

				<listitem>
				<para>
				<application>KBattleship</application> is an
				implementation of the popular game where your goal is to sink your opponent's
				ships by guessing where they are on a grid. Play against the computer or 
				against others over the Internet. &quot;<emphasis>You sunk my battleship!</emphasis>&quot;
				</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
				<para>
				<application>KJumpingcube</application> is a 
				tactical one or two-player game in which the playing field consists of squares
				that contains points which can be increased. The object is to gain as many
				fields as possible, finally winning the board over.
				</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
				<para>
				<application>Klickety</application> is an
				adaption of the <emphasis>Clickomania</emphasis> game, which has rules that are
				similar to those of the <application>Same Game</application>. The goal is to
				clear the board by clicking on groups to destroy them.
				</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
				<para>
				<application>KMines</application> is a clone
				of the classical <emphasis>Minesweeper</emphasis> game, where you have to find 
				hidden mines by logical deduction.
				</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
				<para>
				<application>Kolor Lines</application>, or
				<application>KLines</application>, is the KDE version of the Russian game
				<emphasis>Lines</emphasis>, where you have to align five game pieces of the same
				color in one line to remove them from the gameboard.
				</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
				<para>
				<application>Konquest</application>, the KDE
				version of <emphasis>Gnu-Lactic Konquest</emphasis>, is a multiplayer strategy
				game with the goal of expanding your interstellar empire across the galaxy and
				of course to crush your rivals.
				</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
				<para>
				<application>KSokoban</application> is a
				logic game where you are a warehouse keeper trying to push crates to their
				proper locations in a warehouse.
				</para>
				</listitem>

				<listitem>
				<para>
				<application>KSame</application>, inspired by
				<emphasis>Same Game</emphasis>, is a simple game played for a high score. The
				object is to remove as many of the same pieces that are touching for the most
				points. Speed, the amount of pieces removed at once and the movement of the
				mouse over possible pieces are taken into account for the final score.
				</para>
				</listitem>
			
			</itemizedlist>
		</sect1>
		<sect1 status="review">
				<title>Windows Games</title>
				<para>Many games which are available for Windows can be run on Linux by using an emulator, such as <application>Wine</application> or <application>Cedega</application>.</para>
				<para>These emulators only work on <emphasis>x86</emphasis> (Intel-based) computers, and will not function on <emphasis>AMD64</emphasis> or <emphasis>PowerPC</emphasis> computers.</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role='strong'>Wine (free)</emphasis></para>
							<para><application>Wine</application> is free software, and is able to run several popular games, such as <application>World of Warcraft</application> and <application>Unreal Tournament</application>. For information about Wine, see <ulink url="&wiki-Wine;">the Ubuntu wiki</ulink>.</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis role='strong'>Cedega (commercial)</emphasis></para>
							<para><application>Cedega</application> is based on Wine, but is optimized for running Windows games. Cedega is commercial software and is therefore not free, but it is able to run more games than Wine. For information about Cedega, see <ulink url="&wiki-Cedega;">the Ubuntu wiki</ulink>.</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
		</sect1>
	</article>
