<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
]>
<chapter id="file-servers" status="review">
	<title>File Servers</title>

        <para>
        If you have more than one computer on a single network.  At some point you will probably
        need to share files between them.  In this section we cover installing and configuring 
        FTP, NFS, and CUPS. 
        </para>

	<sect1 id="ftp-server" status="review">
          <title>FTP Server</title> 

          <para>
          File Transfer Protocol (FTP) is a TCP protocol for uploading and downloading
          files between computers. FTP works on a client/server model. The server component is
          called an <emphasis>FTP daemon</emphasis>. It continuously listens for FTP requests
          from remote clients. When a request is received, it manages the login and sets up
          the connection. For the duration of the session it executes any of commands sent by
          the FTP client.
          </para>

          <para>Access to an FTP server can be managed in two ways:</para>

          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem>
              <para>Anonymous</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Authenticated</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>
          In the Anonymous mode, remote clients can access the FTP server by using the
          default user account called &quot;anonymous&quot; or &quot;ftp&quot; and
          sending an email address as the password. In the Authenticated mode a user must
          have an account and a password. User access to the FTP server directories and files is
          dependent on the permissions defined for the account used at login. As a general
          rule, the FTP daemon will hide the root directory of the FTP server and change it to
          the FTP Home directory. This hides the rest of the file system from remote
          sessions.
          </para>

          <sect2 id="vsftpd-ftp-server-installation" status="review">
            <title>vsftpd - FTP Server Installation</title>

            <para>
            vsftpd is an FTP daemon available in
            Ubuntu. It is easy to install, set up, and
            maintain.  To install <application>vsftpd</application> you
            can run the following command:
            </para>
      
<screen>
<command>sudo apt-get install vsftpd</command>
</screen>
                

            </sect2>
            <sect2 id="vsftpd-anonymous-configuration" status="review">
              <title>Anonymous FTP Configuration</title>

                <para>
                By default <application>vsftpd</application> is configured 
                to only allow anonymous download.  During installation a 
                <emphasis>ftp</emphasis> user is created with a home directory 
                of <filename>/home/ftp</filename>.  This is the default FTP directory.
                </para>

                <para>
                If you wish to change this location, to <filename>/srv/ftp</filename>
                for example, simply create a directory in another location and 
                change the <emphasis>ftp</emphasis> user's home directory:
                </para>

<screen>
<command>sudo mkdir /srv/ftp</command>
<command>sudo usermod -d /srv/ftp ftp</command> 
</screen>

                <para>
                After making the change restart <application>vsftpd</application>:
                </para>

<screen>
<command>sudo /etc/init.d/vsftpd restart</command>
</screen>

                <para>
                Finally, copy any files and directories you would like to make available
                through anonymous FTP to <filename>/srv/ftp</filename>.
                </para>

              </sect2>
              <sect2 id="vsftpd-userauth-configuration" status="review">
                <title>User Authenticated FTP Configuration</title>

                <para>
                To configure <application>vsftpd</application> to authenticate
                system users and allow them to upload files edit
                <filename>/etc/vsftpd.conf</filename>:
                </para>

<programlisting>
local_enable=YES
write_enable=YES
</programlisting>

                <para>
                Now restart <application>vsftpd</application>:
                </para>

<screen>
<command>sudo /etc/init.d/vsftpd restart</command>
</screen>

                <para>
                Now when system users login to FTP they will start in their 
                <emphasis>home</emphasis> directories where they can download,
                upload, create directories, etc.
                </para>

                <para>
                Similarly, by default, the anonymous users are not
                allowed to upload files to FTP server. To change
                this setting, you should uncomment the following
                line, and restart <application>vsftpd</application>:
                </para>

<programlisting>
anon_upload_enable=YES
</programlisting>

                <warning>
                  <para>
                  Enabling anonymous FTP upload can be an extreme security risk.  It is best to not enable 
                  anonymous upload on servers accessed directly from the Internet.
                  </para>
                </warning>

                <para>
                The configuration file consists of many
                configuration parameters. The information about
                each parameter is available in the configuration
                file. Alternatively, you can refer to the man
                page, <command>man 5 vsftpd.conf</command> for
                details of each parameter. 
                </para>

                </sect2>
                <sect2 id="vsftpd-security" status="review">
                  <title>Securing FTP</title>

                  <para> 
                  There are options in <filename>/etc/vsftpd.conf</filename> to
                  help make <application>vsftpd</application> more secure.  For
                  example users can be limited to their home directories by uncommenting:
                  </para>

<programlisting>
chroot_local_user=YES
</programlisting>

                  <para>
                  You can also limit a specific list of users to just their home directories:
                  </para>

<programlisting>
chroot_list_enable=YES
chroot_list_file=/etc/vsftpd.chroot_list
</programlisting>

                  <para>
                  After uncommenting the above options, create a <filename>/etc/vsftpd.chroot_list</filename>
                  containing a list of users one per line.  Then restart <application>vsftpd</application>:
                  </para>

<screen>
<command>sudo /etc/init.d/vsftpd restart</command>
</screen>
                  
                  <para>
                  Also, the <filename>/etc/ftpusers</filename> file is a list of users that
                  are <emphasis>disallowed</emphasis> FTP access.  The default list 
                  includes root, daemon, nobody, etc.  To disable FTP access for additional
                  users simply add them to the list.
                  </para>

                  <para>
                  FTP can also be encrypted using <emphasis>FTPS</emphasis>.  Different from <emphasis>SFTP</emphasis>,
                  <emphasis>FTPS</emphasis> is FTP over Secure Socket Layer (SSL).  <emphasis>SFTP</emphasis> is a FTP 
                  like session over an encrypted <emphasis>SSH</emphasis> connection.  A major difference is that users
                  of SFTP need to have a <emphasis>shell</emphasis> account on the system, instead of a 
                  <emphasis>nologin</emphasis> shell.  Providing all users with a shell may not be ideal for some 
                  environments, such as a shared web host.
                  </para>

                  <para>
                  To configure <emphasis>FTPS</emphasis>, edit <filename>/etc/vsftpd.conf</filename> and at the bottom add:
                  </para>

<programlisting>
ssl_enable=Yes
</programlisting>
           
                  <para>
                  Also, notice the certificate and key related options:
                  </para>

<programlisting>
rsa_cert_file=/etc/ssl/certs/ssl-cert-snakeoil.pem
rsa_private_key_file=/etc/ssl/private/ssl-cert-snakeoil.key
</programlisting>

                  <para>
                  By default these options are set the the certificate and key provided by the <application>ssl-cert</application>
                  package.  In a production environment these should be replaced with a certificate and key generated for the specific
                  host.  For more information on certificates see <xref linkend="certificates-and-security"/>.
                  </para>

                  <para>
                  Now restart <application>vsftpd</application>, and non-anonymous users will be forced to use 
                  <emphasis>FTPS</emphasis>:
                  </para>

<screen>
<command>sudo /etc/init.d/vsftpd restart</command>
</screen>

                  <para>
                  To allow users with a shell of <filename>/usr/sbin/nologin</filename> access to FTP, but have no shell access, 
                  edit <filename>/etc/shells</filename> adding the <emphasis>nologin</emphasis> shell:
                  </para>

<programlisting>
# /etc/shells: valid login shells
/bin/csh
/bin/sh
/usr/bin/es
/usr/bin/ksh
/bin/ksh
/usr/bin/rc
/usr/bin/tcsh
/bin/tcsh
/usr/bin/esh
/bin/dash
/bin/bash
/bin/rbash
/usr/bin/screen
/usr/sbin/nologin
</programlisting>

                  <para>
                  This is necessary because, by default <application>vsftpd</application> uses PAM for authentication, and the 
                  <filename>/etc/pam.d/vsftpd</filename> configuration file contains:
                  </para>

<programlisting>
auth    required        pam_shells.so
</programlisting>

                  <para>
                  The <emphasis>shells</emphasis> PAM module restricts access to shells listed in the <filename>/etc/shells</filename>
                  file.
                  </para>

                  <para>
                  Most popular FTP clients can be configured connect using FTPS.  The <application>lftp</application> command line FTP
                  client has the ability to use FTPS as well.
                  </para>

                </sect2>
                <sect2 id="vsftpd-references" status="review">
                  <title>References</title>

                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                      See the <ulink url="http://vsftpd.beasts.org/vsftpd_conf.html">vsftpd website</ulink> for more information.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                      For detailed <filename>/etc/vsftpd.conf</filename> options see the 
                      <ulink url="http://manpages.ubuntu.com/manpages/jaunty/en/man5/vsftpd.conf.5.html">vsftpd.conf man page</ulink>.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                      The CodeGurus article <ulink url="http://www.codeguru.com/csharp/.net/net_general/internet/article.php/c14329">
                      FTPS vs. SFTP: What to Choose</ulink> has useful information contrasting FTPS and SFTP.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                  
                </sect2>

    </sect1>
	<sect1 id="network-file-system" status="review">
		<title>Network File System (NFS)</title>
          <para>
          NFS allows a system to share directories and files with others
          over a network. By using NFS, users and programs can access
          files on remote systems almost as if they were local files.
          </para>

          <para>
          Some of the most notable benefits that NFS can provide are:
          </para>

          <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
      <para>Local workstations use less disk space because commonly used data
can be stored on a single machine and still remain accessible to others
over the network.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
      <para>There is no need for users to have separate home directories on
every network machine. Home directories could be set up on the NFS
server and made available throughout the network.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>

      <para>Storage devices such as floppy disks, CDROM drives, and USB
Thumb drives can be used by other machines on the network. This may
reduce the number of removable media drives throughout the
network.</para>
          </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

      <sect2 id="nfs-installation" status="review">
        <title>Installation</title>
      
          <para>
          At a terminal prompt enter the following command to install the NFS
          Server:
          </para>
          <para>
<screen>
<command>sudo apt-get install nfs-kernel-server</command>
</screen>
          </para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="nfs-configuration" status="review">
        <title>Configuration</title>
          <para>
          You can configure the directories to be exported by adding them to
          the <filename>/etc/exports</filename> file. For example:
          </para>
          <para>
<screen>
/ubuntu  *(ro,sync,no_root_squash)
/home    *(rw,sync,no_root_squash)
</screen>
          </para>

          <para>
          You can replace * with one of the hostname formats. Make the
          hostname declaration as specific as possible so unwanted
          systems cannot access the NFS mount.
          </para>

          <para>
          To start the NFS server, you can run the following command at a terminal prompt:
          </para>
          <para>
<screen>
<command>sudo /etc/init.d/nfs-kernel-server start</command>
</screen>
          </para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="nfs-client-configuration" status="review">
        <title>NFS Client Configuration</title>
          <para>
          Use the <application>mount</application> command to mount a shared NFS directory from
          another machine, by typing a command line similar to the following at a terminal prompt:
          </para>
          <para>
<screen>
<command>sudo mount example.hostname.com:/ubuntu /local/ubuntu</command>
</screen>
</para>
      <warning>
      <para>
      The mount point directory <filename>/local/ubuntu</filename> must
      exist. There should be no files or subdirectories in the
      <filename>/local/ubuntu</filename> directory.
      </para>
      </warning>

      <para>
       An alternate way to mount an NFS share from another machine is to
       add a line to the <filename>/etc/fstab</filename> file. The line must state the
       hostname of the NFS server, the directory on the server being
       exported, and the directory on the local machine where the NFS
       share is to be mounted.
      </para>

      <para>
      The general syntax for the line in <filename>/etc/fstab</filename>
      file is as follows:
      </para>
      
      <para>
<programlisting>
example.hostname.com:/ubuntu /local/ubuntu nfs rsize=8192,wsize=8192,timeo=14,intr
</programlisting>
      </para>
          <para>
          If you have trouble mounting an NFS share, make sure the <application>nfs-common</application> package is 
          installed on your client.  To install
          <application>nfs-common</application> enter the following
          command at the terminal
          prompt:
<screen>
<command>sudo apt-get install nfs-common</command>
</screen>
          </para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="nfs-references" status="review">
        <title>References</title>
				<para><ulink url="http://nfs.sourceforge.net/">Linux NFS faq</ulink></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>

	<sect1 id="cups" status="review">
		<title>CUPS - Print Server</title>
          <para>
            The primary mechanism for Ubuntu printing and print services is the 
			<emphasis role="bold">Common UNIX Printing System</emphasis> (CUPS). 
			This printing system is a freely available, portable printing layer 
			which has become the new standard for printing in most Linux 
			distributions.
          </para>
          <para>
          CUPS manages print jobs and queues and provides network printing using 
		  the standard Internet Printing Protocol (IPP), while offering support 
		  for a very large range of printers, from dot-matrix to laser and many 
		  in between.  CUPS also supports PostScript Printer Description (PPD) and 
		  auto-detection of network printers, and features a simple web-based 
		  configuration and administration tool. 
          </para>
      <sect2 id="cups-installation" status="review">
        <title>Installation</title>
          <para>
            To install CUPS on your Ubuntu computer, simply use <application>sudo</application> with the <application>apt-get</application> command and give the packages to install as the first parameter. A complete CUPS install has many package dependencies, but they may all be specified on the same command line.  Enter the following at a terminal prompt to install CUPS:
          </para>
          <para>
<screen>
<command>sudo apt-get install cupsys</command>
</screen>
          </para>
          <para>
          Upon authenticating with your user password, the packages should be downloaded
		  and installed without error. Upon the conclusion of installation, the CUPS server 
		  will be started automatically. 
 	  </para>
          <para>
          For troubleshooting purposes, you can access CUPS 
		  server errors via the error log file at: <filename>/var/log/cups/error_log</filename>.
		  If the error log does not show enough information to troubleshoot any problems you
		  encounter, the verbosity of the CUPS log can be increased by changing the <emphasis
		  role="bold">LogLevel</emphasis> directive in the configuration file (discussed below)
		  to "debug" or even "debug2", which logs everything, from the default of "info".  If 
		  you make this change, remember to change it back once you've solved your problem, to 
		  prevent the log file from becoming overly large.
          </para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="cups-configuration" status="review">
        <title>Configuration</title>
          <para>
            The Common UNIX Printing System server's behavior is configured through the 
			directives contained in the file <filename>/etc/cups/cupsd.conf</filename>.  
			The CUPS configuration file follows the same syntax as the primary configuration 
			file for the Apache HTTP server, so users familiar with editing Apache's 
			configuration file should feel at ease when editing the CUPS configuration 
			file. Some examples of settings you may wish to change initially will be 
			presented here.
          </para>
          <tip>
               <para>Prior to editing the configuration file, you should make a copy of 
			   the original file and protect it from writing, so you will have the original 
			   settings as a reference, and to reuse as necessary.
               </para>
               <para>Copy the <filename>/etc/cups/cupsd.conf</filename> file and protect it 
			   from writing with the following commands, issued at a terminal prompt:
               </para>
               </tip>
               <para>
<screen>
<command>sudo cp /etc/cups/cupsd.conf /etc/cups/cupsd.conf.original</command>
<command>sudo chmod a-w /etc/cups/cupsd.conf.original</command>
</screen>
               </para>
          <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">ServerAdmin</emphasis>: To configure the email 
				address of the designated administrator of the CUPS server, simply 
				edit the <filename>/etc/cups/cupsd.conf</filename> configuration file 
				with your preferred text editor, and modify the <emphasis 
				role="italics">ServerAdmin</emphasis> line accordingly.  For example, 
				if you are the Administrator for the CUPS server, and your e-mail 
				address is 'bjoy@somebigco.com', then you would modify the ServerAdmin 
				line to appear as such:
                </para>
                <para>
<screen>
ServerAdmin bjoy@somebigco.com
</screen>
                </para>
                </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
                <para>
                For more examples of configuration directives in the CUPS server 
				configuration file, view the associated system manual page by entering the 
				following command at a terminal prompt:
               </para>
               <para>
<screen>
<command>man cupsd.conf</command>
</screen>
               </para>
                               <note>
                <para>
                Whenever you make changes to the <filename>/etc/cups/cupsd.conf</filename> configuration file, you'll need to restart the CUPS server by typing the following command at a terminal prompt:
                </para>
                </note>
                <para>
<screen>
<command>sudo /etc/init.d/cupsys restart</command>
</screen>
                </para>
	<para>Some other configuration for the CUPS server is done in the file <filename>/etc/cups/cups.d/ports.conf</filename>:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Listen</emphasis>: By default on Ubuntu, the CUPS 
				server installation listens only on the loopback interface at IP address 
				<emphasis>127.0.0.1</emphasis>. In order to instruct the 
				CUPS server to listen on an actual network adapter's IP address, you must 
				specify either a hostname, the IP address, or optionally, an IP 
				address/port pairing via the addition of a Listen directive.  For example, 
				if your CUPS server resides on a local network at the IP address <emphasis 
				role="italics">192.168.10.250</emphasis> and you'd like to make it 
				accessible to the other systems on this subnetwork, you would edit the 
				<filename>/etc/cups/cupsd.conf</filename> and add a Listen 
				directive, as such:
                </para>
                <para>
<screen>
Listen 127.0.0.1:631           # existing loopback Listen
Listen /var/run/cups/cups.sock # existing socket Listen
Listen 192.168.10.250:631      # Listen on the LAN interface, Port 631 (IPP)
</screen>
                </para>
                <para>
                In the example above, you may comment out or remove the reference to the 
				Loopback address (127.0.0.1) if you do not wish <application>cupsd
				</application> to listen on that interface, but would rather have it only 
				listen on the Ethernet interfaces of the Local Area Network (LAN). To enable 
				listening for all network interfaces for which a certain hostname is bound, 
				including the Loopback, you could create a Listen entry for the hostname 
				<emphasis>socrates</emphasis> as such:
                </para>
                <para>
<screen>
Listen socrates:631  # Listen on all interfaces for the hostname 'socrates'
</screen>
                </para> 
				<para>or by omitting the Listen directive and using <emphasis>Port</emphasis> instead, as in:</para>
<para>
<screen>
Port 631  # Listen on port 631 on all interfaces
</screen>
</para>
                </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="cups-references" status="review">
        <title>References</title>
        <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.cups.org/">CUPS Website</ulink>
        </para>
        </sect2>
    </sect1>

</chapter>

