<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" 
	"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
%globalent;
<!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
%gnome-menus-C;
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY language "&EnglishAmerican;">
]>
<chapter id="introduction-chap" status="review">
  <title id="introduction">Introduction</title>
  <para>Welcome to the <emphasis>Ubuntu Server Guide</emphasis>!</para>
  <para>
   Here you can find information on how to install and configure various server applications.  It is a step-by-step, task-oriented guide 
   for configuring and customizing your system.
  </para>
  <para>
  This guide assumes you have a basic understanding of your Ubuntu
  system.  Some installation details are covered in <xref linkend="installation"/>, but if you need detailed instructions installing  
  Ubuntu please refer to the <ulink url="https://help.ubuntu.com/&distro-rev;/installation-guide/">Ubuntu Installation Guide</ulink>.
  </para>

  <para>
  A HTML version of the manual is available online at <ulink
  url="&ubuntu-documentation;">the Ubuntu Documentation website</ulink>.  The HTML files are also available in the 
  <application>ubuntu-serverguide</application> package.  See <xref linkend="package-management"/> for details on installing
  packages.
  </para>

  <para>
  If you choose to install the <application>ubuntu-serverguide</application> you can view this document from a console by:
  </para>
<screen>
<command>w3m /usr/share/ubuntu-serverguide/html/en_GB/index.html</command>
</screen>
  <note>
    <para>
    Replace <emphasis>en_GB</emphasis> with your language localization.
    </para>
  </note>
	
<!-- Not currently true for this edition
  <para>
  Also, you can buy this guide in book form from <ulink
  url="&lulu-store;">our Lulu store</ulink>. You will
  only pay for the price of printing and postage.
  </para>
-->

  <sect1 id="ubuntu-support" status="review">
    <title>Support</title>

    <para>
    There a couple of different ways that Ubuntu Server Edition is supported, commercial support and community support.  The main
    commercial support (and development funding) is available from Canonical Ltd.  They supply reasonably priced support contracts
    on a per desktop or per server basis.  For more information see the 
    <ulink url="http://www.canonical.com/services/support">Canonical Services</ulink> page.
    </para>

    <para>
    Community support is also provided by dedicated individuals, and companies, that wish to make Ubuntu the best distribution possible. 
    Support is provided through multiple mailing lists, IRC channels, forums, blogs, wikis, etc.  The large amount of information available 
    can be overwhelming, but a good search engine query can usually provide an answer to your questions.  See the 
    <ulink url="http://www.ubuntu.com/support">Ubuntu Support</ulink> page for more information.
    </para>

  </sect1>	
</chapter>
