<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD Docbook XML V.4.3//EN"
	  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
	  <!ENTITY % globalent SYSTEM "../../libs/global.ent">
	  %globalent;
	  <!ENTITY % gnome-menus-C SYSTEM "../../libs/gnome-menus-C.ent">
	  %gnome-menus-C;
	  <!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../libs/xinclude.mod">
	  %xinclude;
	  <!ENTITY language "en">
	  <!ENTITY ubuntu '<phrase>Ubuntu</phrase>'>
	  ]>

<chapter id="md" status="review">	
	<title>Migrating your data into Ubuntu</title>
	<para>This chapter provides instructions on importing your data from Windows applications to the corresponding Ubuntu applications. The instructions assume that you will use the default collection of applications installed with Ubuntu and have followed the instructions in the <xref linkend="preparing"/> chapter.</para>
	<sect1 id="md-files">
		<title>Files</title>
		<para>You will probably want to move your files into your <emphasis>Home folder</emphasis>. It is considered good practice to store <emphasis>all</emphasis> of your personal files (such as documents, pictures, music and the like) in your Home folder. Then, they are all in one easily-accessed location.</para>
		<para>To access your Home folder, press &home-folder;. You can create new folders inside your Home folder by pressing <menuchoice><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Create Folder</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. You may find it useful to create folders for different types of files, such as music and photos. This will help to keep things organized and you will be able to find your files more quickly and easily if they are categorized in this manner.</para>
		<para>How you copy your files from Windows into your Home folder will depend on how you decided to store your files from Windows. See <xref linkend="preparing-storage"/> for more information on this. However you decided to store your files, the procedure for transferring them across is very simple. For a CD or DVD for example, you would use the following procedure:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Insert the disc into the disc drive of your computer. After a short while, a disc icon should appear on your <filename>desktop</filename>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Double-click the icon to view the contents of the disc.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Ensure that your Home folder is open in another window. You can open your Home folder by clicking <menuchoice><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>New Window</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>In the window corresponding to the disc you inserted, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Select All</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. This will select all of the contents of the disc.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Copy</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to make a copy of all of the selected files.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>In the window corresponding to your Home folder, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Edit</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Paste</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to copy all of the files to your Home folder. If you have many files, this may take a long time.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Once the copying process has finished, your files will be available to use as normal.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<sect2 id="md-files-photos">
			<title>Importing Photos</title>
			<para>Ubuntu includes the <application>F-Spot Photo Manager</application>, which you can use to organize all of your photos.</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Open your Home folder and create a new folder called <emphasis>Photos</emphasis>. You can do this by pressing <menuchoice><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Create Folder</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Copy any photos you have into the folder you just created.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Press &f-spot; to start <application>F-Spot</application>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>The <application>Import</application> screen should be shown. If it is not, press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Import...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to show it.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>To prevent two copies of your photos from being stored, un-check the <guilabel>Copy file to the Photos folder</guilabel>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>From <guilabel>Import source</guilabel> select the option <guilabel>Select Folder</guilabel>. Select the <filename>Photos</filename> folder in your Home folder by clicking it once.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Press <guibutton>Import</guibutton> to start the import process. Depending on how many photos you have, this may take a while.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="md-files-music">
			<title>Importing Music</title>
			<para>Another useful application installed by default in Ubuntu is the <application>Rhythmbox Music Player</application>. This allows you to organize and play all of your music.</para>
			<orderedlist>
				<listitem><para>Open your Home folder and create a new folder called <emphasis>Music</emphasis>. You can do this by pressing <menuchoice><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Create Folder</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Copy any music files you have into the folder you just created.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Press &rhythmbox; to start <application>Rhythmbox</application>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Music</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Import Folder...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to begin importing your music. The <application>Import Folder into Library</application> screen will appear.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>Click the <filename>Music</filename> folder in your Home folder in order to select it, and then press <guibutton>Open</guibutton> to import all playable music in that folder into <application>Rhythmbox</application>.</para></listitem>
				<listitem><para>The import process may take a while depending on how many music files you have. Once finished, you can organize and play your music using <application>Rhythmbox</application>.</para></listitem>
			</orderedlist>
			<para><application>Rhythmbox</application> will alert you if it encounters a file it cannot play. In this case, it is likely that the file cannot be played because support for the audio format it uses is not currently installed. See <xref linkend="preparing-converting-audio"/> for more information on this.</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="md-emails">
		<title>Emails</title>
		<para>If you saved your emails from Windows, you may now want to import them into the <application>Evolution</application> mail client. The following instructions assume that you are importing emails exported using <application>Mozilla Thunderbird</application>, as described in <xref linkend="preparing-email-import"/>:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Start <application>Evolution</application> by pressing &evolution-mail;.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Import...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to start the <application>Evolution Import Assistant</application>. Then, press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Select <guilabel>Import a single file</guilabel> and then press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Press <guibutton>Browse...</guibutton>, locate the folder which you saved your emails into and open it.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Open the folder <filename>Local Folders</filename> and look for files with names such as <filename>Inbox</filename>. Select a file and press <guibutton>Open</guibutton>. If you have many email messages, you may have to wait a while for the file to be checked before you can continue.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>In <guilabel>File type</guilabel>, <guilabel>Berkeley mailbox (mbox)</guilabel> should be selected. Press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Select the location you would like to copy the saved emails into by pressing the button labelled <guilabel>Destination folder</guilabel>. By default this will be the <filename>Inbox</filename> folder, which is the recommended destination for your emails. Then, press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Press <guibutton>Import</guibutton> to import your email messages. If you have a large number of emails, then the import process may take a while. Once importing has finished, your emails should be available for viewing immediately.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="md-contacts" status="review">
		<title>Contacts/Address Book</title>
		<para>If you saved your address book from Windows, you can now import your contacts into <application>Evolution</application>. The following instructions assume that you are importing the address book from <application>Microsoft Outlook Express 6</application> or <application>Microsoft Outlook 2002</application>:</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Start <application>Evolution</application> by pressing &evolution-mail;.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Import...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to start the <application>Evolution Import Assistant</application>. Then, press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Select <guilabel>Import a single file</guilabel> and then press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Press <guibutton>Browse...</guibutton>, locate the file which you saved your address book into and select it. Press <guibutton>Open</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>From <guilabel>File type</guilabel>, select <guilabel>VCard (.vcf, .gcrd)</guilabel> or <guilabel>Outlook CSV or Tab (.csv, .tab)</guilabel>, depending on which format you saved your address book into. Press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Choose a location in which to save the contacts, such as <menuchoice><guimenuitem>On This Computer</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Personal</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.Press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Press <guibutton>Import</guibutton> to import the contacts into <application>Evolution</application>. Once importing has completed, the imported contacts should be immediately available.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="md-calendar" status="review">
		<title>Calendar</title>
		<para>If you saved a calendar from Windows, you can now import it into <application>Evolution</application>, the default calendar application.</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Start <application>Evolution</application> by pressing &evolution-mail;.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Import...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to start the <application>Evolution Import Assistant</application>. Then, press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Select <guilabel>Import a single file</guilabel> and then press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Press <guibutton>Browse...</guibutton>, locate the file which you saved your calendar into and select it. Press <guibutton>Open</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>From <guilabel>File type</guilabel>, select <guilabel>vCalendar files (.vcf)</guilabel>, <guilabel>iCalendar files (.ics)</guilabel> or <guilabel>Outlook CSV or Tab (.csv, .tab)</guilabel>, depending on which format you saved your calendar into. Press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Choose a location in which to save the calendar, such as <menuchoice><guimenuitem>On This Computer</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Personal</guimenuitem></menuchoice>. Ensure that <guilabel>Appointments and Meetings</guilabel> is selected and then press <guibutton>Forward</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Press <guibutton>Import</guibutton> to import the calendar into <application>Evolution</application>. Once importing has completed, the new calendar should be immediately available.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="md-bookmarks">
		<title>Browser Bookmarks/Favorites</title>
		<para>If you saved the list of favorite web pages from the browser you used on Windows, you can now import them into the web browser available with Ubuntu. The following instructions are intended for users of the default <application>Firefox Web Browser</application> who are importing their favorites from <application>Microsoft Internet Explorer 6</application>. Please see <xref linkend="preparing-bookmarks"/> for more information.</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem><para>Press &firefox; to start the <application>Firefox Web Browser</application>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>Bookmarks</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Manage Bookmarks...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> to launch the <application>Bookmark Manager</application>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Press <menuchoice><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Import...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and choose the <guilabel>From File</guilabel> option, then press <guibutton>Next</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Find and select the file which you originally exported from <application>Internet Explorer</application> (see <xref linkend="preparing-bookmarks"/>) and press <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para></listitem>
			<listitem><para>Your list of favorite web pages should be imported into <application>Firefox</application>.</para></listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
